<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-04-25T22:27:57-04:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/feed.xml</id><title type="html">tallcoleman</title><subtitle>A Blog on Politics, Nature, and Culture
</subtitle><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><entry><title type="html">A Google Docs Word Counter for Grant Writers</title><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/programming/2021/04/25/a-google-docs-word-counter-for-grant-writers.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Google Docs Word Counter for Grant Writers" /><published>2021-04-25T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-04-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/programming/2021/04/25/a-google-docs-word-counter-for-grant-writers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tallcoleman.me/programming/2021/04/25/a-google-docs-word-counter-for-grant-writers.html">&lt;p&gt;My girlfriend uses Scrivener for fiction writing, and I was recently checking out the features again because miraculously, Scrivener 3 was finally released for Windows and she bought it. (This is a big deal - Scrivener 3 for Mac came out in 2017 and there were times when it seemed like a Windows version might never ship.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scrivener is designed really well for solo writing, but when it comes to collaborative writing and commenting, Google Docs is much, much better. This makes it ideal for grant writing, and I’ve had very few complaints using Google Docs as my main writing tool. However, there is one feature from Scrivener that would be really nice to have for grant writing: a way of setting a word count and word limit for each question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/Scrivener Example.png&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot of the Scrivener application showing sections with word count targets&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Scrivener’s outline view allows you to get a quick overview of how your writing is coming along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good thing about Google Apps is that is has pretty extensive scripting support, so I was able to make a script to create wordcounts for each section in a document. You can find the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/tallcoleman/heading-word-counter&quot;&gt;script and its instructions on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, but I also made a quick demonstration video:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;video controls=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;&gt;&lt;source src=&quot;/assets/Videos/exampleclip.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/video&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, you can put a word limit in parentheses in the heading, and it will add and update a word count within the parentheses as well. I also added some colouring of the word count to serve as a quick visual indicator of how close you are to the limit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that’s a bit frustrating is that, unlike in Google Sheets, there’s no trigger you can set up in Google Docs to run the script after you make an edit. So the best I was able to do for now is to provide a menu to run the script on command; in addition, the script will run on a time trigger every minute. (Once per minute is as often as Apps Script allows).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the trigger limitations, it works pretty well, and I’m going to try using it and try to make additional refinements over time. I’m also going to dig deeper into different word count algorithms so that I can make sure the word count used in the script handles some of the odd edge cases in the same way that Google Docs does. I’ve also encountered some cases where grant portals count words slightly differently than google docs, and it would be interesting to try to figure out why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re looking for a session word count target as a writing motivator (another well-loved Scrivener feature), you can check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://workspace.google.com/marketplace/app/word_counter_max_for_google_docs/364683295233?hl=en&amp;amp;pann=docs_addon_widget&quot;&gt;Word Counter Max add-on&lt;/a&gt;, which looks like it would also be a pretty useful tool for grant writers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><category term="Programming" /><summary type="html">My girlfriend uses Scrivener for fiction writing, and I was recently checking out the features again because miraculously, Scrivener 3 was finally released for Windows and she bought it. (This is a big deal - Scrivener 3 for Mac came out in 2017 and there were times when it seemed like a Windows version might never ship.)</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Deep Dive: Composer Representation in Apple Music Classical Playlists</title><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/03/01/deep-dive-apple-music.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deep Dive: Composer Representation in Apple Music Classical Playlists" /><published>2021-03-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-03-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/03/01/deep-dive-apple-music</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/03/01/deep-dive-apple-music.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-deep-dive&quot;&gt;The Deep Dive&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal for this blog series was to write about ways to explore and enjoy orchestral music. So, as part of going over the Spotify and Apple Music stats in detail, I wanted to highlight the small number of composers in each playlist that were women, Black, Indigenous, and/or people of colour. This way, you can discover more about them and get to know their music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a really interesting range of artists featured on both streaming services, ranging from composers from as early as the 17th century to some modern musicians who have built careers in and around the streaming platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;using-201920-orchestra-seasons-as-a-benchmark&quot;&gt;Using 2019/20 orchestra seasons as a benchmark&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To provide a benchmark, each playlist below is compared to a hypothetical playlist where the number of composers who are women; Black, Indigenous, or people of colour; or both is proportional to how often these composers are programmed by the average US orchestra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This “average US orchestra” calculation is based on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.composerdiversity.com/orchestra-seasons&quot;&gt;2019/20 season analysis of 120 US orchestras from the Institute for Composer Diversity&lt;/a&gt;. The ICD analysis found that only 7.9% of works on mainstage programs were by women composers, and only 5.6% were by composers from underrepresented racial, ethnic, or cultural heritages. A full summary of their findings is included in the table below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Full ICD List&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;“Top 21” from ICD List &lt;a class=&quot;annotation-link&quot;&gt;*&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Orchestras&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;120&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;21&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Works Programmed&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;4075&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;1490&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Women&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;321 (7.9%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;104 (7.0%)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;BIPOC &lt;a class=&quot;annotation-link&quot;&gt;**&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;236 (5.8%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;67 (4.5%)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;BIPOC Women&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;77 (1.9%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;24 (1.6%)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Living&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;658 (16.1%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;241 (16.2%)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;annotation&quot;&gt;This subgroup of 21 of the largest US orchestras will come up later when I talk about the ICD analysis in more detail. It is the original group analyzed by the Baltimore Symphony for the 2014/15 season and the group that has continued to be analyzed by Women’s Philharmonic Advocacy from 2016/17 to the present.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;annotation&quot;&gt;The designation used by the Institute for Composer Diversity is “Composers from Underrepresented Racial, Ethnic, or Cultural Heritages”. My understanding is that this comprises composers who are Black, Indigenous, or people of colour.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#methodology&quot;&gt;More information about the methodology behind these numbers.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- Needs some fiddling with the CSS to make it work (e.g. H2 adds its own padding under the heading div) --&gt;
&lt;!-- also needs inclusion of footer; add to post template --&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;panel panel-warning&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;panel-warning panel-heading&quot;&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Labels for Composers who are Black, Indigenous, or People of Colour&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Since the intention of the BIPOC acronym is to specifically highlight the unique experiences of Black and Indigenous people, and not to be a catch-all for people who are not white, I’ve only used it in acronym form when talking about a group that includes all of the identities the acronym implies and when the acronym is warranted due to space limitations.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;When talking about a group that does not include all the identities that BIPOC implies, I’ve written out the specific identities that are included. When talking about an individual artist, I’ve tried to use their specific identity, as they describe it.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The NPR podcast &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/transcripts/918418825&quot;&gt;Code Switch had a good episode on the BIPOC acronym&lt;/a&gt; and
the various opinions people have about it.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;One important thing to note is that the labels used in the tables below only describe the specific identities of the composers actually featured in each playlist. However, the &lt;em&gt;Average US Orchestra&lt;/em&gt; numbers should always be understood to imply the potential for broader representation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;apple-music&quot;&gt;Apple Music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apple Music is often seen as a streaming platform that cares more about the experience of classical music listeners. Their app does a better job of displaying pieces of music that have multiple movements, and their metadata is more suited to the genre. Unlike Spotify, &lt;a href=&quot;/exploring-orchestral-music-methodology/streaming-service-demographic-analysis.html#analysis&quot;&gt;they have a pretty reliable “composer” field for most tracks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this increased attention to the genre hasn’t resulted in composer representation that keeps up with the field, as you can see in the playlists examined below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;classical-essentials&quot;&gt;Classical Essentials&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Classical Essentials&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;If Average US Orchestra&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Tracks&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;101&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Women&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;3 (3.0%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;People of Colour&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Women of Colour&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Living&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;4 (4.0%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;16&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, there are no composers of colour represented on this playlist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interesting thing about all of the three women composers on this playlist is that they are partially known for having deep musical and personal relationships with another person: Fanny Mendelssohn with her brother Felix, Nadia Boulanger, with her sister Lili, and Clara Schumann with her husband Robert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;fanny-mendelssohn-string-quartet-in-e-flat-major-i-adagio-ma-non-troppo&quot;&gt;Fanny Mendelssohn: String Quartet in E-Flat Major: I. Adagio ma non troppo&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fanny_Mendelssohn&quot;&gt;Fanny Mendelssohn&lt;/a&gt; (14 November 1805 – 14 May 1847), later Fanny [Cäcilie] Mendelssohn Bartholdy and, after her marriage, Fanny Hensel, also referred to as Fanny Mendelssohn Hensel, was a German composer and pianist of the early Romantic era. Her compositions include a piano trio, a piano quartet, an orchestral overture, four cantatas, more than 125 pieces for the piano, and over 250 lieder, most of which went unpublished in her lifetime. Although praised for her piano technique, she rarely gave public performances outside her family circle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first movement of this string quartet is really good - I see why they chose it for the playlist. Apparently she never formally learned to play any string instruments, and also &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fanny_Mendelssohn#Compositions&quot;&gt;was self-deprecating about this particular piece&lt;/a&gt;, which I think is sad:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;She was also undoubtedly hampered by the fact that, unlike her brother, she had never studied or played any string instruments, experience which would have assisted her in writing chamber or orchestral works… After completing her string quartet, she wrote to Felix in 1835, “I lack the ability to sustain ideas properly and give them the needed consistency. Therefore lieder suit me best, in which, if need be, merely a pretty idea without much potential for development can suffice.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;lili-boulanger--nadia-boulanger-lux-aeterna-for-voice-harp-violin-and-cello&quot;&gt;Lili Boulanger &amp;amp; Nadia Boulanger: Lux Aeterna (For Voice, Harp, Violin And Cello)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nadia_Boulanger&quot;&gt;Juliette Nadia Boulanger&lt;/a&gt; (16 September 1887 – 22 October 1979) was a French composer, conductor, and teacher. She is notable for having taught many of the leading composers and musicians of the 20th century. She also performed occasionally as a pianist and organist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lili_Boulanger&quot;&gt;Marie-Juliette Olga “Lili” Boulanger&lt;/a&gt; (21 August 1893 – 15 March 1918) was a French composer, and the first female winner of the Prix de Rome composition prize. Her older sister was the noted composer and composition teacher Nadia Boulanger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The history of this piece is quite interesting — in an article titled &lt;em&gt;Nadia and Lili Boulanger: Sister Composers&lt;/em&gt;, Dr. Caroline Potter notes that &lt;em&gt;Lux Aeterna&lt;/em&gt; is the second version of the song; the first was &lt;em&gt;Cantique&lt;/em&gt;, a setting of a poem from a play named &lt;em&gt;Soeur Béatrice&lt;/em&gt; by Belgian playwright Maurice Maeterlinck &lt;a class=&quot;annotation-link&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;span class=&quot;annotation&quot;&gt;
Potter, Caroline. “Nadia and Lili Boulanger: Sister Composers.” The Musical Quarterly, vol. 83, no. 4, 1999, pp. 536–556. JSTOR, www.jstor.org/stable/742616. Accessed 24 Jan. 2021.
&lt;/span&gt; Dr. Potter observes that &lt;em&gt;Cantique&lt;/em&gt; is heavily influenced by Gabriel Fauré’s &lt;em&gt;Lydia&lt;/em&gt; and has very similar opening chords &lt;a class=&quot;annotation-link&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;span class=&quot;annotation&quot;&gt;
The key difference between the openings of Fauré’s &lt;em&gt;Lydia&lt;/em&gt; and Boulanger’s &lt;em&gt;Cantique&lt;/em&gt;, according to Dr. Potter, is that Fauré used the Lydian mode as a musical pun.
&lt;/span&gt; Nadia Boulanger later re-orchestrated &lt;em&gt;Cantique&lt;/em&gt; and set it to the text of the &lt;em&gt;Lux Aeterna&lt;/em&gt; for a mass commemorating Lili’s (early) death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Apple Music credits the song to both sisters, this seems to be incorrect. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2011126201.html&quot;&gt;Library of Congress credits Nadia as the sole composer&lt;/a&gt;, though it notes that she intended to have her orchestration match Lili’s &lt;em&gt;Pie Jesu&lt;/em&gt; in the reworking of the song. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.naxos.com/mainsite/blurbs_reviews.asp?item_code=8.223636&amp;amp;catNum=223636&amp;amp;filetype=About%20this%20Recording&amp;amp;language=English&quot;&gt;liner notes for the album&lt;/a&gt; note that “Since 1918, Nadia’s &lt;em&gt;Lux Aeterna&lt;/em&gt; and Lili’s &lt;em&gt;Pie Jesu&lt;/em&gt; have been sung every 15th March at a memorial Mass in Paris”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;clara-schumann-scherzo-no-2-in-c-minor-op-14&quot;&gt;Clara Schumann: Scherzo No. 2 in C Minor, Op. 14&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clara_Schumann&quot;&gt;Clara Josephine Schumann&lt;/a&gt; (née Wieck; 13 September 1819 – 20 May 1896) was a German pianist, composer and piano teacher. Regarded as one of the most distinguished pianists of the Romantic era, she exerted her influence over a 61-year concert career, changing the format and repertoire of the piano recital from displays of virtuosity to programs of serious works. She also composed solo piano pieces, a piano concerto (her Op. 7), chamber music, choral pieces, and songs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like this piece, Isata Kanneh-Mason recorded a whole &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/album/7Jt7TzZQgrMsJgI7CPyApE?si=DPiJdpJoQ-qiRhorHxMP2A&quot;&gt;album of pieces by Clara Schumann&lt;/a&gt; in 2019, including this one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;relaxing-classical&quot;&gt;Relaxing Classical&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Relaxing Classical&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;If Average US Orchestra&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Tracks&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;50&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Women&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;2 (4.0%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;People of Colour&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Women of Colour&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Living&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;2 (4.0%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, no composers of colour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While researching both of the women composers featured on this playlist, I came across the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.swedishmusicalheritage.com/&quot;&gt;Swedish Musical Heritage Website&lt;/a&gt;, which is a project initiated by The Royal Swedish Academy of Music. Thanks to this site, you can read detailed biographies for both composers and even download a lot of their sheet music for free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;helena-munktell-kleines-trio-ii-andante-espressivo&quot;&gt;Helena Munktell: Kleines Trio: II. Andante espressivo&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Helena_Munktell&quot;&gt;Helena Mathilda Munktell&lt;/a&gt; (24 November 1852 – 10 September 1919) was a Swedish composer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the &lt;a href=&quot;https://bis.se/helena-munktell-violin-sonata-dix-melodies-kleines-trio&quot;&gt;liner notes&lt;/a&gt;: “The third work on this disc is a small-scale piano trio, probably an early work and possibly composed for performance at one of the musical salons at the Munktell family home in Stockholm.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were no works by Munktell included in the League analysis of 120 US orchestra mainstage programs, however, there is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/album/7FyUzdTN1C8U1uekkOLsZU?si=su8cZTqpTtqCo16MNjNfOA&quot;&gt;2005 album of her orchestral works by the Gälve Symphony Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;. An untapped opportunity for orchestras looking to increase the number of women on the program, perhaps. Despite the fact that I spent a lot of a &lt;a href=&quot;/music/2020/12/30/exploring-orchestral-music-race-gender-representation-composers.html&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; talking about how women and people of colour should be programmed more in the back half of orchestra programs, I think her symphonic poem &lt;em&gt;Bränningar&lt;/em&gt; (Breaking Waves) would make a great opener.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.swedishmusicalheritage.com/composers/munktell-helena/&quot;&gt;Biography of Helena Munktell on Swedish Musical Heritage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;amanda-rontgen-maier-violin-sonata-in-b-minor-ii-andantino&quot;&gt;Amanda Rontgen-Maier: Violin Sonata in B Minor: II. Andantino&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amanda_R%C3%B6ntgen-Maier&quot;&gt;Amanda Röntgen-Maier&lt;/a&gt; (20 February 1853 – 15 July 1894) was a Swedish violinist and composer. She was the first female graduate in music direction from the Royal College of Music in Stockholm in 1872.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favourite fact about this Sonata, according to her biography, is that when she submitted it to the Swedish Art Music Society, one of the three men who reviewed it suggested she change the slow movement. To which she basically said “no, I like it too much the way it is”. The result: “The sonata was printed without any alterations and published in 1878.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.swedishmusicalheritage.com/composers/maier-rontgen-amanda/&quot;&gt;Biography of Amanda Röntgen-Maier on Swedish Musical Heritage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-a-list-classical&quot;&gt;The A-List: Classical&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;The A-List: Classical&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;If Average US Orchestra&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Tracks&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;51&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Women&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;2 (3.9%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Black / People of Colour&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;2 (3.9%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Women of Colour&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Living&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;5 (9.8%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I understand it, Apple Music’s “A-List” playlists are where they program new releases. The kinds of music on this playlist range from new recordings of the kinds of classical composers you might see on an orchestra program to instrumental streaming artists who primarily make their living based on placement on mood-themed playlists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of the two composers of colour that were featured on this playlist are in the latter category of musicians who have made careers primarily as streaming artists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;sofiane-pamart-san-francisco&quot;&gt;Sofiane Pamart: San Francisco&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sofiane_Pamart&quot;&gt;Sofiane Pamart&lt;/a&gt; is a French pianist, based in Paris and originally from Hellemmes in the suburbs of Lille. He is known to the French public for breaking the elitist codes of classical piano.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every track on Pamart’s &lt;em&gt;Planet Gold&lt;/em&gt; album is geographically-named, so consider this a fun way to get the thrill of travelling while staying safe at home. &lt;em&gt;San Francisco&lt;/em&gt; in particular I thought was pretty hypnotic and cinematic. It reminded me a lot of Christopher Larkin’s very popular &lt;a href=&quot;https://christopherlarkin.bandcamp.com/album/hollow-knight-original-soundtrack&quot;&gt;Hollow Knight soundtrack&lt;/a&gt;, which I think speaks to Pamart’s ability to create a strong sense of atmosphere that really fuels your imagination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;alexis-ffrench-a-time-for-giving&quot;&gt;Alexis Ffrench: A Time for Giving&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexis_Ffrench&quot;&gt;Alexis Ffrench&lt;/a&gt; (born 1970) is a British classical soul pioneer, composer, producer and pianist. Not only is Ffrench the UK’s biggest selling pianist of 2020, he has headlined London’s Royal Albert Hall, collaborated with fashion houses Miyake and Hugo Boss, played Latitude Festival, worked with Paloma Faith, composed several film scores and shares the same management team as Little Mix and Niall Horan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This reminds me of the kinds of music my mum used to play on the piano while people were coming in to church. Which makes sense in a certain way — &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.voice-online.co.uk/article/im-always-trying-retain-spirituality-my-music&quot;&gt;Alexis Ffrench often talks about how he grew up playing the organ at church and the role that spirituality has in his music&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like this song, you should also check out his &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3_YNupMR6A4&quot;&gt;performance of the Bluebird Suite with orchestra at the Classic BRIT Awards 2018&lt;/a&gt;, which also features South African singer Pretty Yende.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;streaming-artists-and-their-audience&quot;&gt;Streaming Artists and Their Audience&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Artists who have been able to make a career on streaming platforms playing classical instruments often get asked in interviews some variant of a question “how do you feel about the fact that you’re not making &lt;em&gt;serious&lt;/em&gt; classical music?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the implication is that their talent is being wasted on an audience who is primarily assumed to be writing emails while listening, other times it’s a nastier implication that they make simple, uncomplicated music with little “high art” merit. I don’t think it’s a particularly fair or meaningful question, but I do find that the variety of responses that these artists give is interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best answers seem to turn the question on its head: instead of being about “is your art valuable” (as judged by the existing gatekeepers), it becomes about the relationship each artist has with their audience, and the value that the audience gets from their music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://panm360.com/en/interviews-panm360/les-mondes-de-sofiane-pamart/&quot;&gt;Sofiane Pamart talks about this&lt;/a&gt; in a recent interview:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;How do you respond to the classical purists, who remain unconvinced?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;… The important thing is to touch, to be moved. That goes beyond the technical repertoire. That comes later. It’s interesting to understand how an artist creates, but that comes later. I’m very happy to move away from that. If it does you good to tell you that there are winks at Debussy, I’m very happy, and if you have no classical references and it makes you think of film music or something else, I’m very comfortable with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.standard.co.uk/culture/alexis-ffrench-interview-classical-music-needs-to-be-more-provocative-to-survive-a3866271.html&quot;&gt;Alexis Ffrench has a good answer too&lt;/a&gt;, I think:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Crucially, this means “breaking down perceived barriers”, therefore the power of the three-and-a-half-minute message should not be underestimated. “You can write 40-minute symphonies, but it’s more important to me to connect with people at this stage.” All of his singles on Spotify are under four minutes long and his new album is “tuneful,” despite many classical artists seeing this a “dirty word”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.standaard.be/cnt/dmf20210108_97760578?adh_i=&amp;amp;imai=&amp;amp;articlehash=CCA16B79E2A7BEBE80A47827F93058CF1FD977FAC79F5EF802575F1CBE816ED8D09D95989DDD769F6DBA00D6A10D290093FC25920ABB3BD55ECF2D337719A86D&quot;&gt;the most entertaining answer I found was from streaming artist Jef Martens&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Doesn’t it bother that the compositions you work so hard on are often listened to as background music?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;‘There are also Debussy arrangements, or pieces by Vikingur Olafsson. Just because people use them as a background doesn’t mean the music is bad. And apart from that: is one listener worth more than another? When I bring someone to a transcendental metaphysical insight with my music, I love it. And if I can help an official through his first tax check on a Monday morning, that’s fine.’
&lt;br /&gt;[Via Google Translate - the original article is in Dutch]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/11/25/arts/music/peter-gelb-met-opera.html&quot;&gt;Even Peter Gelb answers emails while listening to the Met Opera rehearse&lt;/a&gt;. That’s the great thing about music: it can be enjoyed many different ways. Sometimes it can bring joy to your life in the background, and sometimes it can be an all-encompassing artistic experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;milana-zilnik-dicembre&quot;&gt;Milana Zilnik: Dicembre&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.milana.ws/biography/&quot;&gt;Milana&lt;/a&gt; is a multi-award winning pianist, composer and singer-songwriter, who has been a performing and recording artist since her childhood. A strong lyricist and composer in her own right, Milana’s style is reminiscent of Tori Amos, Sarah McLachlan, Michael Nyman, Keith Jarret and Chick Corea. Milana enjoys playing by ear, improvising and using whatever inspires her to create her own style of playing. She is known as an adept improviser, catching melodies on the fly and expanding them into her own creations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Canadian!! I too would write sad piano music if I lived in Ottawa year-round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;amanda-rontgen-maier-violin-sonata-in-b-minor-ii-andantino-1&quot;&gt;Amanda Rontgen-Maier: Violin Sonata in B Minor: II. Andantino&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This track was &lt;a href=&quot;#amanda-rontgen-maier-violin-sonata-in-b-minor-ii-andantino&quot;&gt;also featured in Apple Music’s &lt;em&gt;Relaxing Classical&lt;/em&gt; playlist&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;classical-kids&quot;&gt;Classical Kids&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Classical Kids&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;If Average US Orchestra&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Tracks &lt;a class=&quot;annotation-link&quot;&gt;*&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;50&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Women&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;People of Colour&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Women of Colour&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Living&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;9 (18.0%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;annotation&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Of these 50, three of the tracks are nursery rhymes with no known composer, one did not have an identifiable composer listed (&lt;em&gt;Classical Piano Music for Baby Sleep&lt;/em&gt; by Baby Lullaby Academy), and one was not a piece of music, but rather an audiobook chapter read by Michael Morpurgo. These unknown composers are not omitted for the percentage calculations — &lt;a href=&quot;/exploring-orchestral-music-methodology/streaming-service-demographic-analysis.html#unknown-composers&quot;&gt;see the methodology section for more details&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theoretical underpinning of this whole exercise is “what classical music do new listeners find on streaming platforms”, and no listeners are newer than children. Pretty disappointing that this whole playlist has no women or people of colour at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, music for children has the same representation issues as music for any other audience. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.billboard.com/articles/news/awards/9506870/childrens-music-album-grammy-nominees-withdraw-lack-diversity/&quot;&gt;Billboard recently reported&lt;/a&gt; that “three of this year’s five Grammy nominees for best children’s music album asked the Recording Academy to withdraw their nominations to signal their disappointment that all the nominees in the category are white and only one is female.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;next-up-spotify&quot;&gt;Next Up: Spotify&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Spotify classical playlists were longer than those on Apple Music, and had greater representation of composers who are women and composers who are Black, Indigenous, or people of colour. So I’ll split my Spotify deep dive into two or three posts so that I can talk about all the tracks in proper detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;methodology&quot;&gt;Methodology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full methodology notes for all my music posts can be found via the &lt;a href=&quot;/exploring-orchestral-music-methodology/&quot;&gt;Main Methodology Page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Details and data for the streaming service playlists analysis can be found on the &lt;a href=&quot;/exploring-orchestral-music-methodology/streaming-service-demographic-analysis.html&quot;&gt;Streaming Analysis Methodology Page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More details about how I used the data from the Institute for Composer Diversity to create the comparison to US orchestra mainstage seasons can be found on the &lt;a href=&quot;/exploring-orchestral-music-methodology/ICD-orchestra-season-analysis.html&quot;&gt;ICD 2019/20 Season Analysis Methodology Page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><category term="Music" /><summary type="html">The Deep Dive</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Representation of Composers in Top Classical Playlists on Spotify and Apple Music</title><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/02/07/spotify-apple-music-classical-playlists-representation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Representation of Composers in Top Classical Playlists on Spotify and Apple Music" /><published>2021-02-07T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-02-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/02/07/spotify-apple-music-classical-playlists-representation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/02/07/spotify-apple-music-classical-playlists-representation.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction-the-rise-of-streaming&quot;&gt;Introduction: The Rise of Streaming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Streaming is now the primary way that most people listen to music. &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@RIAA/charting-a-path-to-musics-sustainable-success-12a5625bbc7d#8e10&quot;&gt;According to the Recording Industry Association of America&lt;/a&gt;, streaming now accounts for 79% of U.S. music industry revenues &lt;a class=&quot;annotation-link&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;annotation&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you’ve read any feature piece about the past and future of the music industry, you’ve probably seen the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.riaa.com/u-s-sales-database/&quot;&gt;RIAA’s graph of how revenue sources have changed over time&lt;/a&gt;. As someone who went to high school in the late 2000s, my favourite thing about this graph is looking at the “Era of Paying for Ringtones” between about 2005 and 2010.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Classical music has lagged behind in the overall trend towards streaming: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/news/entertainment-arts-46861984&quot;&gt;a report covered by the BBC in 2019&lt;/a&gt; showed that in the UK, CD sales were still dominant (and growing) in the classical genre. Classical streaming was much smaller as a proportion of the UK market (about a quarter of sales compared to two thirds overall) but catching up quickly. In fact, year over year growth in classical streaming was reported to be 42% compared to 33% for streaming overall. A recent article from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ludwig-van.com/toronto/2020/03/10/report-streaming-music-the-song-economy-classical-music/&quot;&gt;Ludwig van Toronto exploring the same figures in-depth&lt;/a&gt; speculated that “those figures are generally recognized to represent existing classical music lovers. Streaming is the way to get that new blood the classical music world is always looking for.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So — continuing the train of thought &lt;a href=&quot;/music/2020/12/30/exploring-orchestral-music-race-gender-representation-composers.html&quot;&gt;from my last post&lt;/a&gt; — when someone searches for “classical” in their streaming service of choice, what do they find?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they’re listening to some of the most popular classical or orchestral playlists on Spotify or Apple Music, you won’t hear many pieces by composers of colour, or women composers. In some cases you won’t hear them at all. In many cases, your chances of hearing such composers is two to three times higher at a local US symphony than it is on the top classical playlists on these major streaming platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary-classical-playlist-analysis&quot;&gt;Summary: Classical Playlist Analysis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this analysis, I examined top classical playlists — four from Apple Music, and four from Spotify — that you might find by searching “classical” or “orchestral” in each service and picking from the top results. I compared the number of composers that were women, Black, Indigenous, and people of colour in these playlists with similar numbers from the recent mainstage programs of 120 US orchestras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;us-orchestra-mainstage-seasons&quot;&gt;US Orchestra Mainstage Seasons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The comparator I’m using is from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.composerdiversity.com/orchestra-seasons&quot;&gt;Institute for Composer Diversity&lt;/a&gt;. From their 2019/20 season analysis, this is the representation of composers by number of times their pieces were programmed by orchestras:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Women&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;BIPOC&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;120 US Orchestras&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;7.9%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;5.8%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;21 “Top” US Orchestras&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;7.0%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;4.5%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;apple-music-summary&quot;&gt;Apple Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Official classical playlists on Apple Music consistently had about half the number of women composers compared to the average US orchestra mainstage season, and only their new releases playlist, &lt;em&gt;The A-List: Classical&lt;/em&gt;, had any pieces by composers of colour (one track by Sofiane Pamart and another by Alexis Ffrench). Apple Music’s &lt;em&gt;Classical Kids&lt;/em&gt; playlist in particular exclusively featured white men composers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Apple Music Playlist&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Women&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Black / POC&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Classical Essentials&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;3.0%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;none&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Relaxing Classical&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;4.0%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;none&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;The A-List: Classical&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;3.9%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;3.9%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Classical Kids&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;none&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;none&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full figures and composer details for Apple Music playlists can be found in the &lt;a href=&quot;/music/2021/03/01/deep-dive-apple-music.html&quot;&gt;Apple Music Deep Dive post&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spotify-summary&quot;&gt;Spotify&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spotify’s classical playlists were slightly better, but still lagged US orchestras in representation. Most of their playlists had — at best — about half the number of women composers or composers of colour compared to the average US orchestra mainstage season. The one exception was Spotify’s &lt;em&gt;Classical New Releases&lt;/em&gt; playlist, which had nearly comparable representation of women composers, and slightly greater representation of composers of colour. &lt;em&gt;Classical New Releases&lt;/em&gt; also holds the distinction of having the only track written by an Indigenous composer (Yorta Yorta woman Deborah Cheetham).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Spotify Playlist&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Women&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;BIPOC&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Classical Essentials&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;4.1%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;1.7%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Classical Sleep&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;4.2%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;2.8%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Classical New Releases&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;6.4%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;8.6%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Orchestra 100: Spotify Picks&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;2.0%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;2.0%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full figures and composer details for Spotify playlists to come in a future post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-what&quot;&gt;So What?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of these platforms have made repeated commitments to improve representation of women and people of colour on their platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After mass protests in response to racism and police brutality, in particular the police killings of George Floyd, Ahmaud Arbery, and Breonna Taylor, &lt;a href=&quot;https://newsroom.spotify.com/2020-06-01/spotify-stands-with-the-black-community-in-the-fight-against-racism-and-injustice/&quot;&gt;Spotify announced on Blackout Tuesday that it “Stands With the Black Community in the Fight Against Racism and Injustice”&lt;/a&gt;, and outlined a number of measures to amplify Black musicians and podcasts on its platform. Two weeks later, it pledged to donate USD $10 million to “organizations that are focused on the fight against racism, injustice, and inequity around the world”. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2020/6/1/21277501/spotify-blackout-tuesday-george-floyd-racism-police-brutality-violence-protest&quot;&gt;Apple Music made some similar symbolic changes to its platform&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2020/05/31/apple-ceo-tim-cook-email-to-employees-about-george-floyd.html&quot;&gt;Apple pledged to make unspecified donations to racial justice organizations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, many months later, pieces by Black composers remain scarce on classical playlists on both platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to commitments to support movements for racial justice, these platforms have also tried to position themselves as being on the vanguard of sharing the wealth of music offered by global multicuturalism. In 2018, &lt;a href=&quot;https://newsroom.spotify.com/2018-09-28/discover-hits-from-around-the-world-with-spotifys-global-cultures-initiative/&quot;&gt;Spotify launched their Global Cultures Initiative&lt;/a&gt;, “which promotes and advances culturally diverse music, surfacing hits from different countries around the world”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, just over a year later, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.musicbusinessworldwide.com/spotifys-head-of-african-music-tunde-ogundipe-leaves-service-alongside-indian-music-expert-himanshu-suri/&quot;&gt;Spotify disbanded the original Global Cultures curatorial team&lt;/a&gt;. Although they pledged to continue the initiative with “a larger, region-specific editorial team of experts”, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rollingstone.com/pro/features/spotify-global-cultures-initiative-892762/&quot;&gt;the change elicited negative reactions from many artists, as reported by Rolling Stone&lt;/a&gt;. Rolling Stone also noted that the disbanding coincided with an exodus of several high-profile curators who are people of colour, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2020/12/03/how-spotify-hopes-to-win-the-podcasting-wars.html&quot;&gt;a nearly-billion dollar shift towards podcasting&lt;/a&gt; — which has largely been to the benefit of creators and businesspeople who are white and established.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Underrepresentation of women has also been an issue on streaming platforms for many years. In 2019, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rollingstone.com/music/music-country/martina-mcbride-spotify-country-music-882401/&quot;&gt;country singer Martina McBride posted about her frustration with overwhelmingly male-dominated algorithmic recommendations&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nbcnews.com/think/opinion/country-music-radio-has-ignored-female-artists-years-we-have-ncna1137571&quot;&gt;a genre that is well known for being hostile to female artists&lt;/a&gt;. Musicologist &lt;a href=&quot;https://songdata.ca/2019/10/01/reflecting-on-spotifys-recommender-system/&quot;&gt;Dr. Jada E. Watson also found similar results when testing the algorithmic song recommendations&lt;/a&gt; for country music fans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even earlier, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thebaffler.com/latest/discover-weakly-pelly&quot;&gt;writer Liz Pelly used Spotify’s absurd “Smirnoff Equalizer” marketing campaign to show that the platform had a distinct male bias&lt;/a&gt; that was “subtly shifting us back toward a more homogenous and overtly masculine pop music culture”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I listened almost exclusively to a sampling of the most popular entries: Today’s Top Hits, New Music Friday, Rock This, Rap Caviar, Hot Country, ¡Viva Latino!, and more. Every week, for one month, I downloaded a spreadsheet of the playlist data and analyzed the gender disparity. In the interest of not misgendering artists on the basis of their appearance or sound, I focused on confirming how artists self-identify on their Spotify “about” pages or other verified bios.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The result of this experiment: I found Spotify’s most popular and visible playlists to be staggeringly male-dominated. Not only this, I approached the project by listening from a brand new account in order to confirm that gender bias would be reproduced by way of algorithmic recommendations—that when a user listens to mostly male-dominated playlists, what is produced are yet more male-dominated playlists. Indeed, the sexist music industry status quo is upheld widely by Spotify, even as the platform exploits the woke optics of playlists like Feminist Friday and advertising schemes like the Smirnoff Equalizer to further benefit its brand recognition and bottom line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all likelihood, human–algorithmic curation that reinforces bias against cis women is even more inhospitable for trans and non-binary musicians. Despite looking through hundreds of songs, Liz Pelly reported that she “encountered no artists on Spotify’s top playlists who did not identify as a man or woman”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the platforms could argue that classical music is such a small niche that it’s just been overlooked by their efforts to feature diverse artists. Or that the lack of representation in their playlists reflects a lack of representation in a historically-white genre. But neither of these reactions would hold up to much scrutiny. Wouldn’t a genuine commitment to diversity be reflected in all curatorial decisions; in official playlists of all sizes? If the genre is to blame, why do most of the playlists have at best half the number of women composers or composers of colour compared to an average US orchestra season?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;annotation-wrapper&quot;&gt;Playlist diversity compared to orchestra mainstage programming is not a hard benchmark to exceed. Most orchestras are literally-eurocentric, small-c conservative institutions. And yet, the meager steps taken by US orchestras — at least a full year before the pandemic &lt;a class=&quot;annotation-link&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;annotation&quot;&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Orchestras are known for having long planning timelines. For the 2019/20 season, conductors and soloists might have been booked two or three years ahead of their performances.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;The latest a piece could have been confirmed would have been December 2018 (maybe January 2019 at a stretch), since marketing teams then need to prepare materials for a mid-winter subscription on-sale that usually launches at least half a year in advance of the first performance.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt; — to program more composers from the likes of Florence Price, Gabriela Lena Frank, Jennifer Higdon, and Anna Clyne have put them much further ahead than the current efforts of these two tech companies &lt;a class=&quot;annotation-link&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;annotation&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The dates that tracks were added to a Spotify playlist are visible in the metadata, so we know when curatorial decisions were published:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;All of the tracks in &lt;em&gt;Classical Essentials&lt;/em&gt; were added on October 2, 2020&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The tracks in &lt;em&gt;Classical New Releases&lt;/em&gt; were added between December 18, 2020 and January 1, 2021&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;All of the tracks in &lt;em&gt;Classical Sleep&lt;/em&gt; were added on January 1, 2021&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Orchestra 100: Spotify Picks&lt;/em&gt; by contrast, hasn’t been actively curated since 2017; most of the tracks were added in May of 2016&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Apple Music’s metadata has “Date Modified” and “Date Added” fields, but both appear to be blank when exporting data from official playlists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to see progress in orchestra programming continue and pick up speed. If streaming platforms lived up to their diversity commitments, perhaps a new generation of audience members who discover classical composers online would act as a catalyst, demanding orchestra programs that better represent the communities that ensembles work in. As it is, these platforms are cementing the status quo; investing in unseen curators and algorithms who spend their time tending to a musical monoculture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-better-options&quot;&gt;Some Better Options&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For people looking to find ways to listen to a more diverse range of classical music composers, there are some options:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For US listeners, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.composerdiversity.com/media&quot;&gt;Institute for Composer Diversity has a partnership with Pandora&lt;/a&gt; to curate channels that feature a diverse mix of composers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Canadian listeners, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbc.ca/listen/live-radio/2-4278-tempo&quot;&gt;CBC’s &lt;em&gt;Tempo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; seems to be a good choice. There are also a number of Canadian composers who are women or people of colour featured on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://cmccanada.org/product-category/recordings/centrediscs/&quot;&gt;Canadian Music Centre’s Centredisks Label&lt;/a&gt;. (Centredisks albums are also on the major streaming services, e.g. you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/album/4YJETJz7W99jMXRlEHPWJb?si=pLfDSybqRbiSB6chYt0x4g&quot;&gt;listen to Alexina Louie’s &lt;em&gt;Take the Dog Sled&lt;/em&gt; on Spotify&lt;/a&gt;. While I’m at it, I should shill a little bit and note that you can also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yYvegcavM9k&quot;&gt;listen to her Triple Concerto&lt;/a&gt; on the TSO’s YouTube channel.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the major streaming services themselves, there are some playlists designed to specifically showcase women composers, e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/playlist/37i9dQZF1DX5hL1aT2vhMb&quot;&gt;Spotify’s &lt;em&gt;Women of Classical&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://music.apple.com/ca/playlist/women-in-classical-music/pl.03392dae73604942b02ab8e53c482ae0&quot;&gt;Apple Music’s &lt;em&gt;Women in Classical Music&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I couldn’t find official playlists on either service specifically for classical composers of colour, but you can certainly find third party playlists, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/playlist/67avQ7fZ1zvEk1RDI9C3sd?si=ydgJJhfnQ1OCiRCjv3A7Pg&quot;&gt;this playlist on Spotify made by NAXOS for Black History Month&lt;/a&gt;. I’ll also give an honourable mention to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uoftfomara.org/&quot;&gt;University of Toronto Faculty of Music Anti-Racism Alliance&lt;/a&gt; who made this &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/playlist/7KsIccKNvDyftVlxWWPEdQ?si=7d886f70c97b420b&quot;&gt;Centring BIPOC Musicians Playlist&lt;/a&gt; (It has a much broader selection of genres than orchestral/classical, but I think it’s very good).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, although the numbers of women composers and composers who are Indigenous, Black, or people of colour on streaming services are low, I researched over 650 tracks for this project &lt;a class=&quot;annotation-link&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;annotation&quot;&gt;It’s actually 666 tracks exactly, which feels very ominous. Maybe I should throw out the one track on Apple Music’s &lt;em&gt;Classical Kids&lt;/em&gt; where Michael Morpurgo just reads a book on the basis of not being music so that I can say it’s 665…&lt;/span&gt;, so the list of people who &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; represented is still fairly long and interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So those will be the next posts - doing a deep dive into the specific composers represented on the Apple Music and Spotify playlists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;methodology&quot;&gt;Methodology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full methodology notes for all my music posts can be found via the &lt;a href=&quot;/exploring-orchestral-music-methodology/&quot;&gt;Main Methodology Page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Details and data for the streaming service playlists analysis can be found on the &lt;a href=&quot;/exploring-orchestral-music-methodology/streaming-service-demographic-analysis.html&quot;&gt;Streaming Analysis Methodology Page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More details about how I used the data from the Institute for Composer Diversity to create the comparison to US orchestra mainstage seasons can be found on the &lt;a href=&quot;/exploring-orchestral-music-methodology/ICD-orchestra-season-analysis.html&quot;&gt;ICD 2019/20 Season Analysis Methodology Page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><category term="Music" /><summary type="html">Introduction: The Rise of Streaming</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Exploring Orchestral Music: Race and Gender Representation of Composers</title><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/music/2020/12/30/exploring-orchestral-music-race-gender-representation-composers.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exploring Orchestral Music: Race and Gender Representation of Composers" /><published>2020-12-30T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-12-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/music/2020/12/30/exploring-orchestral-music-race-gender-representation-composers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tallcoleman.me/music/2020/12/30/exploring-orchestral-music-race-gender-representation-composers.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In thinking about creative ways that people can explore orchestral music and find new pieces that they like, I’ve been thinking a lot about representation. There are many good pieces written by composers who don’t fit the stereotype of dead white men, and I want to make sure they are prominently featured in my posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some cases, this means exploring the work of living composers, since opportunities for women composers and composers of colour are marginally better now than in previous centuries. In other cases, it means exploring composers from history who are recently being “rediscovered”. Sometimes the rediscovery is literal, as in the case of Florence Price’s fourth symphony, written in 1945, where the manuscript was found in 2009 during a renovation of what used to be her summer home
&lt;a class=&quot;annotation-link&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;annotation&quot;&gt;See: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2018/02/05/the-rediscovery-of-florence-price&quot;&gt;New Yorker Magazine: “The Rediscovery of Florence Price”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.
Other times, the rediscovery is more of a re-examination, such as appreciating Clara Schumann as a talented composer and performer in her own right, and not just a footnote to her husband’s legacy
&lt;a class=&quot;annotation-link&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;annotation&quot;&gt;See: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/08/28/arts/music/clara-schumann.html&quot;&gt;New York Times: “Clara Schumann, Music’s Unsung Renaissance Woman”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking about race and gender representation is an interesting way to look at music, but it also leads us into other interesting trains of thought. Exploring new music naturally leads us to thinking about the curators—visible and invisible—that select music, promote it, and make it easy to find. It’s also an interesting way to think about the tension between honouring the past and pushing for the future; to what extent orchestras should spend their time acting as a living museum versus playing the work of artists on the vanguard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I hope that highlighting diverse composers for people who want to get into orchestral music helps to cement change. Familiarity is essential to enjoyment and mass appeal, as noted in the 2019 book &lt;em&gt;Rockonomics&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“[T]here is a tendency for music that is popular in our networks to become more appealing to us. And bandwagon effects are further reinforced by the well-established psychological tendency for people to grow to like a particular song the more they hear it.” &lt;a class=&quot;annotation-link&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;annotation&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Krueger, Alan B. &lt;em&gt;Rockonomics: A Backstage Tour of What the Music Industry Can Teach Us about Economics and Life&lt;/em&gt;. Broadway Business, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The author cites two research papers for the last quoted sentence, which I have listed below:&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;David J. Hargreaves, “The Effects of Repetition on Liking for Music,” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Research in Music Education&lt;/em&gt; 32, no. 1 (1984): 35–47 (No public PDF link, but you should be able to get a copy if your local library has access to JSTOR.)&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Robert B. Zajonc, “Attitudinal Effects of Mere Exposure,” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Personality and Social Psychology&lt;/em&gt; 9, no. 2, pt. 2 (1968): 1–27. (&lt;a href=&quot;http://web.mit.edu/curhan/www/docs/Articles/biases/9_J_Personality_Social_Psychology_1_%28Zajonc%29.pdf&quot;&gt;Link to PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, the more that people discover, listen to, and enjoy the work of composers who are people of colour, women, or both, the more that these composers will be given their rightful stature in the “canon” of orchestral music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;research-on-composer-representation-in-orchestra-seasons&quot;&gt;Research on composer representation in orchestra seasons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to some of my own research, I have been looking at existing research that has been done on the representation of composers within orchestra seasons (primarily for orchestras in the United States). I’ve included a list at the &lt;a href=&quot;#appendix-analyses-of-orchestra-seasons&quot;&gt;end of this post&lt;/a&gt; as an appendix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of these analyses highlight the lack of women composers, composers of colour, or both, who are programmed in orchestra seasons. The good news is that some progress is being made — for example, among the biggest US orchestras, representation of women composers has more than tripled in the last five years (more on this later). However, there is still a long way to go — the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.composerdiversity.com/orchestra-seasons&quot;&gt;2019/20 season analysis of 120 US orchestras from the Institute for Composer Diversity&lt;/a&gt; found that only 8% of works performed were by women composers, and only 6% were by composers from underrepresented racial, ethnic, or cultural heritages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;not-just-who-also-how&quot;&gt;Not just &lt;em&gt;who&lt;/em&gt;: also &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To complement the quantitative information from the various season analyses mentioned above, I want to introduce two other interesting ways to dig deeper into how composers are represented in orchestra programs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;duration-and-placement&quot;&gt;Duration and placement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common format for an orchestral concert looks something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A short feature piece, maybe about 10-15 minutes long&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A medium-length piece, usually a concerto &lt;a class=&quot;annotation-link&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;annotation&quot;&gt;A concerto is a piece of music that showcases a soloist, e.g. a pianist or violinist.&lt;/span&gt; or a short symphony&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A long piece, usually a symphony or some other multi-movement work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see this pretty clearly in the format of MasterWorks &lt;a class=&quot;annotation-link&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;annotation&quot;&gt;The TSO’s MasterWorks series is what you might call the orchestra’s “core classical” program. The TSO also has pops concerts, school and youth concerts, film concerts, and other special events. Most of the season analyses I’ve linked to in the appendix only focus on core classical concerts for artistic and logistical reasons.&lt;/span&gt; concerts from the TSO’s last season:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/MW Concerts Format 19-20 with legend.png&quot; alt=&quot;Visualization showing the length of pieces in Toronto Symphony MasterWorks Concerts&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;A visual summary of the duration
&lt;a class=&quot;annotation-link&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;annotation&quot;&gt;It’s interesting to note that the median total length of pieces + intermission for these programs is about 100 minutes, which is very close to the average movie runtime in recent decades (For more on movies, see this interesting &lt;a href=&quot;https://towardsdatascience.com/are-new-movies-longer-than-they-were-10hh20-50-year-ago-a35356b2ca5b&quot;&gt;analysis of movie runtimes done by Przemysław Jarząbek on the Toward Data Science blog&lt;/a&gt;.) In reality, I would guess the median concert runtime is probably about 110 minutes due to stage resets between pieces, introductions, etc.&lt;/span&gt;
and placement of pieces in TSO MasterWorks concerts planned for the 2019/20 season. Rows represent individual concert programs, with each piece colour-coded by type. The large uncoloured gaps represent intermissions. Concerts have been ordered by onset of intermission for visual clarity. &lt;a class=&quot;annotation-link&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;annotation&quot;&gt;Source: Concert programs for 2019/20 Toronto Symphony Orchestra MasterWorks concerts. Due to COVID-19, not all of these concerts actually happened—about a third of them were cancelled.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the time, pieces by living composers get put into the “short feature piece” slot. I’m don’t know for sure why this is, so I can only speculate. Maybe this is because writing or commissioning new music for orchestra involves a lot of expense and effort, so long pieces written by living composers are rarer. Another potential reason is the fact that orchestra concerts themselves are expensive to produce, so it’s risky to bet your biggest piece on something audiences don’t already know and love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A slightly more cynical take would be that, for some people, new music has a reputation of being hard to listen to, so keeping it short and early in the program makes concerts tolerable for audience members who don’t like abstract or atonal music that much. The Baltimore Symphony has a good &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bsomusic.org/stories/reconsidering-our-assumptions-about-new-music/&quot;&gt;blog post about the reputation that “new music” has with audiences&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, it’s notable when works by a composer of colour, or a woman composer (or honestly, a living composer) takes the longest spot on the program. In fact, the Institute for Composer Diversity &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.composerdiversity.com/programming&quot;&gt;specifically makes a point of recommending&lt;/a&gt; that Orchestras “Include more substantial works by composers from underrepresented groups in the second or third positions on the program.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;representation-in-marketing-materials&quot;&gt;Representation in marketing materials&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marketing focus is also an interesting way to think about programming, and is reflected in the title of a concert program, its description, and the images used to sell it. My guess is that in most orchestras, the names and descriptions for concert programs are primarily written by the marketing department, with some input from the artistic staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concerts are most commonly named after the most well-known piece on the program, the featured soloist or conductor, or some combination of both. It’s very rare for a concert program title to be based on a living composer, unless it’s a Pops Concert (e.g. “Music of John Williams”). It’s notable when this occasionally happens, since it signifies an intentional artistic decision or that the living composer is popular enough that their name will sell tickets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Women’s Philharmonic Advocacy had some &lt;a href=&quot;https://wophil.org/2017-18-season-by-the-numbers/?doing_wp_cron=1609128744.0469379425048828125000&quot;&gt;good notes on this subject in their 2017/18 season analysis&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is worth noting that even though these works are being performed, they are not necessarily being recognized or promoted.  There were disturbingly few mentions of works by women in the online or print descriptions of each concert, even when the included work was commissioned.  For example, the Seattle Symphony has included Lili Boulanger’s &lt;em&gt;D’un matin de printemps&lt;/em&gt; for a program titled Rachmaninov Symphony No. 3, taking place in February.  The other works on the program include Elgar’s Violin Concerto and, of course, the Rachmaninov Symphony.  The description for the event, however, only mentions two of the three[.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you may have guessed, Boulanger’s piece is the one out of the three not mentioned in the concert description—and this is only one out of four examples WPA included of women composers being ignored in marketing materials. (I would highly encourage you to go &lt;a href=&quot;https://wophil.org/2017-18-season-by-the-numbers/?doing_wp_cron=1609128744.0469379425048828125000&quot;&gt;read the whole post&lt;/a&gt; - it’s very good.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;up-next-streaming-services-and-their-classical-playlists&quot;&gt;Up next: streaming services and their classical playlists&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point I want to explore to the various season analyses that are linked below. Before that (in the next post), I’m going to use some of my own research to take a look at representation in some of the biggest classical and orchestral playlists from Spotify and Apple Music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spoiler alert: it’s not great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;appendix-analyses-of-orchestra-seasons&quot;&gt;Appendix: analyses of orchestra seasons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;panel panel-info&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;panel-info panel-heading&quot;&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Updated and Expanded Version of This List&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’ve since expanded this list into its own page with additional studies and commentary. You can &lt;a href=&quot;/exploring-orchestral-music-methodology/analyses-of-orchestra-seasons.html&quot;&gt;view the expanded version of this list here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bsomusic.org/stories/all-stories&quot;&gt;Baltimore Symphony Orchestra&lt;/a&gt; had a series called “By the Numbers” analyzing the concert seasons of top US orchestras:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bsomusic.org/stories/the-2014-15-orchestra-season-by-the-numbers.aspx&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Baltimore 2014/15 (22 Orchestras)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bsomusic.org/stories/what-data-tells-us-about-the-2015-16-orchestra-season.aspx&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Baltimore 2015/16 (89 Orchestras)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bsomusic.org/stories/the-data-behind-the-2016-2017-orchestra-season/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Baltimore 2016/17 (85 Orchestras)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Baltimore series stopped after three seasons, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://wophil.org/&quot;&gt;Women’s Philharmonic Advocacy&lt;/a&gt; started doing their own season analysis starting in 2016/17 with a smaller list of 21 orchestras &lt;a class=&quot;annotation-link&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;annotation&quot;&gt;I think the intention was to continue using the 21 orchestras that Baltimore had initially looked at for 2014/15, though Baltimore later added Nashville, bringing their 2014/15 number up to 22.&lt;/span&gt; as a way to highlight the lack of women composers represented in orchestra programs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://wophil.org/works-by-women-in-the-2016-2017-season/?doing_wp_cron=1609362368.6617569923400878906250&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;WPA 2016/17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://wophil.org/2017-18-season-by-the-numbers/?doing_wp_cron=1609128744.0469379425048828125000&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;WPA 2017/18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://wophil.org/2018-19-season-by-the-numbers/?doing_wp_cron=1609129077.7042410373687744140625&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;WPA 2018/19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://wophil.org/2019-2020-season-by-the-numbers/?doing_wp_cron=1609129530.1376090049743652343750&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;WPA 2019/20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another organization, called DONNE, &lt;a href=&quot;https://donne-uk.org/orchestras-research/&quot;&gt;has been doing similar analysis for a more global set of 15 orchestras&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://donne-uk.org/2018-2019/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;DONNE 2018/19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://donne-uk.org/2019-2020/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;DONNE 2019/20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DONNE also has a research page with links to other studies on representation in music, including &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.presencecompositrices.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/06/Bilan-Novembre-2019-_OBSERVER.pdf&quot;&gt;one on (mostly-classical) French music festivals&lt;/a&gt;, which I have put on my reading list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most recently, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.composerdiversity.com/&quot;&gt;Institute for Composer Diversity&lt;/a&gt; was founded within the School of Music at the State University of New York at Fredonia. They published an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.composerdiversity.com/orchestra-seasons&quot;&gt;analysis of Orchestra Seasons for 2019/20&lt;/a&gt; that includes data from 120 orchestras. Their analysis looks at representation of composers from underrepresented racial, ethnic, or cultural heritages in addition to gender.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><category term="Music" /><summary type="html">Introduction</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Exploring Orchestral Music via a Favourite Instrument</title><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/music/2020/12/20/exploring-orchestral-music-favourite-instrument-horn.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exploring Orchestral Music via a Favourite Instrument" /><published>2020-12-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-12-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/music/2020/12/20/exploring-orchestral-music-favourite-instrument-horn</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tallcoleman.me/music/2020/12/20/exploring-orchestral-music-favourite-instrument-horn.html">&lt;p&gt;I like Orchestral music quite a lot. I used to be in a youth orchestra, I work for an orchestra now—orchestral music plays a big role in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, lots of people find getting into orchestral music intimidating. Even I do, from time to time. So I thought I would write about some creative ways that people can explore orchestral music and find new pieces that they like. My hope is that this will be informative for people who are new to orchestral music, and interesting to people who already feel they know orchestral music pretty well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to start with the way that I found a lot of pieces I like to listen to now: by looking at pieces that feature a favourite instrument. If you’ve played an instrument, and liked it, that’s often a good way to get into music. However, even just being a fan of a certain instrument is a great way to find some music that you’ll love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pieces-with-good-french-horn-parts&quot;&gt;Pieces with good French Horn parts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I played French Horn throughout high school and into University, and this helped introduce me to a number of great pieces of orchestral music. In some cases, I learned about pieces I liked by playing them (e.g. Tchaikovsy’s sixth symphony, Bizet’s &lt;em&gt;Carmen&lt;/em&gt;), but in other cases I learned about pieces through excerpts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Excerpts are small sections from pieces that musicians have to play when they do orchestra auditions. (In most cases, they will be required to play a full piece or movement from a pieces as well). Excerpts are meant to demonstrate their ability to play a broad range of music and their skill with some of the most challenging or high-stakes parts they might encounter playing with the orchestra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, if you’re a fan of a certain instrument, looking through the pieces on an audition list is a great way to find pieces that feature some pretty amazing parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to take some top picks for French Horn, but you could do this for any instrument you’re a fan of. Just search for “favourite instrument” + “excerpts” or “favourite instrument” + “audition list” and you’ll find lots to get you started. Maybe I’ll do a couple other instruments in later posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve put links to albums on Spotify and also links to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hornsociety.org/hornexcerpts-org&quot;&gt;International Horn Society’s excerpts pages&lt;/a&gt; so that you can easily find the parts I’m talking about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script defer=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/scripts/spotifyEmbedLoader.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;panel panel-info&quot;&gt;
  &lt;h2 class=&quot;panel-heading panel-info&quot; id=&quot;embedded-spotify-players&quot;&gt;Embedded Spotify Players&lt;/h2&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you click the button below, it will load embedded Spotify players for each of the pieces described. However, you should be aware that they also load several ad-trackers and third party cookies,
    &lt;a class=&quot;annotation-link&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;annotation&quot;&gt;A more detailed description of the trackers and cookies loaded by the embedded Spotify player can be found on the
      &lt;a href=&quot;https://themarkup.org/blacklight?url=open.spotify.com&quot;&gt;Blacklight privacy inspector&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/span&gt;
 so make sure to disable third-party cookies and use a tool like
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://privacybadger.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Privacy Badger&lt;/a&gt; if you choose to use this option.&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.naxosmusiclibrary.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Naxos Music Library&lt;/a&gt; is also a great way to listen to orchestral music, and you can get free access to it through most local library systems.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;panel-footer panel-info&quot;&gt;
    &lt;button class=&quot;spotify-embed-button&quot; type=&quot;button&quot;&gt;Load Embedded Spotify Players&lt;/button&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tchaikovsky-symphony-no-5-second-movement&quot;&gt;Tchaikovsky Symphony No. 5, Second Movement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/track/6MjG7iydUWghs8xL2ddIva&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;🔗 Spotify: Chicago Symphony&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;spotify-embed&quot;&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;iframe id=&quot;iframe&quot; src=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/6MjG7iydUWghs8xL2ddIva&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;80&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; allow=&quot;encrypted-media&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt; --&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is probably one of the most beautiful French Horn solos in the orchestral repertoire. Although it doesn’t sound like it, it’s absolute murder to play since holding long, high notes without a break is a real workout for the lips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The horn player in this recording is presumably Dale Clevenger, who retired in 2013 after nearly five decades as Chicago’s principal horn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bonus-holst-the-planets-second-movement-venus-the-bringer-of-peace&quot;&gt;Bonus: Holst &lt;em&gt;The Planets&lt;/em&gt;, Second Movement “Venus, the Bringer of Peace”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/track/2voC37VwC0NcD4LME5t6sS&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;🔗 Spotify: Toronto Symphony Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;spotify-embed&quot;&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;iframe id=&quot;iframe&quot; src=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/2voC37VwC0NcD4LME5t6sS&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;80&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; allow=&quot;encrypted-media&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt; --&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another famous and incredibly serene French Horn solo. Also incredibly difficult for the same reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TSO’s principal horn is Neil Deland. Maybe it’s home team bias, but I’m always blown away by the quality of his sound and how it just totally fills the hall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mahler-symphony-no-5-first-and-third-movements&quot;&gt;Mahler Symphony No. 5, First and Third Movements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/album/6Mlx6uECLVK8v4q0zPyqdL&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;🔗 Spotify: Philadelphia Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;spotify-embed&quot;&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;iframe id=&quot;iframe&quot; src=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/embed/album/6Mlx6uECLVK8v4q0zPyqdL&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;80&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; allow=&quot;encrypted-media&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt; --&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like things to get loud, Mahler is a pretty safe bet. (One of his symphonies famously features a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dSh5I_rMr9c&quot;&gt;comically large hammer&lt;/a&gt; as an instrument.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good horn parts are everywhere in this one, including in:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hornsociety.org/mahler/mahler5#excerpt-1&quot;&gt;The opening fanfare&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hornsociety.org/mahler/mahler5#excerpt-2&quot;&gt;A scale, but dramatic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hornsociety.org/mahler/mahler5#excerpt-3&quot;&gt;The happy part in-between all the turmoil&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hornsociety.org/mahler/mahler5#excerpt-4&quot;&gt;The part where four horn players have to play the same loud note in tune (just after 1:00 in the linked clips)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;annotation-link&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;annotation&quot;&gt;Most people consider French Horn to be a hard instrument to consistently play in tune because of how much the pitch can be affected by what you do with your lips and the hand that sits in the bell. These four notes are particularly difficult because they have to be played with the bell end of the horn held up in the air, which makes playing in tune even harder (no hand control and harder to keep the mouthpiece stable on your lips). The video with Sarah Willis linked below gives a good demonstration of how the hand can sometimes be used to help manage pitch.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Philadelphia’s principal horn is Jennifer Montone - she’s played on a wide range of recordings that includes her work as a soloist, in orchestras, and in chamber groups.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jenmontone.com/discography&quot;&gt;Jennifer Montone’s Discography&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bonus-strauss&quot;&gt;Bonus: Strauss&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/album/2n4AlQGkNYktJ2m5VYYdJR&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;🔗 Spotify: Philharmonia Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;spotify-embed&quot;&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;iframe id=&quot;iframe&quot; src=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/embed/album/2n4AlQGkNYktJ2m5VYYdJR&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;80&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; allow=&quot;encrypted-media&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt; --&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like fanfares and big soaring passages, you’ll probably like Strauss’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hornsociety.org/strauss/strauss-te&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Till Eulenspiegel&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hornsociety.org/strauss/strauss-eh&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ein Heldenleben&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Philharmonia’s principal horn is Nigel Black. I thought it might also be interesting to link this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SZoZLWaMYaQ&quot;&gt;video of Sarah Willis from the Berlin Philharmonic giving a demonstration of &lt;em&gt;Till Eulenspiegel&lt;/em&gt; and also a common Beethoven excerpt&lt;/a&gt;. I think it’s a good demonstration that being a good horn player often isn’t about playing things that are super complicated and fiddly, but rather playing things that often sound simple while achieving the best sound possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ravel-pavane-for-a-dead-princess&quot;&gt;Ravel: &lt;em&gt;Pavane for a Dead Princess&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/track/2DmlTLFphBLAIACKPsLAQH&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;🔗 Spotify: Orchestre Philharmonique du Luxembourg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;spotify-embed&quot;&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;iframe id=&quot;iframe&quot; src=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/2DmlTLFphBLAIACKPsLAQH&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;80&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; allow=&quot;encrypted-media&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt; --&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An all time classic. Incredibly beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This recording was conducted by the TSO’s new Music Director, Gustavo Gimeno. The horn player I would guess is OPL’s principal, Miklós Nagy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bonus-berlioz&quot;&gt;Bonus: Berlioz&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/album/1Z0qIV4ZqwzERjiWw62JRR&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;🔗 Spotify: Cleveland Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;spotify-embed&quot;&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;iframe id=&quot;iframe&quot; src=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/embed/album/1Z0qIV4ZqwzERjiWw62JRR&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;80&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; allow=&quot;encrypted-media&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt; --&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like the French, you should check out this other Cleveland Orchestra recording, which is of Berlioz’s &lt;em&gt;Symphonie fantastique&lt;/em&gt;. The principal horn on the recording is Shelly Showers, who now is part of the Philadelphia Orchestra (they’ve got some incredible horn section bench strength over there…)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it for today - the next post will be looking at ways to explore living and diverse composers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><category term="Music" /><summary type="html">I like Orchestral music quite a lot. I used to be in a youth orchestra, I work for an orchestra now—orchestral music plays a big role in my life.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">TSO Blog Post: Carmina Burana</title><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/tso/2019/05/30/tso-carmina-burana.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TSO Blog Post: Carmina Burana" /><published>2019-05-30T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/tso/2019/05/30/tso-carmina-burana</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tallcoleman.me/tso/2019/05/30/tso-carmina-burana.html">&lt;p&gt;As a grant writer, I don’t get to write for the public very often. However, the TSO needed some extra help writing web content recently, and I was incredibly lucky to have the opportunity to write about Carl Orff’s &lt;em&gt;Carmina Burana&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the surface, orchestral music seems very “proper” most of the time—art that is produced for aesthetic enjoyment and nothing else. However, orchestral music is like any other art form, and contains many examples of the political, the extreme, and the provocative. Some well-known examples would include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leck_mich_im_Arsch&quot;&gt;Mozart’s &lt;em&gt;Leck mich im Arsch&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (I am also quite fond of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7vuq9Ls2OVs&quot;&gt;Mozart’s “motivational” notes in the original score for his first Horn Concerto&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;John Adams’ various compositions, including &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doctor_Atomic&quot;&gt;an opera about the Manhattan Project&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Death_of_Klinghoffer&quot;&gt;another opera based on the 1985 Palestinian Liberation Front hijacking of a passenger liner&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Der_Ring_des_Nibelungen&quot;&gt;Wagner’s entire Ring Cycle, which heavily features an incestuous romance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a musical experience, &lt;em&gt;Carmina Burana&lt;/em&gt; is enjoyable and varied, but the fun is heightened by the fact that it is based on a historical collection of poems that are crude, satirical, and highly sexual. As a result, the source text is quite a fun read, and I enjoyed finding excerpts to feature in my blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you enjoy reading them too, in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tso.ca/coming-soon-carl-orff-carmina-burana&quot;&gt;my post about &lt;em&gt;Carmina Burana&lt;/em&gt; on the TSO website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><category term="TSO" /><summary type="html">As a grant writer, I don’t get to write for the public very often. However, the TSO needed some extra help writing web content recently, and I was incredibly lucky to have the opportunity to write about Carl Orff’s Carmina Burana.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Formatting Restrictions in Grant Portals</title><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/writing/2019/04/07/Formatting-Restrictions-in-Grant-Portals-Part-I.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Formatting Restrictions in Grant Portals" /><published>2019-04-07T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-04-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/writing/2019/04/07/Formatting-Restrictions-in-Grant-Portals-Part-I</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tallcoleman.me/writing/2019/04/07/Formatting-Restrictions-in-Grant-Portals-Part-I.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-pains-of-plaintext&quot;&gt;The Pains of Plaintext&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my biggest frustrations with grant portals is that they make writing feel primitive. Most portals only allow you to submit answers in unformatted plaintext, taking away a lot of important formatting tools that good writers use to make their text easy to read and to understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t just take my word for it: some of the things in the standard formatting toolbox come recommended by the U.S. government! At &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.plainlanguage.gov&quot;&gt;plainlanguage.gov&lt;/a&gt; you can find a whole set of guidelines about how to be a clear and effective writer. These guidelines are designed for people in government who might write a regulation, a form, or a letter that is sent out to citizens, but the advice applies to a lot of technical writing. Grant writing is no exception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a selection of some of their tips:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.plainlanguage.gov/guidelines/organize/add-useful-headings/&quot;&gt;Add useful headings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.plainlanguage.gov/guidelines/design/highlight-important-concepts/&quot;&gt;Highlight important concepts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.plainlanguage.gov/guidelines/organize/use-lists/&quot;&gt;Use lists&lt;/a&gt; (with bullets or numbers)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.plainlanguage.gov/guidelines/design/use-tables-to-make-complex-material-easier-to-understand/&quot;&gt;Use tables to make complex material easier to understand&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.plainlanguage.gov/guidelines/design/consider-using-visuals/&quot;&gt;Consider using visuals&lt;/a&gt; (such as diagrams, maps, and images)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The descriptive text for “Highlight important concepts” is particularly fun to read:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You can … add &lt;strong&gt;bold&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;em&gt;italics&lt;/em&gt; to emphasize important concepts within a particular section …. Only emphasize important information, otherwise you’ll dilute its impact.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;PUTTING EVERYTHING IN CAPITAL LETTERS IS NOT A GOOD EMPHASIS TECHNIQUE. ALTHOUGH IT MAY DRAW THE USER’S ATTENTION TO THE SECTION, IT MAKES IT HARDER TO READ. AND ONLINE, IT’S CONSIDERED SHOUTING.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On to the problems…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;organizing-complex-information-is-hard-without-headings&quot;&gt;Organizing Complex Information is Hard Without Headings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most grant applications, it’s not a huge deal that you can’t make your own headings because the application is structured for you, with headings and questions set out by the funder. However, I still find myself using headings all the time—usually in one of two cases:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;case-1---the-question-is-incredibly-long&quot;&gt;Case 1 - The Question Is Incredibly Long&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most grant application questions have word limits in the range of 100–500 words. Since a full page of single-spaced writing is usually about 500 words, this makes things very manageable, and ensures that there’s usually at least one heading on each page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there are some cases where questions can be much, much longer. In the Year 1 Canada Council for the Arts operating funding application, half of the questions are over 500 words, and the longest is a full 3,000 words, which is about &lt;em&gt;six full pages&lt;/em&gt; of text. For one question!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;case-2---the-question-has-multiple-parts&quot;&gt;Case 2 - The Question Has Multiple Parts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quite often, a question will ask you to talk about multiple things in the same answer. Take this question from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arts.on.ca/grants/general-granting-information/guide-to-operating-programs/operating-program-application-questions&quot;&gt;Ontario Arts Council operating funding application&lt;/a&gt;, for example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brief History&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Tell us about your organization, for example: the year you were founded, what you’re doing now, the communities you serve, important milestones in your development and how they have had an impact on your current programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This question has a 250-word limit, so instead of moving from topic to topic with transition sentences, you can just use simple headings instead like “Current Activities”, “Milestones”, and “Communities Served” to jump between topics without wasting words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make sure the reviewers don’t get lost in the sea of your 3,000 word answer or can follow along as you jump between different topics or time periods, you have to use headings, even though it’s not supported in plaintext. The best workaround I’ve found so far is to shout THIS IS A HEADING in all caps and put some extra space before it through judicious use of the enter key. It’s not ideal—it doesn’t help people who might use headings to navigate with a screen reader—and you can’t use bigger or smaller headings to organize your work in a sophisticated way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;you-cant-highlight-key-points-or-italicize-titles-in-plaintext&quot;&gt;You Can’t Highlight Key Points or Italicize Titles in Plaintext&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s try an experiment. Imagine you are skimming the following paragraph in an application. Where do your eyes land? How long does it take you to understand the main point of the paragraph?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Schools scoring in the top 25% of the &lt;strong&gt;Learning Opportunity Index (LOI)&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;annotation-link&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;annotation&quot;&gt;This is a real metric used by the Toronto District School Board: &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20190407190902/https://www.tdsb.on.ca/Portals/research/docs/reports/LOI2017.pdf&quot;&gt;tdsb.on.ca/Portals/research/docs/reports/LOI2017.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
 make up 40% of paid attendees, and schools in the bottom 25% only represent 10% of participants, showing that schools from lower-income neighbourhoods face barriers to attending our theatre programs. However, ABC Neighbourhood Theatre  has long run a targeted program offering complimentary tickets, with over 80% of free tickets going to schools with LOI scores in the bottom 25%. As a result, &lt;strong&gt;30% of our total attendees are from schools with LOI scores in the bottom 25%, demonstrating our commitment to serving schools that do not usually have good access to arts programs&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now skim it again without the formatting. What changes? Are you still able to figure out the main point in only a couple seconds?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Schools scoring in the top 25% of the Learning Opportunity Index (LOI) make up 40% of paid attendees, and schools in the bottom 25% only represent 10% of participants, showing that schools from lower-income neighbourhoods face barriers to attending our theatre programs. However, ABC Neighbourhood Theatre  has long run a targeted program offering complimentary tickets, with over 80% of free tickets going to schools with LOI scores in the bottom 25%. As a result, 30% of our total attendees are from schools with LOI scores in the bottom 25%, demonstrating our commitment to serving schools that do not usually have good access to arts programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you are able to put your key points in bold, you have much more flexibility to decide how to structure your writing. When you can’t use formatting for emphasis, you have to write everything like a newspaper article—main point at the top, and less important information below. The only thing you can do to help out a skim reader is to put your paragraph breaks in the right places. IT’S NOT LIKE YOU CAN PUT YOUR KEY POINTS IN ALL CAPS INSTEAD. THEN YOU JUST COME ACROSS LIKE YOU’RE SHOUTING.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-workaround-for-italics&quot;&gt;A Workaround for Italics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As someone who has mostly written grants for arts organizations, one of the most frustrating limitations of grant portals is that you can’t use italics, since they are an essential part of writing titles of artistic works like movies and pieces of music. There’s an easy workaround for this, but let me illustrate the problem first:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine that there is a composer who writes a piece for orchestra called “my deepest, most horrible fantasy”. When I write my grant, I might write a sentence like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The orchestra performed &lt;em&gt;my deepest, most horrible fantasy&lt;/em&gt; in Salzburg last spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see that the italics really help make it clear that the orchestra did not commit any crimes or heinous acts on stage in Salzburg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution is pretty simple—use single quotes instead. So in most portals, I would write:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The orchestra performed ‘my deepest, most horrible fantasy’ in Salzburg last spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only challenges I sometimes come across are communicating this convention to my editors (I usually leave a note at the top saying something like “single quotes = italics”) and catching myself when I habitually italicize things in my answers. Fortunately, searching for italicized text is &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.office.com/en-us/article/find-and-replace-text-or-formatting-in-word-for-mac-ac12f262-e3cd-439a-88a0-f5a59875dcea&quot;&gt;actually quite easy in Microsoft Word&lt;/a&gt;, so you can just look for any italics that should be single quotes before the text is uploaded into a portal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there isn’t really a good replacement for using italics as a method of emphasis. You could use some plaintext alternatives, but they *very* often look _incredibly_ odd, and -unprofessional- to many readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lists-look-ugly-and-dont-stand-out&quot;&gt;Lists Look Ugly and Don’t Stand Out&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can still have lists in plaintext. They just look messy (and maybe a bit unprofessional), because they’re not properly indented. In the case where you want to make entire paragraphs into list items, numbering or bullets don’t stand out as strongly as they should. Lists are a great way to make sure skim readers catch key information, but if you can’t make them look different than the rest of your text, then they’ll get missed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could re-write your lists into prose, but that will make them harder to read (there’s a reason listicles are so popular), it will probably increase your word count, and it won’t give you the benefit of providing some variety in the way you write your answers. The Canada Council application I mentioned earlier is about 22 pages long—can you imagine how much harder it would be to read 22 pages without the occasional list to spice things up a bit?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tables-and-spreadsheets-arent-tools-at-your-disposal&quot;&gt;Tables and Spreadsheets Aren’t Tools At Your Disposal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grant applications are mostly about summarizing, and nothing summarizes like a table. Want to give an overview of your programs, when they were established, who they are targeted to, and how many people they reach a year? Want to write out a schedule for the project you’re applying to have funded? A table summarizes multi-faceted information much more effectively and succinctly than text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not to say that tables don’t exist in grant portals—they do—but only at the funder’s discretion, not as a tool the writer can choose for themselves. Usually funder-created tables take the form of an array of text boxes, one for each table cell. In a similar vein, most applications require a budget, but when it comes to spreadsheets, most portals  either give up and ask you to upload an attachment, or force you to enter your spreadsheet data into a text box table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often these text box tables are implemented in pop-up windows (so 90’s!) and suffer from a number of user experience sins, such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;not telling you a text box has word limits until you press ‘save’,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;automatically rounding budget numbers, and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(my personal favourite) selecting all the text in a cell on the first click, making it easy to accidentally over-write everything while making edits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-graphs-and-images-are-allowed-theyre-out-of-context&quot;&gt;When Graphs and Images &lt;em&gt;Are&lt;/em&gt; Allowed, They’re Out of Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve seen a couple operating funding applications that ask something along the lines of “What are your main sources of revenue? Are they well-diversified?” The painful way to answer this question is to start with “Our greatest source of revenue is ticket sales, at 40% of the overall total…” The easy way is to just provide a pie chart and add commentary as needed. Alas, usually the pie chart is not an option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Images are also an essential communication tool for many applications. A good picture gives a more visceral idea of what a program does and who it serves. It’s one thing to read about a program that works with kids in school—it’s another to read about it and also see a picture of those kids looking excited, engaged, and deep in thought. For artists, pictures, videos, and sound recordings are a standard part of a funding application to demonstrate past works or show off a prototype of the work to be funded. In applications for capital funds, or for equipment purchases, images are essential for the funder to understand what their money is going towards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often, funders will provide an option to upload attachments to allow for images and graphs to be included. Unfortunately, this usually puts them in a separate context to the application text, like a book where all the colour photos are in a couple pages in the middle. When &lt;em&gt;Pitchfork&lt;/em&gt; writes about a pop song, they can put the music video after the paragraph where they talk about how catchy the melody is. When I write about my orchestra’s JUNO-award winning album, I have to hope the reader will remember what I wrote when they listen to the sound clip in the support material section at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;links-references-and-footnotes-arent-supported&quot;&gt;Links, References, and Footnotes Aren’t Supported&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A grant application is usually a very fact-heavy piece of writing, but unlike a research report or academic paper, detailed citations and footnotes are the exception, not the rule. Portals encourage this status quo by making it difficult to include these things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a particular shame that footnotes aren’t an option in plain-text writing. You often don’t know who is going to read your application, and jury panels usually have people with a mix of different professional experiences. Unobtrusive footnotes that are excluded from word limits could allow you to write as if your audience was someone closely familiar with your particular field, while providing the additional context they would need if they weren’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ultimate tool for increasing the optional context at your reader’s fingertips is the hyperlink. For plain text-based portals, link shorteners provide a workaround for providing links that can be copy-pasted without cluttering up a paragraph. However, they’re not as fluid as real hyperlinks, like this one linking to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20190824154934/https://pdos.csail.mit.edu/~neha/hyperlinks/main-no.html&quot;&gt;post by MIT Researcher Neha Narula about whether news articles should have more or fewer hyperlinks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion-make-clear-communication-easier&quot;&gt;Conclusion: Make Clear Communication Easier!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a concluding thought to tie all these things together, when I tell people that I’m a grant writer, people often tell me that they think grant writing is uniquely difficult, with lots of traps you need to avoid and tricks and techniques you have to know to be successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an ideal world, it wouldn’t be like this. If you assume that funders want to give funding to the best organizations and the best ideas, then that should be possible without talented grant writers. Putting barriers in the way of clear communication only benefits established organizations who have grant writers on staff. List formatting and ALL CAPS HEADINGS may be small gripes, but they matter because they contribute to a system of giving out public money that is exclusionary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you wanted to make the doling out of funds even more inclusive, you might even challenge the idea that written applications are the ideal way to assess worthiness. It’s certainly the option that’s most convenient for funders, but not necessarily the most equitable option for everyone. Perhaps a good topic for a later post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think my next post will diverge from the minutiae of formatting and talk about how the structure of some grant programs contributes to precarious employment in the arts. Until next time…&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><category term="Writing" /><summary type="html">The Pains of Plaintext</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Steps to Writing A Grant: Part II</title><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/writing/2019/03/10/Steps-to-Writing-a-Grant-Part-II.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Steps to Writing A Grant: Part II" /><published>2019-03-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-03-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/writing/2019/03/10/Steps-to-Writing-a-Grant-Part-II</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tallcoleman.me/writing/2019/03/10/Steps-to-Writing-a-Grant-Part-II.html">&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/writing/2019/03/04/Steps-to-Writing-a-Grant-Part-I.html&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt; we went through all the steps a grant writer goes through before they even type their first word. In this post, we’ll go through the rest of the steps, including typing your first word. Let’s assume that you’ve found a funding program, have done your research, and have made the decision to go for it and submit an application. What comes next?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-set-up-your-drafting-document&quot;&gt;4. Set up your drafting document&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like to live life dangerously, you could write your application right in the portal. For people who buy a cute puppy without researching food and vet costs first, or who apply makeup and/or shave while driving, this might be appealing. The rest of us usually open up our word processor of choice and get to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The frustrating part of this process is that most funders don’t provide a word doc version of their portal questions, so most grant writing starts with the dull drudgery of copy-pasting questions into a new document. I suppose some might be afraid of people who would try to apply by submitting the document in spite of any instructions saying “APPLY THROUGH THE PORTAL” in big bold text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Canada-Council-Application-Doc-Red-Text.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of a word document with application questions downloaded from the Canada Council for the Arts website.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Canada Council for the Arts is one of the few funders that will give you a word doc of the application questions. Note that they’ve made the “You must use the portal to apply” warning very big and very red.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The copy-paste process is not always straightforward either. Some portals like to trick you by implementing logic in their application forms. For example, in the Canada Summer Jobs application, there is a part where you pick skills from a list to indicate what your hired student is going to learn. For each skill that you pick in the list, a new text box pops up asking you to provide more details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you made your word doc based on the questions listed on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20190310031443/https://www.canada.ca/en/employment-social-development/services/funding/canada-summer-jobs/apply.html&quot;&gt;Canada Summer Jobs webpage&lt;/a&gt;, there isn’t really any indication that this is how the form works. If you are unlucky, you might write up your whole draft and only realize you have more writing to do at the very last minute when you’re pasting your answers into the form. I’ve seen this in Ontario Arts Council applications as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a precautionary measure, I now try and go through every question in an application form to make sure there aren’t any hidden surprises, clicking every potentially relevant drop-down in case a new text box pops up. Some forms will also check to make sure you’ve answered mandatory questions, so this sometimes requires the extra step of putting in fake answers so you can get through to the next page. While I’m doing these things, I also check how the portal formats text so that I know if it will add in automatic paragraph spacing or if I should double-press the enter key after each paragraph instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of all these foibles, grant writers have to start their work by doing a  bunch of pointless copy-pasting and playing around with the application form to make sure they’ve caught everything. It’s an incredibly frustrating waste of time, and it’s unavoidable because you need to use a proper word processor to do good grant writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if you use Word or Google Docs, here is a list of life-saving features that most grant portals don’t have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Robust spelling and grammar checking&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Track changes and comments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;File back-ups and autosave&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some kind of version control (ranging in sophistication from saving word files with “Version X” in the file name up to Google Docs’ detailed document history)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find and replace&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Space to write drafting and research notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And most importantly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ability to highlight sections that you know are badly written so that you can put off fixing them until much later&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-research-the-evaluation-criteria&quot;&gt;5. Research the evaluation criteria&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you have a nice word doc with all the application questions in it. Time to start writing, right? Wrong! Before typing anything, you should take a look at how your application will be scored. I often like to find the evaluation criteria that are relevant to each question and write out some notes about them under every question. It’s a great way to make sure your writing stays focused and to ensure that your efforts are going to result in a high-scoring application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also paste the full criteria at the top of the document in case I need to refer to it quickly. This also helps people who will later edit your work—if the first thing they read is the scoring criteria, they’ll hopefully make their edits while keeping in mind what the funder is looking for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6-start-drafting&quot;&gt;6. Start drafting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s finally time to write! I often start with a bullet point outline and type it all out into prose later, but if you just want to let your keyboard fingers fly, that’s cool too. You’re all set up, so go ahead and start writing out your answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A small tip for grant writers who want to make the world a better place: cite your sources, both internal and external. Most grant applications don’t require citations (in the arts anyway—we’ll talk more about this in a later post). However, if you add footnotes/endnotes that detail where you got a specific fact, especially when you are writing annual operating funding applications, you will be doing a big solid for the person who has your job after you leave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;7-editing&quot;&gt;7. Editing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once at least part of your application is written up, you can start sharing it with your boss, friends, coworkers, etc. to start getting feedback. It might take a while to get to this stage, and I’ve usually found that it takes around 60-70% of the total project time to get to the first full draft. If possible,  try to get there with some time to spare, because the less you rush your editors, the better feedback they’ll give you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I strongly recommend having multiple people edit your draft, if possible. That being said, don’t go too overboard, because going through multiple sets of edits can be quite time-consuming. Ideally you want a small group who collectively tick off all the following boxes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Good writers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Good copy-editors (some people can’t write a good narrative, but they can spot a grammatical error from a mile away)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At least one person who has the authority to sign off on anything you’re promising in your application&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At least one person who knows your organization/field very well&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, you should also have at least one person who isn’t an expert on your organization/field and has the same level of background knowledge as the people who will end up reviewing your application. This person will help make sure you haven’t included any jargon or skipped explaining something because you’ve incorrectly assumed it’s “obvious”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you’ve finished incorporating the edits from all your reviewers, make sure to save time to go through the whole application one more time in case there are any errors that were missed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;8-submit&quot;&gt;8. Submit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve finished the editing process and you’ve done a last check of the whole thing, it’s time to log in to the portal and upload. &lt;em&gt;Ideally&lt;/em&gt; you should submit your application with some time to spare in case you run into any issues along the way. Some portals have also been known to crash under the load of everyone submitting their applications at the last minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve pasted all your answers into the portal, uploaded your supporting material, and double-checked that all the questions in the portal are answered, take a deep breath and click “submit”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re done!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we’ve gone through the grant writing steps, we can take a deeper look at where most portals fall short. In the next post, I’m going to write boldly about formatting and underline what some of the common limitations are. It’s going to be colourful!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><category term="Writing" /><summary type="html">In the last post we went through all the steps a grant writer goes through before they even type their first word. In this post, we’ll go through the rest of the steps, including typing your first word. Let’s assume that you’ve found a funding program, have done your research, and have made the decision to go for it and submit an application. What comes next?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Steps to Writing a Grant: Part I</title><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/writing/2019/03/04/Steps-to-Writing-a-Grant-Part-I.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Steps to Writing a Grant: Part I" /><published>2019-03-04T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-03-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/writing/2019/03/04/Steps-to-Writing-a-Grant-Part-I</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tallcoleman.me/writing/2019/03/04/Steps-to-Writing-a-Grant-Part-I.html">&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/writing/2019/02/24/Grant-Portal-Limitations-Intro.html&quot;&gt;intro post&lt;/a&gt; I argued that grant portals are rarely designed to make life easier for the grant writer. But what if they were? There is a whole list of things that a grant writer has to do before they press “submit”, and grant portals can help or hinder that work at various points along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re looking for a broader overview of grants for non-profits and charities, I would highly recommend this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imaginecanada.ca/en/360/grants-101-how-guide-nonprofits&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;“grants 101” article from Imagine Canada&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to describe the steps that most grant writing projects go through. Along the way, we can imagine how portals &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; make grant writing easier, and then we’ll take a look at the reality of how they mostly don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-discover-the-funding-program&quot;&gt;1. Discover the funding program&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To state the obvious, you have to know a funding program exists in order to apply for it. Funders usually advertise and describe their funding programs on their website. However, this is a difficult task, because they have to communicate lots of different things to different people. Eligibility, for example, varies by artistic discipline and organization type, but most grant writers want to be able to quickly drill down to the programs that are meant for them or their organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most organizations try to help with this by designing their websites with detailed menus to help you find relevant programs. See, for example, the website menu for the Ontario Arts Council (OAC):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ontario-Arts-Council-Website-Menu-Taken-2019-02-23.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of the arts.on.ca website showing the navigation menu for their grant programs. It has four columns, including one for different types of activities, one for artists from different disciplines, one for artists from different priority groups, such as Artists of Colour, and a final column for general information about grants.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or the less helpful website menu for the Canada Council for the Arts (CCA):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Canada-Council-Website-Menu-Taken-2019-02-23.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of the canadacouncil.ca website showing the navigation menu for their grant programs. The grant menu includes links to each of their funding programs which only have somewhat-descriptive names, such as Engage and Sustain. There is also a second column for general information about grants.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grant portals should have an advantage here—to use a grant portal, you usually have to create a detailed profile for you or your organization. This means that the portal should already know who you are and what programs you are eligible for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some organizations, such as the Canada Council for the Arts, do take advantage of this and provide a customized list of available funding programs within their portals. Others, such as the Ontario Arts Council seemingly do not. (For example, in my OAC account registered to an incorporated non-profit, it lists the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arts.on.ca/grants/discipline/visual-arts/exhibition-assistance&quot;&gt;Exhibition Assistance&lt;/a&gt; program which explicitly does not fund non-profit corporations.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given how much a portal already knows about you, there is a lot of potential here, but it is mostly untapped. For example, most portals do not send you emails when deadlines for eligible programs are coming up, meaning that even if a portal did the work of showing you eligible programs, you would still have to log in to see it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a lot of ways, it makes sense that the potential here is ignored. Most grant writers only visit the portal when they are going to write a grant, so unless you can send customized emails, the effort would probably go un-seen. Funders might also assume that most people who have gone to the trouble of setting up a portal account are probably familiar enough with their funding programs to know which ones they are eligible for. We’ll come back to that assumption later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-find-out-more-about-the-program&quot;&gt;2. Find out more about the program&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you’ve found a program you can apply to. Is it worth it to write an application? Part of being a good grant writer is being strategic about where you commit your time and the time of other people in your organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grant writers are fundraisers, and over the course of a year they have to try to pick applications that strike a balance between getting the most funding possible and getting dependable funding that will help them meet their revenue budget. If there’s only a 10% chance an application will be successful or if it only offers a small amount of money for the time invested, it’s probably not worth the effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More importantly, grants are dangerous, because they almost always come with obligations. Picking the wrong grant could make an organization’s finances worse–for example, if a grant only funds 50% of a project’s costs, and taking it forces you to spend the other 50% from money your organization doesn’t have. The wrong grant could also contribute to mission creep, forcing your organization to work on projects that are outside its core purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To weigh all these factors, a grant writer needs to be able to answer a lot of questions about a funding program. What kinds of projects and expenses will it fund? How much funding will it offer in total? What are the obligations and work that would come with taking the funding? How long will it take to put together a good application?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That last question can be quite tricky to answer. I’ve seen some portals where you can’t see what the application form looks like until quite close to the deadline. This often happens because you’re waiting for your registration to be approved, or because the funder only makes one type of application “live” in the portal at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually funders are nice and will &lt;del&gt;hide&lt;/del&gt; provide a PDF of the application questions on their website, though these don’t always give you all the little details, like whether you can put descriptions on supporting material, or if you just have to rely on writing meaningful file names. For some reason, information like “estimated writing time”, “total question word count”, and “list of appendices required” is usually not summarized for you, so you have to make your own summary to figure out how much work it’s going to take to apply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-decide-to-apply&quot;&gt;3. Decide to apply&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once all your questions about the funding program have been answered, the grant writer can decide whether an application is worth their time. More importantly, anyone else who would be affected needs to decide that it’s worth their time too. This needs to be a &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; decision—the kind where everyone is committed to whatever is promised in the application, including the worst and best possible scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has nothing to do with grant portals. It’s just a super important part of grant writing and I wanted to mention it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a lot of work already, and we haven’t even gotten to the &lt;em&gt;writing&lt;/em&gt; part. In fact, if I were going to hire a grantwriter, I wouldn’t ask them for a writing sample from an application. I would ask them to write a one-page briefing for program staff about a funding program, the kind of document you would write up for step #3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The writing part does come next though, and I’ll go through that… in the next post.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><category term="Writing" /><summary type="html">In the intro post I argued that grant portals are rarely designed to make life easier for the grant writer. But what if they were? There is a whole list of things that a grant writer has to do before they press “submit”, and grant portals can help or hinder that work at various points along the way.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Grant Portal Limitations - Intro</title><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/writing/2019/02/24/Grant-Portal-Limitations-Intro.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Grant Portal Limitations - Intro" /><published>2019-02-24T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-02-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/writing/2019/02/24/Grant-Portal-Limitations-Intro</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tallcoleman.me/writing/2019/02/24/Grant-Portal-Limitations-Intro.html">&lt;p&gt;I strongly believe that if you have a blog, the best way to use it is to write about something incredibly specific, with the hope of enlightening or enriching the lives of the other nine people who care about that thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence my topic today: in the last several years, many government ministries and agencies who give out grants (I’ll call them “funders”) have transitioned away from using forms made in Microsoft Word or Adobe Acrobat and have started using web portals. As a grant writer, I spend a lot of time using these portals. And they generally suck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quality of most mass-market web applications creates a false sense of security. Google Docs is so consistent with saving your work that it takes effort to actually lose something you’ve written. Products like Dropbox have whole teams of user experience designers who work to ensure that their service is intuitive and easy to use. Grant Portals, on the other hand, are usually implemented by government agencies who do not have a lot of people and money to throw towards IT. If a grant portal is reasonably functional and reliable, it’s already doing well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Microsoft-Word-Canada-Council-Application.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Microsoft Word. The document being worked on is an application form for travel funding from the Canada Council for the Arts.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Microsoft Word: still the worst way to write a grant, except for all the others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the biggest problem for a grant writer is that most grant portals are not designed with them in mind. In a lot of ways, the most user-friendly grant application software is still Microsoft Word. No, grant portals are there because they are meant to make life easier for the &lt;em&gt;funder&lt;/em&gt;. It’s a lot easier to manage and sort through hundreds (or maybe even thousands) of applications if they’re in a database. It’s the same reason some employers have job application sites where you have to re-write out your resume into their online form. It makes their work simpler, at your expense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At surface level, I am going to gripe about all the things I find frustrating about grant portals. I have so many gripes, in fact, that I’ve decided to make this a multi-part series. Perhaps it will be enjoyable, cathartic reading if you too write grants. If you work for a funder, or design grant portal software, perhaps it will be useful user feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I have a loftier goal in mind. Even if you don’t write grant applications or give out grants, they are an incredibly important part of how our civil society functions. Through grant applications, government gives resources to all manner of people, companies, and non-profits. Grant applications are also one of the most common ways that government communicates with the people it gives money to and holds them accountable. The design of grant portals says a lot about who government gives priority to (and who it doesn’t) and what relationship they have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grant portals are also an interesting study in how technology shapes the way we communicate. The tools we use to communicate often change what we say, how we say it, and how it is received. I have lots of interesting examples of that to share with you later in this series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But before that… on with the gripes!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><category term="Writing" /><summary type="html">I strongly believe that if you have a blog, the best way to use it is to write about something incredibly specific, with the hope of enlightening or enriching the lives of the other nine people who care about that thing.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>