<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-10-15T21:51:16-04:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/feed.xml</id><title type="html">tallcoleman</title><subtitle>A Blog on Politics, Nature, and Culture
</subtitle><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><entry><title type="html">How to mail merge double-sided tent cards in Word</title><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/crafts/2022/10/15/mail-merge-double-sided-tent-cards.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to mail merge double-sided tent cards in Word" /><published>2022-10-15T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-10-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/crafts/2022/10/15/mail-merge-double-sided-tent-cards</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tallcoleman.me/crafts/2022/10/15/mail-merge-double-sided-tent-cards.html">&lt;p&gt;I ran into this problem at work recently and didn’t find many good explanations for how to solve it — so here you go!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine you’re organizing a banquet dinner, or some kind of formal meeting, and you need to mail merge tent cards with your attendee’s names on them. Ideally you want to be able to print their name on both sides of the card so that it’s easily visible. This is how you do it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main trick is to ignore the default template that Word or the Avery website gives you, and to make your own template, &lt;em&gt;sideways&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;instructions-two-to-a-page-tent-cards&quot;&gt;Instructions: Two-to-a-Page Tent Cards&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll use the example of two-to-a-page cards like Avery 5305 or most of the St. James Overtures cards, but there are some additional tips at the end for cards where you have one, four, or six cards on a page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;set-up&quot;&gt;Set Up&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Tent Card Table Set Up.png&quot; alt=&quot;Microsoft Word application window with a four-column table set up&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(If you’re using a different card than Avery 5305, you might want to adjust the margin measurements.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Open a new word document and set the layout to Landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Set the page margins to &lt;abbr title=&quot;inches&quot;&gt;0.5&quot;&lt;/abbr&gt; on the top and sides, and 0&quot; on the bottom. If Word complains about printable area, just select “ignore”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Insert a four-column table and set the cell dimensions to &lt;abbr title=&quot;inches&quot;&gt;2.5&quot;&lt;/abbr&gt; wide x 7.5&quot; tall. (You can leave the table borders as-is, we’ll remove them later.)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using the “Mailings” tab, select “Start Mail Merge”, and select “Labels”. Then select “Cancel”. It may seem like you’ve done nothing, but this strange ritual will put Word into the right merge mode and enable the “Update Labels” button.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Connect to your external data using “Select Recipients”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;!-- Needs some fiddling with the CSS to make it work (e.g. H2 adds its own padding under the heading div) --&gt;
&lt;!-- also needs inclusion of footer; add to post template --&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;panel panel-info&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;panel-info panel-heading&quot;&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;💡 &lt;strong&gt;Tip&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Make sure you select “Start Mail Merge” &amp;gt; “Labels” and not just the “Labels” button right next to Envelopes. Even though they both bring you to the same dialog screen, only “Start Mail Merge” &amp;gt; “Labels” puts you into labels mode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;Design&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Tent Card Finished Merge Tags.png&quot; alt=&quot;Microsoft Word application window showing merge field tags&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steps 1–4 can be done in whatever order you find easiest:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using the “Layout” tab, set the alignment for all your table cells to be centred vertically and horizontally.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Insert your merge fields in the first column.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using the “Layout” tab, change the text direction so that the text is rotated 90 degrees clockwise in columns one and three, and counter-clockwise in columns two and four. (You might need to type a little bit of text in each column to check.)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Style your text so that it looks the way you want it (I often will use the “Preview” button on the “Mailings” tab to skip through to the longest name and set the font size based on that.)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using the “Mailings” tab, select “Update Labels”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At this point, it will show a new name in each column - to fix this, delete the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;Next Record&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; merge fields in columns two and four. (You will have to turn off “Preview” if you have that on.)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Remove the borders on your table and check that everything looks the way you want it. Make sure to save your file if you haven’t done so already.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;printing&quot;&gt;Printing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Tent Card Finished Preview.png&quot; alt=&quot;Microsoft Word application window showing off a preview of the finished set up&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using the “Mailings” tab, select “Finish and Merge” and then “Edit Individual Documents”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Save the newly-generated file and check to make sure that everything merged correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At this point, it’s usually a good idea to try printing just one page to make sure you know how to correctly orient your cards in the feed tray. I usually run it through with a piece of paper that has “Top” written on the top of one side so you can figure out the correct rotation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once you’re confident that everything is set up correctly, print out your cards and have fun separating them and folding them up!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-sizes&quot;&gt;Other Sizes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have one-to-a-page cards like Avery 5309, the correct set up would be a portrait page like this, with margins of &lt;abbr title=&quot;inches&quot;&gt;0.5&quot;&lt;/abbr&gt; at the top, 0.75&quot; on the sides, and 0&quot; on the bottom; as well as table cells that are 3.5&quot; wide and 10&quot; tall:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Avery 5309 Layout Example.png&quot; alt=&quot;Microsoft Word application window showing the layout for Avery 5309&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have four-to-a-page cards like Avery 5302, it gets a bit trickier. Start by setting up a landscape page with margins of &lt;abbr title=&quot;inches&quot;&gt;0.5&quot;&lt;/abbr&gt; at the top, 1.25&quot; on the sides, and 0&quot; at the bottom. You’ll then want to a 5x3 table where the gutters, i.e. the centre column and centre row, are 0.5&quot; and the cells for each side of the card are 2&quot; wide by 3.5&quot; tall:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Avery 5302 Layout Example with Table Dimensions.png&quot; alt=&quot;Microsoft Word application window showing the table dimensions for Avery 5302&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only other step is to make sure that you delete the merge tags from the gutter cells, and delete the appropriate &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;Next Record&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tags.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Avery 5302 Layout Example with Merge Tags.png&quot; alt=&quot;Microsoft Word application window showing the merge tag layout for Avery 5302&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can use a similar approach for cards that are six-to-a-page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;troubleshooting&quot;&gt;Troubleshooting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-merged-document-doesnt-print&quot;&gt;My merged document doesn’t print&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure how common this issue is, but I’ve run into it occasionally. Try exporting the Word file to PDF and printing from Acrobat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;i-updated-my-spreadsheet-but-the-data-doesnt-show-up-when-i-preview-the-merge&quot;&gt;I updated my spreadsheet but the data doesn’t show up when I preview the merge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Close and re-open Word if you have updated your spreadsheet but the new data is not showing yet in your preview. This will force Word to re-pull the data from the spreadsheet file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;i-put-in-the-right-dimensions-for-the-table-but-after-styling-my-text-the-dimensions-have-changed&quot;&gt;I put in the right dimensions for the table, but after styling my text, the dimensions have changed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setting Layout &amp;gt; Autofit to “Fixed Column Width” might help, but in most cases, you’ll just have to re-set the table layout to the correct dimensions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The main problem is that while Word can have text oriented 90 degrees sideways in either direction, but it can’t orient text upside down. You can make upside down text using a text box, but that doesn’t seem to play well with the mail merge feature. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><category term="Crafts" /><summary type="html">I ran into this problem at work recently and didn’t find many good explanations for how to solve it — so here you go!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Experimenting with RGB Colours for Cosmo Embroidery Floss</title><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/crafts/2022/01/01/experimenting-rgb-colours-cosmo-embroidery-floss.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Experimenting with RGB Colours for Cosmo Embroidery Floss" /><published>2022-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/crafts/2022/01/01/experimenting-rgb-colours-cosmo-embroidery-floss</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tallcoleman.me/crafts/2022/01/01/experimenting-rgb-colours-cosmo-embroidery-floss.html">&lt;!-- Needs some fiddling with the CSS to make it work (e.g. H2 adds its own padding under the heading div) --&gt;
&lt;!-- also needs inclusion of footer; add to post template --&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;panel panel-primary&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;panel-primary panel-heading&quot;&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Downloadable list of Cosmo RGB and Hex Colours&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Looking for a list of RGB or Hex colours for the 2020 Cosmo embroidery floss collection? You can download it or copy the Google Sheets version here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/tallcoleman/CosmoToRGB&quot;&gt;Github: 500 colour Cosmo dataset&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the winter holiday, my girlfriend asked me to help her with the spreadsheet she uses to keep track of her embroidery floss &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/kt_vogan/&quot;&gt;check out her creations on Instagram&lt;/a&gt;). She wanted to be able to see how many of each colour she owned at a glance, and what kind of inventory she had on hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was provided with a helpful diagram:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/Embroidery_Floss_Inventory_Diagram.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Layout diagram which includes thread code, a colour box, and types of inventory on hand&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some discussion, we decided on trying to mimic the layout of the 2020 colour card &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, which looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/cosmo_colour_card_500.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Full Cosmo colour card&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal was to make an inventory dashboard with the same layout as the colour card. This all seemed easy enough, until I got to the problem of finding RGB colours for each thread…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some lists out there that will give you RGB colours for Cosmo threads, but they’re much harder to find than lists for DMC (which is a more widely-used brand). &lt;a href=&quot;https://cs-pattern.com/cosmo-list.php&quot;&gt;cs-pattern.com&lt;/a&gt; has a good list, but they only have 400 colours as a result of sampling from an older colour card, as you can see their &lt;a href=&quot;https://cs-pattern.com/viewtopic.php?f=8&amp;amp;t=234&quot;&gt;forum post&lt;/a&gt;. I later discovered that MacStitch also ships with a list of Cosmo threads, but it’s also slightly out of date and a little tricky to convert to RGB hex codes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another, worse option I tried before finding the cs-pattern list was to use a conversion chart to get an equivalent DMC thread for each Cosmo thread &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, which then allowed me to get a RGB colour from a DMC list. This filled in about half of the colours from the 2020 Cosmo colour card, leaving the other half for me to fill in manually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, none of these options worked and I ended up sampling my own Cosmo to RGB dataset from the 2020 colour card PDF using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gimp.org/&quot;&gt;GIMP&lt;/a&gt;. (Download via GitHub: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/tallcoleman/CosmoToRGB&quot;&gt;500 colour Cosmo dataset&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along the way, I learned some interesting things, which are described below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem-1-you-usually-cant-mix-data-sources&quot;&gt;Problem #1: You (usually) can’t mix data sources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I assume that most thread to RGB colour conversion charts are created by sampling an RGB colour from an image of the threads. If you use multiple data sources, it’s hard to ensure the colours are consistent: the lighting could be different between cameras/scanners and the sampling method could be different. Even differences between software might cause the colour of a single thread to vary from one dataset to another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s an example of what mixed data sources looks like, comparing a section from the full manual sample (left) with the mixed sourcing I had initially used:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/Purple-side-by-side-mixed-source.png&quot; alt=&quot;Two columns of purple colours going from lightest to darkest in each column&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Left: all manually sampled; Right: mix of DMC conversions and manual samples, with labels for data sources&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The colours pulled from converting Cosmo to DMC were lighter and pinker than the manual samples, so the mixed source sequence looks mottled instead of showing a smooth gradient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sequences where all the colours came from DMC conversion looked a little better, but still came out a little mottled:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/Pink-side-by-side-single-sources.png&quot; alt=&quot;Two columns of pink colours going from lightest to darkest in each column&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Left: all manually sampled; Right: all DMC conversions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why does this matter? Fans of Cosmo threads (including the one that lives in my apartment) say that &lt;a href=&quot;http://thecopperfox.blogspot.com/2020/04/lets-talk-about-cosmo-threads.html&quot;&gt;Cosmo threads have nice gradients&lt;/a&gt;. Each colour family has a range of options for slight variations in shade and tone, and this allows you to have very fine control over the colours used in your embroidery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To show the gradients properly in the inventory spreadsheet, I needed a colour dataset that was very precise. If the measurement of each colour varied more than the differences between neighbouring shades, then the gradient effect would be lost. As you can see in the examples above, the gradients look much better (and closer to how they look on the colour card) if you take all the colours from one consistent source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Variability between data sources is also a challenge for DMC threads, as evidenced by this spreadsheet comparing different DMC colour lists &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/DMC Comparison Spreadsheet.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of a spreadsheet with columns of DMC colours from different sources&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, lesson learned — make sure to use the same data source for consistency. And if the source you need doesn’t exist, you’ll have to make it yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem-2-whats-a-correct-rgb-colour-for-a-real-world-object&quot;&gt;Problem #2: What’s a “correct” RGB colour for a real-world object?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding an “equivalent” digital colour for a real-world object can be quite challenging. You have to contend with the difference between the additive (emitted) colour of computer screens compared to the subtractive (reflected) colour of dyed objects, monitor calibration, the colour spaces used by software, and other factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Archivists deal with some of these problems by using image targets to calibrate their scanning equipment and to assess the colour accuracy of an image. (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imagescienceassociates.com/mm5/pubs/50Arch07BurnsWilliams.pdf#page=5&quot;&gt;This journal article has an example&lt;/a&gt; on page 5.) To achieve a certain &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20211111200525/http://www.digitizationguidelines.gov/guidelines/FADGI%20Federal%20%20Agencies%20Digital%20Guidelines%20Initiative-2016%20Final_rev1.pdf&quot;&gt;archival standard&lt;/a&gt;, you have to ensure the white balance, colour accuracy, and luminance are within acceptable margins of error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my knowledge, no-one has scanned a floss colour card to archival standards, and probably won’t any time soon, since the equipment is quite expensive. But I did want to test the perceived colour accuracy of different data sources, so I set up a blind experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I randomly selected 20 threads with manually sampled and DMC conversion colours, and created blind pairs of both colour sources:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;max-width: 350px&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Colour-Test-Pairs.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pairs of coloured cells with two colour cells for each thread&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once everything was set up, I had Katrina look at each floss colour and mark down which of the two computer colours was the better match. Interestingly enough, neither data source had any huge advantage over the other in providing a more “accurate” match to the real-world object. She picked 13/20 of the manually-sampled colours as the better match, and 7/20 of the colours from DMC conversion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also tried the experiment, and had even more ambivalent results, with a 50:50 split between manual samples and DMC conversion as being the closer match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing we both noticed while doing the test was that the angle of lighting played a huge role in our perceptions of the physical thread. Cosmo thread is, for lack of a better term, shiny. As you can see from the video below, even minor changes in the angle of lighting affect how light the thread appears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;video autoplay=&quot;&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot; muted=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;&gt;
  &lt;source src=&quot;/assets/Videos/cosmo_thread_light_colour_perception.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Katrina also noted that people could have different subjective ideas of what makes a good match. One person could prioritize matching the lightness of the physical thread with the computer colour, while another could prioritize matching the hue, even if the lightness was slightly off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;miscellaneous-final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Miscellaneous Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also did some experiments with mathematical calculations of colour distance, which are pretty dull to write about. However, the math of calculating the difference between colours, &lt;em&gt;weighted to human perception&lt;/em&gt;, is kinda neat and you can read about it on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Color_difference&quot;&gt;Wikipedia page on colour difference calculations&lt;/a&gt; &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re curious about how to sample colours using GIMP, this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=p7oyUekkrVo&quot;&gt;video tutorial on the color picker tool&lt;/a&gt; does a great job of showing the basics. A couple additional tips I would share:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you detach the info window, it looks a lot better and you can move it around. I found it particularly useful to keep the info window next to the part of the image I was sampling to make sure the colour looked right compared to the source.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By adjusting the “number of columns” option, you can change the palette layout.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you click on the swatches added to a palette, you can name them. E.g. in this case you could put the thread number used by the manufacturer.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can export palettes to several different formats. Unfortunately, the “text file” format doesn’t include the names given to each swatch, so you’ll have to use one of the other formats (e.g. CSS stylesheet) if you want the names as well.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/GIMP-Palette-Options.png&quot; alt=&quot;Diagrams of the palette editing and palette export menus in GIMP&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Using the palette menus in GIMP&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Final thought — I mentioned archival digitization standards earlier in the post. If you’re interested in this kind of thing, I would glance through the document I had linked above, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20211111200525/http://www.digitizationguidelines.gov/guidelines/FADGI%20Federal%20%20Agencies%20Digital%20Guidelines%20Initiative-2016%20Final_rev1.pdf&quot;&gt;2016 Technical Guidelines for Digitizing
Cultural Heritage Materials&lt;/a&gt;. It’s incredible how much care goes into digitizing archival objects. It’s much more complicated than just having someone take regular scans of old documents!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;My understanding is that “floss” consists of six strands of thread bundled together, which you can split apart as desired. Throughout the post I’ll use “thread” and “floss” somewhat interchangeably. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A colour card is to floss what a paint chip fan deck is to paint. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I used &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.twogreenzebras.com/category/512-cosmo&quot;&gt;this chart from the Two Green Zebras shop&lt;/a&gt; in Australia and converted it into a spreadsheet using &lt;a href=&quot;https://tabula.technology/&quot;&gt;Tabula&lt;/a&gt;. I then got the DMC colours from &lt;a href=&quot;http://my.crazyartzone.com/dmc.asp&quot;&gt;crazyartzone.com&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/CrossStitch/comments/mluu4e/chat_converting_hex_codes_to_dmc/gtnpxcj/&quot;&gt;Bura510 on Reddit r/CrossStitch&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;If you want to give it a go yourself in Google Sheets, here’s a custom function you can use, based on the redmean formula from that Wikipedia page:&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;language-javascript highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cm&quot;&gt;/**
 * Compare color difference in RBG hex codes
 * @param {string} rgb1 First RGB hex color starting with #
 * @param {string} rgb2 Second RGB hex color starting with #
 * @customfunction
 */&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;DELTAHEX&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;hex1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;hex2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;deltaRGB&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;([&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;parseInt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;hex1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;slice&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;parseInt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;hex1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;slice&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;parseInt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;hex1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;slice&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;7&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],[&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;parseInt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;hex2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;slice&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;parseInt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;hex2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;slice&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;parseInt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;hex2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;slice&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;7&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;cm&quot;&gt;/**
 * Compare color difference in RGB
 * @param {Array} rgb1 First RGB color in array
 * @param {Array} rgb2 Second RGB color in array
 * source: https://gist.github.com/ryancat/9972419b2a78f329ce3aebb7f1a09152
 * with slight change to redmean formula used to match more precise Wikipedia version
 */&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;deltaRGB&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;rgb1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;rgb2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;r1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;g1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;b1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;rgb1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;r2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;g2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;b2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;rgb2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;drp2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;Math&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;pow&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;r1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;r2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;dgp2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;Math&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;pow&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;g1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;g2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;dbp2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;Math&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;pow&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;b1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;b2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;t&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;r1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;r2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;Math&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;sqrt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;256&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;drp2&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;dgp2&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;255&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;256&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;dbp2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><category term="Crafts" /><summary type="html">Downloadable list of Cosmo RGB and Hex Colours Looking for a list of RGB or Hex colours for the 2020 Cosmo embroidery floss collection? You can download it or copy the Google Sheets version here: Github: 500 colour Cosmo dataset</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Embroidery_Floss_Inventory_Diagram.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Embroidery_Floss_Inventory_Diagram.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Deep Dive: Composer Representation in Spotify Classical Playlists (Part Four)</title><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/11/14/deep-dive-spotify-part-four.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deep Dive: Composer Representation in Spotify Classical Playlists (Part Four)" /><published>2021-11-14T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-11-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/11/14/deep-dive-spotify-part-four</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/11/14/deep-dive-spotify-part-four.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;finishing-up-with-spotify&quot;&gt;Finishing Up With Spotify&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/10/31/deep-dive-spotify-part-three.html&quot;&gt;previous post on Spotify’s &lt;em&gt;Classical Sleep&lt;/em&gt; playlist&lt;/a&gt;, I noted that Spotify and Apple Music had very different ideas about what a “classical” playlist is (emphasis added):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[T]he two mood-themed playlists are wildly different when it comes to living composers, because they seem to have very different programming approaches. Apple Music’s &lt;em&gt;Relaxing Classical&lt;/em&gt; takes the existing “canon” and selects mood-appropriate pieces from within it. Pieces by Beethoven, Mozart, Brahms, Debussy, and Rachmaninoff make up nearly half of the playlist. As a result, only two of the tracks featured are by living composers.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Spotify’s &lt;em&gt;Classical Sleep&lt;/em&gt;, on the other hand, has 36 tracks by living composers, half of the overall total. This is because &lt;strong&gt;“Classical” in Spotify’s parlance means a mix of mood-appropriate pieces from the “canon” alongside modern artists who make mood music using classical instruments.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not just true of mood-themed classical playlists! It’s also true of Spotify’s &lt;em&gt;Classical New Releases&lt;/em&gt; playlist, in part because of how “new releases” playlists play into Spotify’s curatorial approach. Like with Spotify’s &lt;em&gt;Classical Sleep&lt;/em&gt; playlist, one of the clearest signifiers of this distinction between the two platforms is the very large number of living composers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;classical-new-releases&quot;&gt;Classical New Releases&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Classical New Releases&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;If Average US Orchestra&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Tracks&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;70&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Women&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;5 (7.1%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;BIPOC&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;6 (8.6%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Indigenous / Black Women&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;2 (2.9%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Living&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;39 (55.7%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first notable thing about this playlist is that it is the only one to have more people of colour than the “Average US Orchestra” comparison. It also has a very high number of living composers, as noted above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compared to the equivalent playlist from Apple Music, &lt;a href=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/03/01/deep-dive-apple-music.html#the-a-list-classical&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The A List: Classical&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, this playlist has more women (five compared to two), a greater number of people of colour (six compared to two), and two tracks by women of colour (there are none in Apple music’s playlist). Like with the mood-themed playlists, the biggest gap is in living composers: 39 in Spotify’s new releases playlist compared to five in Apple’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, going back to what I said at the top, it’s not an Apple to apples &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; comparison. In contrast to Apple’s &lt;em&gt;A List&lt;/em&gt;, Spotify’s playlist isn’t meant to be a showcase for new recordings of classical music — it’s primarily a feeder playlist for classical-themed mood playlists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-ecosystem-supporting----------------------------algorithmic-curation&quot;&gt;The Ecosystem Supporting                            Algorithmic Curation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you read about how Spotify approaches curation, it becomes clear that they view their playlists as an ecosystem that works hand in hand with the algorithm to surface the most popular and engaging music to listeners. This &lt;a href=&quot;https://playlistradar.com/spotify-101-understanding-the-spotify-playlist-landscape/&quot;&gt;article by Playlist Radar&lt;/a&gt; explains it well:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Spotify editors often test out new tracks on smaller “feeder” playlists. Tracks that perform well on a playlist like “New Noise” (289K followers) might be promoted to “Rock This” (4.3M followers); songs that gain traction on a playlist such as “Most Necessary” (1.8M followers) might eventually end up on “Rap Caviar” (10.3M followers).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New release playlists are a good entry point to this system: every week a new batch of songs are tested to see how they perform, and the winners (as determined by the algorithm), make their way onto other official playlists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Winning the algorithmic hunger games and getting a song placed on a prominent official playlist is how you make a living on Spotify, and the stakes are high. Just take a look at &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/album/1r7qNZsIrYhszVnFp92pv9?si=ltfVroSuQJqyAuCtxb-EWw&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Butterflying&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the album by Elena Kats-Chernin that includes &lt;em&gt;Lullaby for Nick&lt;/em&gt;, which we examined in the previous post. &lt;em&gt;Lullaby for Nick&lt;/em&gt; has over 6 million listens &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The next most-played song, &lt;em&gt;Butterflying&lt;/em&gt;, has only 86,000 listens &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Butterflying&lt;/em&gt; is aided slightly by its position as the first song in the album, but nothing compares to the power of official playlists to drive listens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Placement on a prominent official playlist like &lt;em&gt;Classical Sleep&lt;/em&gt; probably therefore makes the difference between a song that pays for a very nice dinner out and a song that pays rent for an entire year. With that said, let’s meet some of the contenders for an algorithmic golden ticket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;deborah-cheetham-christmas-with-you&quot;&gt;Deborah Cheetham: Christmas With You&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deborah_Cheetham&quot;&gt;Deborah Joy Cheetham&lt;/a&gt; AO (born 24 November 1964), is an Aboriginal Australian soprano, actor, composer and playwright.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the data for this project was collected around the winter holiday period in 2020, hence the occurrence of this modern Christmas carol and &lt;em&gt;Silent Night&lt;/em&gt; below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The carol was commissioned by the classical arm of the Australian Broadcasting Company (ABC Classic) and performed by over 1,500 singers whose performances were digitally edited together with music from the Queensland Symphony Orchestra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a song composed in 2020, you could believe it had been part of Christmas traditions for decades. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.abc.net.au/classic/read-and-watch/music-reads/deborah-cheetham-christmas-with-you/12821958&quot;&gt;Cheetham writes&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I do not apologise for the nostalgic style of this carol. There is longing, yes, but there is also hope. For me, hope is ultimately the message and meaning of Christmas. Hope is born into this world every day. We have only to grasp it, commit to it, cherish it and renew it. Sounds like a lot to do? Well… that is what music is for. That is why we sing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.abc.net.au/classic/read-and-watch/music-reads/deborah-cheetham-christmas-with-you/12821958&quot;&gt;learn more about the project and get the sheet music&lt;/a&gt; on the ABC Classic website. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20211027225850/https://www.abc.net.au/classic/events/classic-choir/welcome/&quot;&gt;Archive Link&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ABC Classic also commissioned artwork from Wadawarrung artist &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.deannegilson.com/&quot;&gt;Deanne Gilson&lt;/a&gt; to illustrate the themes explored in the Christmas carol, which has a number of cool birds on it &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, so I’ve included it below. You can read &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.abc.net.au/classic/read-and-watch/music-reads/deanne-gilson-morning-star/12821968&quot;&gt;more about the painting and Deanne&lt;/a&gt; on the ABC website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/christmas-with-you-artwork.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image of painting titled Nyirram turt-barram&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nyirram turt-barram&lt;/em&gt; (The Morning Star Story) by Deanne Gilson&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;celeste-wrabel--jamie-hartman-arr-kris-bowers-strange-feat-hillary-smith&quot;&gt;Celeste, Wrabel &amp;amp; Jamie Hartman arr. Kris Bowers: Strange (feat. Hillary Smith)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Celeste_(singer)&quot;&gt;Celeste Epiphany Waite&lt;/a&gt; (born 5 May 1994) is an American-British singer and songwriter. In 2019, she became the fifth artist to top the BBC’s annual Sound of… poll and win the Rising Star Award at the Brit Awards in the same year. Her debut album Not Your Muse was released in 2021 and debuted at No. 1 on the UK Albums Chart…. In the same year, Celeste was also nominated for the Academy Award for Best Original Song for co-writing “Hear My Voice” from the film The Trial of the Chicago 7 (2020).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here’s the origin story of this track: The &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/track/5Ck2pBM8zZNIjIxeiEiVvy?si=4fda76f94be74fdf&quot;&gt;original song&lt;/a&gt; was written by Celeste with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wrabel&quot;&gt;(Stephen) Wrabel&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jamie_Hartman&quot;&gt;Jamie Hartman&lt;/a&gt; &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and it was released in September 2019 as the lead single for her album &lt;em&gt;Not Your Muse&lt;/em&gt;. This version, however, is an instrumental cover arranged by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kris_Bowers&quot;&gt;Kris Bowers&lt;/a&gt; for the first season of the Netflix series &lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt;, and performed by cellist &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hillarysmithcello.com/menu&quot;&gt;Hillary Smith&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The entire &lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt; soundtrack has classical pop covers like this, with many performed by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vitamin_String_Quartet&quot;&gt;Vitamin String Quartet&lt;/a&gt;. For example, a string cover of Ariana Grande’s &lt;em&gt;thank u, next&lt;/em&gt; is the music for a ballroom dance in episode one. An &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;article in &lt;em&gt;Vulture&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; comments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Alongside these classical-pop mashups, &lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt; serves up classical warhorses like Mozart and Shostakovich…. By bringing modern melodies into the proper world of Regency England, &lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt; reminds us that classical music wasn’t always so stuffy and solemn. In its time, it trafficked in the same scandal as modern pop. Just with powdered wigs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this sounds interesting to you, I would highly recommend checking out this &lt;a href=&quot;https://switchedonpop.com/episodes/bridgerton-kris-bowers&quot;&gt;interview with the composer, Kris Bowers&lt;/a&gt;, on the &lt;em&gt;Switched on Pop&lt;/em&gt; podcast. Bowers also wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.laphil.com/musicdb/pieces/5585/for-a-younger-self-world-premiere&quot;&gt;violin concerto that was premiered by the American Youth Symphony&lt;/a&gt;. I don’t think there’s a full recording of it, but you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/american-youth-symphony/for-a-younger-self-excerpt-by-kris-bowers&quot;&gt;listen to an excerpt on the AYS SoundCloud page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ramin-djawadi-game-of-thrones-theme&quot;&gt;Ramin Djawadi: Game of Thrones Theme&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ramin_Djawadi&quot;&gt;Ramin Djawadi&lt;/a&gt; (born 19 July 1974) is a German score composer. He is known for his scores for the 2008 Marvel film Iron Man and the HBO series Game of Thrones, for which he was nominated for Grammy Awards in 2009, 2018 and 2020…. He won two consecutive Emmy Awards for Game of Thrones, in 2018 for the episode “The Dragon and the Wolf” and in 2019 for “The Long Night”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The track featured on the playlist is a cover of the &lt;em&gt;Game of Thrones&lt;/em&gt; theme by the Metamorphose String Orchestra in Belarus. I actually prefer &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/track/2q6fxAvSpqXR4jx9Ne7RGz?si=4fd1b46a87b3409f&quot;&gt;the original&lt;/a&gt; because it has the big percussion backing, but this version is pretty good too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently Ramin Djawadi did a big &lt;em&gt;Game of Thrones&lt;/em&gt; with orchestra tour before the pandemic and it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.toronto.com/events/game-of-thrones/&quot;&gt;came to Toronto&lt;/a&gt;. I’m very sad I missed it; looks like it was a pretty sick show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;masayoshi-fujita-sadness---carlos-cipa-rework&quot;&gt;Masayoshi Fujita: Sadness - Carlos Cipa Rework&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://masayoshifujita.com/about/&quot;&gt;Masayoshi Fujita&lt;/a&gt; is a Japanese vibraphonist, multi-percussionist and composer. Masayoshi first learned how to play the drums, followed by extensive vibraphone training to craft and play his own compositions.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Determined not to stick to traditional vibraphone styles or techniques and theory of composition, he seeks his own sound of vibraphone and new possibility of it. [He] also prepares his instrument with strings of bead, strips of foil and similar objects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose in the lo-fi world, “rework” conveys something more chill than “remix”, which implies adding another feature artist, dialing some element of the production up to 11, or both. But this is somewhere in-between a remix and a re-orchestration, so “rework” makes a certain kind of sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/track/5vCtL7CKdORJTfJ23OnJTr?si=f5b4f0d02dd74c9d&quot;&gt;original &lt;em&gt;Sadness&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was performed by Fujita on vibraphone. In this version, pianist Carlos Cipa is playing the textural parts, and Fujita comes in with the more melodic components on vibraphone. There are some distortion effects thrown in for good measure, especially at the end, and some truly impressive recording techniques used on Cipa’s piano. The resulting tone is incredibly soft and mellow; in fact, after my original half-listen, I had incorrectly jotted down “marimba” instead of “piano”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m incredibly intrigued by what’s happening at 1:20. There’s some kind of echoing knocking sound and what sounds like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8uAkaUShxxc&quot;&gt;bowed vibraphone&lt;/a&gt;. But maybe it’s some other technique, and the echoing knocking sound is the attack? &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Not really sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;astor-piazzolla-invierno-porteño&quot;&gt;Astor Piazzolla: Invierno Porteño&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Astor_Piazzolla&quot;&gt;Astor Pantaleón Piazzolla&lt;/a&gt; (March 11, 1921 – July 4, 1992) was an Argentine tango composer, bandoneon player, and arranger. His works revolutionized the traditional tango into a new style termed Nuevo tango, incorporating elements from jazz and classical music. A virtuoso bandoneonist, he regularly performed his own compositions with a variety of ensembles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is appearance number two for Piazzolla; his &lt;em&gt;Libertango&lt;/em&gt; was featured in &lt;a href=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/05/03/deep-dive-spotify-part-one.html#astor-piazzolla-libertango&quot;&gt;Spotify’s &lt;em&gt;Classical Essentials&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It’s part of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Estaciones_Porte%C3%B1as&quot;&gt;“Four Seasons of Buenos Aires” suite&lt;/a&gt; inspired by Antonio Vivaldi’s famous &lt;em&gt;The Four Seasons&lt;/em&gt;, and Invierno is the “Winter” part of Piazzolla’s suite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The track featured on the playlist is a cover of &lt;em&gt;Invierno Porteño&lt;/em&gt; by the Japanese duo of cellist &lt;a href=&quot;https://daimiyata.com/eng/biography&quot;&gt;Dai Miyata&lt;/a&gt; (宮田大) and classical guitarist &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yasuji_Ohagi&quot;&gt;Yasuji Ohagi&lt;/a&gt; (大萩康司). It’s the final track from their album &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/album/3gtXPnwpKsrQ0pltXB6l68?si=Q71ZLRHrSRSDgWkwL6HWog&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Travelogue&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which features guitar and cello covers of classical music from European and South American composers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like with the &lt;em&gt;Game of Thrones&lt;/em&gt; theme, I would encourage you to check out the original so you can hear Piazzolla play the bandoneon (which is in the same family of instruments as the accordion). But Miyata and Ohagi’s version is well-done too, with lyrical cello lines and warm guitar accompaniment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;kouhei-morita-low-roar&quot;&gt;Kouhei Morita: Low Roar&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[Kohei Morita (森田晃平) is] a scene musician from Kagoshima prefecture. He started playing contrabass and electric bass at the age of 16. In 2010, he moved his base of activities to Tokyo and participated in live performances and recordings of many artists such as VAMPS, Ikimonogakari, little green monster, Anri Kumaki as a bassist. His PRIMITIVE ART ORCHESTRA, which has been active since 2012, has released his three original albums. He is also active as a composer and arranger…. He is active with an emphasis on warm and unsophisticated bass tones, nostalgic tunes with scenes, and emotional and romantic arrangements. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/artist/7LdO9fKTNWQ6C52N1gcwo8?si=CNMrG6MRSVuZ-ldneTXJ7Q&quot;&gt;森田晃平 Spotify Artist Bio&lt;/a&gt;, via Google Translate)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the use of glissando &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; here; it really evokes a feeling that the double bass is singing. One neat effect of streaming is that it does remove a lot of the barriers to reaching a global audience. I don’t think there’s any English media about Morita, so how else would someone from Canada discover a double bass player in Japan? Very cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;hania-rani-silent-night&quot;&gt;Hania Rani: Silent Night&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hania_Rani&quot;&gt;Hania Rani&lt;/a&gt; (born Hanna Raniszewska; 1990, Gdańsk) is a Polish pianist, composer and singer. She studied music at the Music School Feliks Nowowiejski in Gdańsk and the Fryderyk Chopin University of Music. (Also: &lt;a href=&quot;http://haniarani.com/about/&quot;&gt;Bio on Hania Rani Website&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, this is essentially &lt;em&gt;Silent Night&lt;/em&gt;, deconstructed. Part of a rich tradition in classical music of taking a tune, pulling it apart, making variations, and putting it back together again as a bigger or different whole. Another good example from earlier would be Coleridge-Taylor’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/05/03/deep-dive-spotify-part-one.html#samuel-coleridge-taylor-symphonic-variations-on-an-african-air-op63&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Symphonic Variations on an African Air&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If stores are going to insist on playing holiday songs as soon as November rolls around (even the local falafel shop was playing christmas music already the other night), this kind of track is probably the way to go. It evokes the holidays without being so strong a flavour that your average retail worker would be losing their mind the tenth time it’s played &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;martina-stock-see-the-face&quot;&gt;Martina Stock: See The Face&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[Martina Stock] plays her black concert harp not in the “classical way“ - contemporary, combining acoustic melodies with electronic surfaces and a loop station…. In addition to this, she has developed a lighting system, which makes her possible, an unique play in the dark [sic].&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;…Martina Stock grew up in Bischofshofen, in the mountains of Salzburg countryside, Austria. She studied at the University Mozarteum Salzburg which she completed in 2009. She lives and works in Berlin and Salzburg. (from &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/artist/6kv6jaS62CE2oWnH7msKzT&quot;&gt;Martina Stock Spotify Artist Bio&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the circular structure of this one: it begins and ends with a fanfare-like theme, with a long series of variations in the middle that are constantly moving and evolving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Martina Stock is also a visual artist, and does a lot of silkscreen pieces (i.e. serigraphy). In some of her shows she combines her visual and musical talents, surrounding herself in her silkscreen works and adding lighting effects to the space and to her harp. Here’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pNK9ZJ6XGDY&quot;&gt;one example, titled &lt;em&gt;The Blue Eros&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;james-morgan--juliette-pochin-veni-creator-spiritus---chill-mix&quot;&gt;James Morgan &amp;amp; Juliette Pochin: Veni Creator Spiritus - Chill Mix&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.morganpochin.com/63/Morgan-Pochin&quot;&gt;James Morgan and Juliette Pochin&lt;/a&gt; formed their partnership Morgan Pochin whilst undergraduates at Cambridge, and have gone on to work in a huge variety of fields, from EMMY award winning TV series to UK album chart successes, feature films and compositions for the concert platform and stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, so “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Veni_Creator_Spiritus&quot;&gt;a hymn&lt;/a&gt;, but for spa days” is actually not a bad idea! Choral music can be very relaxing and beautiful, and the addition of soft synths is well done here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the claps… I can’t get over the claps. This song would have been fine if they hadn’t scrolled over to the percussion section of their keyboard, picked the fakest-sounding clap, and then applied reverb to it. Why???&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kind of a weird way to end, but there it is. Good idea, hate the claps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;up-next&quot;&gt;Up Next&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the end of the deep dives, but probably not the last post on the topic of classical streaming playlists. There are a number of interesting things I came across relating to the streaming platforms themselves, ranging from the UK parliament study mentioned in the previous post to the oddly-anonymous streaming artists that featured on several of the Spotify playlists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also have two other data sets that could be analyzed. The first one is longitudinal: I’ve been saving a weekly copy of the track listings for the Spotify playlists examined in this series to see how they evolve over time. I have a similar dataset for Apple Music, but it only covers a couple months &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second dataset includes playlists and track listings from Primephonic, the classical streaming service &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2021/08/apple-acquires-classical-music-streaming-service-primephonic/&quot;&gt;acquired by Apple in late August&lt;/a&gt;. From a glance, I don’t think the representation of composers on Primephonic is going to be notably different than on Apple Music’s existing playlists, but it’ll be interesting to look through regardless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before digging into all that, I might take a break and write about other things. I’ve been wanting to write about &lt;a href=&quot;https://donne-uk.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/Equality-Diversity-in-Concert-Halls_2020_2021.pdf&quot;&gt;DONNE’s 2021 study of repertoire by 100 orchestras&lt;/a&gt; worldwide for a while. There are also some interesting visualizations I can make from the 2019/20 Institute for Composer Diversity analysis using the &lt;a href=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/programming/2021/07/03/building-orchestra-season-visualization-tool.html&quot;&gt;tool I created earlier this year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or maybe I’ll write about something else entirely! I have an interesting idea for a post about geographic data analysis for nonprofit impact measurement. We’ll see…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;playlist-methodology-and-data&quot;&gt;Playlist, Methodology, and Data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can listen to all of the pieces featured in this playlist analysis series here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/playlist/6vQwkvRqWbGEF5IKZmC6na?si=1829c2da26b84f03&quot;&gt;Spotify: Classical Deep Dive - Spotify &amp;amp; Apple Music&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full methodology notes for all my music posts can be found via the &lt;a href=&quot;/exploring-orchestral-music-methodology/&quot;&gt;Main Methodology Page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Details and data for the streaming service playlists analysis can be found on the &lt;a href=&quot;/exploring-orchestral-music-methodology/streaming-service-demographic-analysis.html&quot;&gt;Streaming Analysis Methodology Page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More details about how I used the data from the Institute for Composer Diversity to create the comparison to US orchestra mainstage seasons can be found on the &lt;a href=&quot;/exploring-orchestral-music-methodology/ICD-orchestra-season-analysis.html&quot;&gt;ICD 2019/20 Season Analysis Methodology Page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I was going to do a sort of “ba-dum tsssh” here with emoji, but it turns out there’s no cymbal emoji, so this is not possible. Poor 🥁, all alone in the emoji percussion section. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;6,082,741 listens as of November 6, 2021 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;85,689 listens as of November 6, 2021 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Just look at that Kookaburra on the top right! &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Interesting to note that Wrabel and Jamie Hartman were also involved with writing &lt;em&gt;Don’t Go Breaking My Heart&lt;/em&gt;, the 2018 Backstreet Boys comeback single. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Attack” is the starting part of a sound - e.g. if you hit a vibraphone with a mallet, there’s a initial burst of sound from the mallet hitting the metal, and then a long “decay” as the metal bar resonates. Pulling a bow across a violin string, for example, would actually have three components: the attack of the bow starting to move (if you’re up close, it sounds a bit crunchy), the “sustain” of the string resonating as the bow continues to move, and then a soft “decay” as the string keeps ringing after the bow has been lifted. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A fancy Italian music term for a note that slides from one pitch to another. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;My personal tolerance level is that I think I could listen to Mariah Carey’s &lt;em&gt;All I Want for Christmas Is You&lt;/em&gt; maybe about three times before starting to feel irate; on the other hand, I’m not actually sure I have a limit for Wham!’s &lt;em&gt;Last Christmas&lt;/em&gt;. Famous last words, probably… &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Apple Music doesn’t have an ad-supported account option, so the only way to export the playlist info each week would have been to pay for the service after my 3-month free trial. Apparently my dedication to this topic does have &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; limits. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><category term="Music" /><summary type="html">Finishing Up With Spotify</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/christmas-with-you-artwork.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/christmas-with-you-artwork.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Deep Dive: Composer Representation in Spotify Classical Playlists (Part Three)</title><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/10/31/deep-dive-spotify-part-three.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deep Dive: Composer Representation in Spotify Classical Playlists (Part Three)" /><published>2021-10-31T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-10-31T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/10/31/deep-dive-spotify-part-three</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/10/31/deep-dive-spotify-part-three.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;music-for-every-mood&quot;&gt;Music For Every Mood&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuing from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/09/19/deep-dive-spotify-part-two.html&quot;&gt;previous post on Spotify’s all-orchestra playlist&lt;/a&gt;, we’re now turning back to the calm and digression-worthy world of mood playlists with a look at Spotify’s &lt;em&gt;Classical Sleep&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;classical-sleep&quot;&gt;Classical Sleep&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Classical Sleep&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;If Average US Orchestra&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Tracks&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;72&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Women&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;3 (4.2%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Black&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;2 (2.8%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Women of Colour&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Living&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;36 (50%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compared to &lt;a href=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/03/01/deep-dive-apple-music.html#relaxing-classical&quot;&gt;Apple Music’s &lt;em&gt;Relaxing Classical&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, this mood-themed playlist has representation of at least &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; composer of colour with the two pieces by Alexis Ffrench, and one more piece by a female composer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the two mood-themed playlists are wildly different when it comes to living composers, because they seem to have very different programming approaches. Apple Music’s &lt;em&gt;Relaxing Classical&lt;/em&gt; takes the existing “canon” and selects mood-appropriate pieces from within it. Pieces by Beethoven, Mozart, Brahms, Debussy, and Rachmaninoff make up nearly half of the playlist. As a result, only two of the tracks featured are by living composers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spotify’s &lt;em&gt;Classical Sleep&lt;/em&gt;, on the other hand, has 36 tracks by living composers, half of the overall total. This is because “Classical” in Spotify’s parlance means a mix of mood-appropriate pieces from the “canon” alongside modern artists who make mood music using classical instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The living composers responsible for those 36 tracks range from often-anonymous artists, &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; whose entire career is designed around providing the kind of algorithmically-friendly music favoured by mood playlists, to artists like Elena Kats-Chernin, who frequently work with orchestras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;alexis-ffrench-together-at-last-bluebird&quot;&gt;Alexis Ffrench: Together At Last; Bluebird&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexis_Ffrench&quot;&gt;Alexis Ffrench&lt;/a&gt; (born 1970) is a British classical soul pioneer, composer, producer and pianist. Not only is Ffrench the UK’s biggest selling pianist of 2020, he has headlined London’s Royal Albert Hall, collaborated with fashion houses Miyake and Hugo Boss, played Latitude Festival, worked with Paloma Faith, composed several film scores and shares the same management team as Little Mix and Niall Horan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Appearance #2 for Ffrench, whose &lt;em&gt;A Time for Giving&lt;/em&gt; was featured on &lt;a href=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/03/01/deep-dive-apple-music.html#alexis-ffrench-a-time-for-giving&quot;&gt;Apple Music’s &lt;em&gt;The A-List: Classical&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The first of these two songs, &lt;em&gt;Together At Last&lt;/em&gt;, is the titular song from Ffrench’s 2018 holiday EP. Like &lt;em&gt;A Time for Giving&lt;/em&gt;, which is from Ffrench’s 2020 holiday EP, &lt;em&gt;Home&lt;/em&gt;, it reminds me of the church music influences that Ffrench has spoken about in his music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second, &lt;em&gt;Bluebird&lt;/em&gt;, is far and away Ffrench’s most popular song, and in my comments about the Apple Music playlist, I linked to a great performance of it from the BRIT awards. It reminds me in so many good ways of &lt;em&gt;Married Life&lt;/em&gt; from Michael Giacchino’s soundtrack to &lt;em&gt;UP&lt;/em&gt; — the sighing phrases, the gentle piano, the sense of time looping and passing at the same time. It’s really excellent. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;amy-beach-berceuse-lullaby-no-2-from-three-compositions-op-40&quot;&gt;Amy Beach: Berceuse (Lullaby), No. 2 from Three Compositions, Op. 40&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amy_Beach&quot;&gt;Amy Marcy Cheney Beach&lt;/a&gt; (September 5, 1867 – December 27, 1944) was an American composer and pianist. She was the first successful American female composer of large-scale art music. Her “Gaelic” Symphony, premiered by the Boston Symphony Orchestra in 1896, was the first symphony composed and published by an American woman. She was one of the first American composers to succeed without the benefit of European training, and one of the most respected and acclaimed American composers of her era. As a pianist, she was acclaimed for concerts she gave featuring her own music in the United States and in Germany.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another second appearance: Beach’s &lt;em&gt;Young Birches, Op. 128&lt;/em&gt; were featured on &lt;a href=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/05/03/deep-dive-spotify-part-one.html#amy-beach-young-birches-op-128-no-2&quot;&gt;Spotify’s &lt;em&gt;Classical Essentials&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The song title doesn’t really make it clear (the track in the playlist is from a lullaby compilation album), but this is the second movement from a trio, which you can listen to on this &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/album/24nOyX4MeANGSsKhYclqDa?si=Ekwz695wRRGbpme2rf2j6w&amp;amp;dl_branch=1&quot;&gt;album from the Klugherz-Timmons Duo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;nadje-noordhuis-bluebird&quot;&gt;Nadje Noordhuis: Bluebird&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Described as “one of the most compelling voices to emerge on her instrument in recent years” (Dan Bilawksy, All about Jazz), Australian-born New York based trumpeter/composer Nadje Noordhuis possesses one of the most unforgettably lyrical voices in modern music. Her deeply-felt, clarion tone and evocative compositional gift meld classical rigor, jazz expression, and world music accents into a sound that is distinctively her own. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nadjenoordhuis.com/about-1&quot;&gt;Personal Website Biography&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our second song called &lt;em&gt;Bluebird&lt;/em&gt; on this playlist. One interesting thing they both have in common is that the piano is mic’d in such a way that you can hear the sounds of the sustain pedal and other moving parts click and thud in the background. It’s an interesting feature of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://switchedonpop.com/episodes/why-lo-fi-is-the-perfect-background-music&quot;&gt;lo-fi production&lt;/a&gt; you can find on many mood-themed playlists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the real jewel of this track is the trumpet performance. Noordhuis plays with a lovely warm tone and is able to effortlessly glide into and out of silence in certain phrases. If you like this track, I’d recommend you check out the whole album, which is titled &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/album/7k6LMeVKzWrL9XHzNTPkXu?si=9RwJMxm6Sa-pDQ6A-w4nGQ&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ten Sails&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-digression-about-metadata&quot;&gt;A Digression About Metadata&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other interesting thing about this song is that it illustrates an issue that has been frequently discussed about Spotify and other streaming platforms. At a high level, a song has two sets of rights, which result in two types of revenue streams. First, there is the “master” right to the recording itself, and second, there are the “publishing” rights for the music composition. When you stream a track on Apple Music or Spotify, both sets of rightsholders need to be paid. However, especially for publishing rightsholders (e.g. a composer or songwriter), the data that tells the streaming service who to pay is often missing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; problem. In a recent review, the UK Digital, Culture, Media and Sport Committee heard that there are billions of dollars unallocated due to bad data:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At best, mismatched, incomplete or missing metadata can result in delays to creator royalties for months or even years. At worst, this can result in payments being misallocated or otherwise consigned as unclaimed or non-attributable royalties to ‘black boxes’. Black boxes consisted of $2.5 billion in unallocated income in 2019 alone. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, artists are able to get the data fixed and collect the income they are entitled to. However, the committee heard that most of the money goes elsewhere:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;After a period of time, black boxes are then assigned pro-rata to streams that have been correctly identified, which is established in standard publishing agreements. This means that those creators and companies, particularly who are most listened to, are effectively are [sic] paid twice: first for their own streams, and then for streams that cannot be allocated. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many reasons this problem persists, including the need to digitize paper records for back catalogues, and limitations on who can submit corrections or challenges to bad data. However, a big part of the problem is lack of effort from record labels:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Because the recording and song rights are licensed separately and often held by different music creators and companies, many labels do not supply the relevant ISWC &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; when licensing music to streaming services, meaning that songwriters often lose out altogether when music is streamed. Often, this is by choice because of the difficulty of doing so: in oral evidence, Maria Forte asserted that in conversation with one record label, a representative said “‘I don’t care about composer information because it’s nothing to do with me. I’m not changing my system to do that’”. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, there is a mismatch of responsibility and incentive. The record label earns its income from owning the master rights to a song. However, it is responsible for supplying the data that identifies the master rights holder(s) &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; the publishing rights holder(s) when the song is uploaded. As a result, the master rights data is usually correct, but the publishing rights data is often incorrect or omitted, unless the record label has a financial stake in ensuring the publishing rights data is correct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bluebird&lt;/em&gt; is an excellent example of this — when the song was originally uploaded to Spotify, the songwriter credit for Nadje Noordhuis was missing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;max-width: 400px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/Screen Shot 2021-09-18 at 4.30.30 PM.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Spotify &amp;quot;Show Credits&amp;quot; dialog box. &amp;quot;Written by&amp;quot; is blank.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, at the time, songwriter credits for Nadje’s collaborator, Luke Howard, &lt;em&gt;were&lt;/em&gt; included on the same album. The label, Lukktone, appears to be owned or controlled by Luke Howard (since &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.discogs.com/label/792716-Lukktone&quot;&gt;all of its releases feature him as an artist&lt;/a&gt;). I’m not accusing anyone here of malice — it just illustrates the broader issue: Lukktone had a strong financial incentive to ensure that the songwriter credits for Luke Howard were correctly submitted; it had less of an incentive to ensure that the credits for Nadje Noordhuis were also correct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, this particular story has a positive ending. At some point between September and October 2021, the credits were corrected:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;max-width: 400px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/Screen Shot 2021-10-31 at 12.17.23 PM.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Spotify &amp;quot;Show Credits&amp;quot; dialog box. &amp;quot;Written by&amp;quot; lists &amp;quot;Nadje Noordhuis-Fairfax&amp;quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even still, this album was released in 2015, which means that at best, Nadja Noordhuis will be receiving a couple thousand dollars in publishing revenue &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; for a song that’s been streamed over 4 million times on Spotify — six years late.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in reading more about this issue, you can check out a good &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2019/5/29/18531476/music-industry-song-royalties-metadata-credit-problems&quot;&gt;article from &lt;em&gt;The Verge&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; from a couple years ago as well as the full discussion of the issue in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://committees.parliament.uk/publications/6739/documents/72525/default/&quot;&gt;UK Parliament Report&lt;/a&gt; (starting on the page numbered 49/page 53 in the PDF). (&lt;a href=&quot;https://committees.parliament.uk/work/646/economics-of-music-streaming/&quot;&gt;Full materials from the UK committee review&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;elena-kats-chernin-lullaby-for-nick&quot;&gt;Elena Kats-Chernin: Lullaby For Nick&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elena_Kats-Chernin&quot;&gt;Elena Kats-Chernin&lt;/a&gt; AO (born 4 November 1957) is a Soviet-born Australian pianist and composer, best known for her ballet &lt;em&gt;Wild Swans&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I would describe the vibe of this song as “Pull up a chair and get comfortable. I’m about to tell you a long story, starting from the beginning.” Perhaps I should have suggested you listen to this before the metadata digression above. If I had a piano in my house, I would definitely learn how to play this; if you want to learn how to play it, you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.boosey.com/shop/prod/Kats-Chernin-Elena-Lullaby-for-Nick-Violin-Piano-Digital-Sheet-Music/2498011&quot;&gt;buy the sheet music from Boosey &amp;amp; Hawkes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;up-next&quot;&gt;Up Next&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next post in this series, I’ll finish off the Spotify deep dive with a look at their &lt;em&gt;Classical New Releases&lt;/em&gt; playlist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;playlist-methodology-and-data&quot;&gt;Playlist, Methodology, and Data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can listen to all of the pieces featured in this playlist analysis series here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/playlist/6vQwkvRqWbGEF5IKZmC6na?si=1829c2da26b84f03&quot;&gt;Spotify: Classical Deep Dive - Spotify &amp;amp; Apple Music&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full methodology notes for all my music posts can be found via the &lt;a href=&quot;/exploring-orchestral-music-methodology/&quot;&gt;Main Methodology Page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Details and data for the streaming service playlists analysis can be found on the &lt;a href=&quot;/exploring-orchestral-music-methodology/streaming-service-demographic-analysis.html&quot;&gt;Streaming Analysis Methodology Page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More details about how I used the data from the Institute for Composer Diversity to create the comparison to US orchestra mainstage seasons can be found on the &lt;a href=&quot;/exploring-orchestral-music-methodology/ICD-orchestra-season-analysis.html&quot;&gt;ICD 2019/20 Season Analysis Methodology Page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If you look at the &lt;a href=&quot;/exploring-orchestral-music-methodology/streaming-service-demographic-analysis.html#source-data&quot;&gt;data for this project&lt;/a&gt;, you’ll see “No Sources Found” for the demographic attributes of artists that could not be linked to a known person. The methodology page also has notes on &lt;a href=&quot;/exploring-orchestral-music-methodology/streaming-service-demographic-analysis.html#unknown-composers&quot;&gt;how unknown artists were handled in the analysis&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;To make sure, I went to listen to &lt;em&gt;Married Life&lt;/em&gt; again, and this has tangentially inspired me with a business idea for orchestras:&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Nearly everyone who has seen &lt;em&gt;UP&lt;/em&gt; will be unable to listen to &lt;em&gt;Married Life&lt;/em&gt; without being brought to tears, or at least this is my personal experience. It’s a masterpiece of modern cinema, packing an incredible amount of emotional affect into a very short number of minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Now, the last time I went to see a Pops program about film scores, &lt;em&gt;Married Life&lt;/em&gt; was not on it, which is surely a crime, but also an incredible missed opportunity. Much like you can shore up a financially deficient theme park in &lt;em&gt;Rollercoaster Tycoon&lt;/em&gt; by jacking up the price of umbrellas when it rains, every orchestra should put &lt;em&gt;Married Life&lt;/em&gt; just before intermission and then have the ushers sell packets of tissues for $5 each on the way out to the lobby.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;OK, OK, so in the current context of there still very much being a global pandemic, maybe encouraging everyone to nose trumpet for revenue is a bad idea health-wise. But when COVID-19 is finally over and dead in the ground (dear lord, one day soon I hope), this is the path back to financial stability that all orchestras should surely take.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Anyway, my point is that &lt;em&gt;Bluebird&lt;/em&gt; is a really good song. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Paragraph 93, page 51. Sources in original.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Digital, Culture, Media and Sport Committee. “Economics of Music Streaming: Second Report of Session 2021–22.” London, United Kingdom: House of Commons, July 9, 2021. &lt;a href=&quot;https://committees.parliament.uk/publications/6739/documents/72525/default/&quot;&gt;https://committees.parliament.uk/publications/6739/documents/72525/default/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;The original source for the $2.5 billion figure was a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digitalmusicnews.com/2017/08/03/music-industry-royalty-black-box/&quot;&gt;2017 article by Digital Music News&lt;/a&gt; which cited figures provided by Paperchain, a tech company. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Paragraph 93, page 51. Sources in original.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Digital, Culture, Media and Sport Committee. “Economics of Music Streaming: Second Report of Session 2021–22.” London, United Kingdom: House of Commons, July 9, 2021. &lt;a href=&quot;https://committees.parliament.uk/publications/6739/documents/72525/default/&quot;&gt;https://committees.parliament.uk/publications/6739/documents/72525/default/&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;International Standard Musical Works Code, a unique identifier used to help identify the correct rightsholders. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Paragraph 90, page 50. Sources in original.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Digital, Culture, Media and Sport Committee. “Economics of Music Streaming: Second Report of Session 2021–22.” London, United Kingdom: House of Commons, July 9, 2021. &lt;a href=&quot;https://committees.parliament.uk/publications/6739/documents/72525/default/&quot;&gt;https://committees.parliament.uk/publications/6739/documents/72525/default/&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;It’s hard to estimate exactly, but you could extrapolate from the average master right payout and take a guess at what the publishing revenue might be:&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;USD $0.004 per-stream master right payment × (15% publishing / 55% master) × 4,200,000 streams × 50% revenue share with publisher ≈ $2,300 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><category term="Music" /><summary type="html">Music For Every Mood</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Deep Dive: Composer Representation in Spotify Classical Playlists (Part Two)</title><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/09/19/deep-dive-spotify-part-two.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deep Dive: Composer Representation in Spotify Classical Playlists (Part Two)" /><published>2021-09-19T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-09-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/09/19/deep-dive-spotify-part-two</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/09/19/deep-dive-spotify-part-two.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;diving-deeper-into-spotify&quot;&gt;Diving Deeper into Spotify&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuing from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/05/03/deep-dive-spotify-part-one.html&quot;&gt;previous post on Spotify classical music playlists&lt;/a&gt;, we’re now turning to Spotify’s all-orchestra playlist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;orchestra-100-spotify-picks&quot;&gt;Orchestra 100: Spotify Picks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Orchestra 100&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;If Average US Orchestra&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Tracks&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;100&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Women&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;2 (2.0%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;People of Colour&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;2 (2.0%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Women of Colour&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;none&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Living&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;8 (8.0%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;16&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oddly enough, given Apple Music’s stronger UI and metadata for classical music, it didn’t have an equivalent first party “all-orchestra” playlist like this one. In a sense, this should be the most comparable playlist to the average US orchestra season since it only focuses on orchestral repertoire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like &lt;a href=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/05/03/deep-dive-spotify-part-one.html#classical-essentials&quot;&gt;Spotify’s &lt;em&gt;Classical Essentials&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, this playlist has significantly fewer composers who are women or people of colour compared to the average US orchestra season, and no women of colour composers at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;heitor-villa-lobos-choros-no-8&quot;&gt;Heitor Villa-Lobos: Choros No. 8&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heitor_Villa-Lobos&quot;&gt;Heitor Villa-Lobos&lt;/a&gt; (March 5, 1887 – November 17, 1959) was a Brazilian composer, conductor, cellist, and classical guitarist described as “the single most significant creative figure in 20th-century Brazilian art music”. Villa-Lobos has become the best-known South American composer of all time. A prolific composer, he wrote numerous orchestral, chamber, instrumental and vocal works, totaling over 2000 works by his death in 1959.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is part of a larger series of pieces named after chôro, “music played by an ensemble of Brazilian street musicians (called chorões) using both African and European instruments, who improvise in a free and often dissonant kind of counterpoint called contracanto.” &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I’m quite fond of the fact that the beginning sounds a bit like the warm-up that happens onstage before most concerts start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems that Villa-Lobos is played much less often by US orchestras now than during his late lifetime. In his 1951 book “The American Symphony Orchestra: A Social History of Musical Taste”, John H. Mueller wrote “Among the composers [of Latin America], Villa-Lobos of Brazil is the most noted and enjoys a statistically perceptible rank in the repertoire.” &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://americanorchestras.org/learn/artistic-planning/orchestra-repertoire-report/&quot;&gt;League of American Orchestras Repertoire Reports&lt;/a&gt; note only two programs featuring pieces by Villa-Lobos in 2012/13 and no programs in 2011/12. The Institute for Composer Diversity analysis from 2019/20 (which included slightly more than twice as many orchestras compared to the League reports) notes eight performances of pieces by Villa-Lobos. The only major symphony featured in either source was Oregon, who included Villa-Lobos’ &lt;em&gt;Uirapurú&lt;/em&gt; in their 2019/20 season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the explanation may be related to US foreign policy? It’s possible that the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Good_Neighbor_policy&quot;&gt;Good Neighbour Policy&lt;/a&gt; espoused by President Roosevelt contributed to interest in South American composers; in turn, after the fall of Brazilian president Getúlio Vargas in 1945, Villa-Lobos was able to travel again, and his Wikipedia page notes that he “made regular visits to the United States”. If I can find an analysis of US orchestral repertoire that follows on from the time period of Mueller’s book, it would be interesting to see if there was a decline in performances of Villa-Lobos’ work brought on by a return to more interventionist South American US foreign policy with the onset of the Cold War.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One other fun comment on Villa-Lobos from Mueller’s book: in a section about audience reactions, he writes about how the tastes of conductor Leopold Stokowski were sometimes at odds with those of his audience. A Schoenberg performance apparently elicited a “shower of forthright hisses” from the audience, after which Stokowski “turned to his audience and defensively pleaded freedom of expression for the artist.” Mueller then tactfully notes that “Those who agreed with him applauded; those who preferred freedom of expression for the audience made known their opinions by a contrary sign.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stokowski later performed this piece—Chorôs No. 8—resulting in a similar audience reaction. Presumably having learned that arguing with the audience did no good, “on this occasion [Stokowski] invited the disaffected members of the audience to leave “and smoke the classic cigarette.”” &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Final note: I recently discovered an &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/album/3jvrf0brPEohaxmFHffZGM?si=YbyASROJTk6RiGjFaDCvyQ&amp;amp;dl_branch=1&quot;&gt;album of Villa-Lobos Choral Transcriptions&lt;/a&gt; performed by the São Paulo Symphony Choir and Valentina Peleggi and really enjoyed it. I would highly recommend you give it a listen!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;toru-takemitsu-a-flock-descends-into-the-pentagonal-garden&quot;&gt;Toru Takemitsu: A Flock Descends Into the Pentagonal Garden&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/T%C5%8Dru_Takemitsu&quot;&gt;Tōru Takemitsu&lt;/a&gt; (武満 徹, Takemitsu Tōru, October 8, 1930 – February 20, 1996) was a Japanese composer and writer on aesthetics and music theory. Largely self-taught, Takemitsu was admired for the subtle manipulation of instrumental and orchestral timbre. He is known for combining elements of oriental and occidental philosophy and for fusing sound with silence and tradition with innovation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know, I’ve listened to this one several times, and I don’t think I like it; it’s too abstract for my tastes. It seems to be one of Takemitsu’s more well-known pieces for Orchestra, and one of the ones I had heard of already before doing this project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you do like this style of music, then let me shill for my employer and recommend you check out an &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/album/3BFaA08GIWtZlfKdUxDIHu?si=2jf4L9brS7-fKsUKxDFZ7w&amp;amp;dl_branch=1&quot;&gt;album of four of Takemitsu’s early orchestra pieces&lt;/a&gt; from 1969, with the TSO conducted by then-Music Director Seiji Ozawa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;louise-farrenc-symphony-no-3-in-g-minor-op-36-i-adagio---allegro&quot;&gt;Louise Farrenc: Symphony No. 3 in G Minor, Op. 36: I. Adagio - Allegro&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louise_Farrenc&quot;&gt;Louise Farrenc&lt;/a&gt; (née Jeanne-Louise Dumont; 31 May 1804 – 15 September 1875) was a French composer, virtuoso pianist and teacher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the second piece we’ve looked at by Farrenc; the third movement from her Nonet in E-Flat Major, Op. 38 was on &lt;a href=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/05/03/deep-dive-spotify-part-one.html#louise-farrenc-nonet-in-e-flat-major-op-38-iii-scherzo-vivace&quot;&gt;Spotify’s &lt;em&gt;Classical Essentials&lt;/em&gt; playlist&lt;/a&gt;. This symphony was written two years earlier than the Nonet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By self-admission, Farrenc’s Symphony No. 3 is the only symphony by a female composer on Tom Service’s 2014 Guardian series on “50 Greatest Symphonies”. In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/music/tomserviceblog/2014/jun/24/symphony-guide-louise-farrenc-third-symphony-tom-service&quot;&gt;Service’s article on Farrenc’s symphony&lt;/a&gt;, he says the final movement is his favourite. I think mine is the first — the boisterous theme that comes after the slow lead-in is a top-tier example of “big C” classical drama.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-role-of-commercial-recordings&quot;&gt;The Role of Commercial Recordings&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his article, Service noted that there were only two commercial recordings of Farrenc’s Symphony No. 3: one from the North German Radio Philharmonic (the one featured on this playlist) and another from the Orchestre de Bretagne. Two more recordings have since been made by the Solistes Européens, Luxembourg in 2018 &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and very recently by the Insula Orchestra in July 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s interesting to watch how the availability of commercial recordings has started to catch up with changes in orchestra programming to feature more diverse composers. For example, Florence Price became a household name for many orchestras in 2020/21, while at the same time only her first symphony had more than one recording. Now, as of September 24, Deutche Grammophon is releasing a recording of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.umusic.ca/press-releases/yannick-nezet-seguin-the-philadelphia-orchestra-announce-new-album-florence-price-symphonies-nos-1-3/&quot;&gt;Philadelphia Orchestra playing symphonies 1 &amp;amp; 3&lt;/a&gt; conducted by Yannick Nézet-Séguin. There’s still only the one &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/album/2EKqIZNOAbDdk4F1gL56Wh?si=65OzboWRSyiCotqOY3pANQ&amp;amp;dl_branch=1&quot;&gt;recording of Symphony No. 4 by the Fort Smith Symphony&lt;/a&gt;, but hopefully more are on their way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are still some gaps to fill: earlier in the year I did some back-of-the-napkin math, and about one-third of the most-played orchestra pieces by women composers have no commercial recordings at all; most notably Missy Mazzoli’s &lt;em&gt;Sinfonia (for Orbiting Spheres)&lt;/em&gt;, although you can find some &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RPyJt0aSnP8&quot;&gt;recorded performances of it on YouTube&lt;/a&gt;. Maybe this is a small part of the puzzle — even if you had curators at Spotify and Apple Music whose programming choices were more in line with the average US orchestra, there are still a sizeable number of pieces that aren’t in the catalogue yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;kaija-saariaho-du-cristal&quot;&gt;Kaija Saariaho: Du Cristal&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kaija_Saariaho&quot;&gt;Kaija Anneli Saariaho&lt;/a&gt; (Finnish: [ˈkɑi̯jɑ ˈsɑːriɑho]; née Laakkonen; born 14 October 1952) is a Finnish composer based in Paris, France. … In a 2019 composers’ poll by BBC Music Magazine, Saariaho was ranked the greatest living composer.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Saariaho studied composition in Helsinki, Freiburg, and Paris, where she has lived since 1982. Her research at the Institute for Research and Coordination in Acoustics/Music (IRCAM) marked a turning point in her music away from strict serialism towards spectralism. Her characteristically rich, polyphonic textures are often created by combining live music and electronics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like “A Flock Descends…” this one is also a bit abstract for my tastes, though I find myself liking it more, and I would definitely be interested in hearing it live. In particular, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://saariaho.org/works/du-cristal/&quot;&gt;description on Saariaho’s website&lt;/a&gt; mentions that the piece has “an important part for synthesizer” which isn’t immediately obvious to me; &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; maybe being able to see the synth player press the keys would be a good clue as to which sounds are analogue and which are digital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The piece is actually a two-parter of sorts: &lt;a href=&quot;https://saariaho.org/works/a-la-fumee/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;…à la Fumée&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is meant to follow, though it’s clear that Saariaho thinks that each can stand alone, and in fact they were each commissioned for two different orchestras. Like with &lt;em&gt;Du Cristal&lt;/em&gt;, there’s an electronic element to &lt;em&gt;à la Fumée&lt;/em&gt;, with electronically modified alto flute and cello soloists. There were a couple moments where the solo instruments sounded like they were using an effect or filter, but like with &lt;em&gt;Du Cristal&lt;/em&gt;, it’s very subtle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the difference in how I feel about this piece compared to “A Flock Descends…” is that despite both being abstract (by which I mean neither has any clear melody), &lt;em&gt;Du Cristal&lt;/em&gt; feels like it has a clearer structure created by the differences in intensity and instrumentation, whereas I don’t think the musical ideas in “A Flock Descends…” come together in a way that makes the whole greater than the sum of its parts. I will admit, in both cases, I like each piece a little more after every repeat listen, so who knows, maybe after two dozen plays, I’ll change my mind and think “A Flock Descends…” is great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;up-next&quot;&gt;Up Next&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I’m increasingly adding long digressions to these deep dives, it seems like I’m going to have to get through the rest of the Spotify tracks one playlist at a time. Up next is &lt;em&gt;Classical Sleep&lt;/em&gt;, where there are some interesting connections to wider conversations about streaming platforms, including metadata and how artists get paid, and the whole universe of streaming-first artists fostered by Spotify. In-between the digressions, there will also be interesting music to listen to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;playlist-methodology-and-data&quot;&gt;Playlist, Methodology, and Data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can listen to all of the pieces featured in this playlist analysis series here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/playlist/6vQwkvRqWbGEF5IKZmC6na?si=1829c2da26b84f03&quot;&gt;Spotify: Classical Deep Dive - Spotify &amp;amp; Apple Music&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full methodology notes for all my music posts can be found via the &lt;a href=&quot;/exploring-orchestral-music-methodology/&quot;&gt;Main Methodology Page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Details and data for the streaming service playlists analysis can be found on the &lt;a href=&quot;/exploring-orchestral-music-methodology/streaming-service-demographic-analysis.html&quot;&gt;Streaming Analysis Methodology Page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More details about how I used the data from the Institute for Composer Diversity to create the comparison to US orchestra mainstage seasons can be found on the &lt;a href=&quot;/exploring-orchestral-music-methodology/ICD-orchestra-season-analysis.html&quot;&gt;ICD 2019/20 Season Analysis Methodology Page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ch%C3%B4ros&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chôros&lt;/em&gt; on Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Page 265. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Page 359 of &lt;em&gt;The American Symphony Orchestra: A Social History of Musical Taste&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;From their bio, it seems like the Solistes Européens, Luxembourg claim to be the NBA all star team of European orchestras, but maybe that’s just marketing. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If I were to guess, I think you can hear it around 11:00? &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><category term="Music" /><summary type="html">Diving Deeper into Spotify</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Building an Orchestra Season Visualization Tool</title><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/programming/2021/07/03/building-orchestra-season-visualization-tool.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building an Orchestra Season Visualization Tool" /><published>2021-07-03T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-07-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/programming/2021/07/03/building-orchestra-season-visualization-tool</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tallcoleman.me/programming/2021/07/03/building-orchestra-season-visualization-tool.html">&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/music/2020/12/30/exploring-orchestral-music-race-gender-representation-composers.html&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I had made a diagram to show the common structure of orchestra concerts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/MW Concerts Format 19-20 with legend.png&quot; alt=&quot;Visualization showing the length of pieces in Toronto Symphony MasterWorks Concerts&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After making it, it occurred to me that this kind of diagram would be useful to demonstrate other attributes of an orchestra season, especially some of the qualitative aspects of composer representation (which were discussed in that post).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make the original diagram, I built a stacked bar chart in excel, and then coloured each piece according to their category manually. It worked once as a proof of concept, but was way too cumbsersome a method to use repeatedly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;initial-attempts&quot;&gt;Initial Attempts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To try to simplify the creation process, I first tried to see if could make the chart in R using &lt;a href=&quot;https://ggplot2.tidyverse.org/&quot;&gt;ggplot&lt;/a&gt;. However, I wasn’t able to assign colours using values that were unrelated to those invovled in creating the stacked bar chart itself. Perhaps this is possible, but I don’t know ggplot that well, so I wasn’t able to make it work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also interested in interactivity (e.g. being able to click one of the bar segments and see information about which piece it represents), so I tried making a stacked bar chart using DataWrapper:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Season Vis&quot; aria-label=&quot;Stacked Bars&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-xQNLw&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/xQNLw/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;224&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This worked &lt;em&gt;pretty&lt;/em&gt; well as a proof of concept. However, it still had a number of drawbacks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;no way to show piece information on click&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hard to distinguish between data elements with the same colour (see the two symphonies in Concert B)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cumbersome to make for datasets of any complexity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To explain the last point: the colour formatting is applied per-column, so to do the chart properly, you need to create a column for each unique combination of a piece’s position and category. If you download the data from the chart, you’ll see that the chart uses nine columns, because there are three pieces on each program multiplied by three potential categories for each piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This also makes the interactivity a bit odd - you’ll notice if you hover over the opening fanfare in Concert A, the opening fanfare in Concert C is also highlighted, because they’re both in the same column.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, having tested a couple of potentially-simpler options, I decided to take the plunge and make my own app to generate season visualizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;building-the-visualization-tool&quot;&gt;Building the Visualization Tool&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the Datawrapper test didn’t do exactly what I was looking for, examining how they structured the chart helped me figure out how to set up the styling and structure for the chart I wanted to make. After a bit of reverse engineering, I was able to make a HTML prototype of what the end result should look like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Structure Prototype&quot; src=&quot;/assets/Graphs/structurePrototype.html&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;270&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From there, I decided to make a client-side app (i.e. it just runs in the browser, no need for a server) since it seemed simple, safe, and could be hosted for free via github. Before this point, I had dabbled in Javascript to do simple things, like giving website viewers the choice to load an embedded spotify player, or making fancy footnotes. This project, unsurprisingly, was quite a bit harder, but I learned quite a lot by making it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I’ve done data manipulation before, I’ve usually used python/pandas or R. In comparison, Javascript is… less good. A couple examples that came to mind:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sort this 2D data by its second column:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;pandas: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;dataframe.sort_values('col2')&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Javascript: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;array.sort((a,b) =&amp;gt; a[1] - b[1])&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Give me the second column from this 2D data:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;pandas: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;dataframe['col2']&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Javascript: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;array.map(a =&amp;gt; a[1])&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK so maybe comparing base Javascript to a python data analysis library isn’t fair. Let’s do something basic, language to language:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Round this number to two decimal places:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;python: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;round(1.2345, 2)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Javascript: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Math.round(1.2345 * 100) / 100&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting back on track, the major milestones I remember include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;learning how to parse CSV data using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.papaparse.com/&quot;&gt;Papa Parse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;generating a graph from the CSV data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;making a system to style and customize the graph&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;using bootstrap to make the app pretty without trying very hard&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;making a proper system for the user to match the CSV data to the values needed to generate the chart&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;generating embeddable code that can be copied into blog posts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After putting all those pieces together, I was able to make a beta version of the app to start generating charts for blog posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find the beta (or any improved versions that may come later) on github &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/tallcoleman/orchestra-season-visualization&quot;&gt;github.com/tallcoleman/orchestra-season-visualization&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The live app can be found at &lt;a href=&quot;https://osv.tallcoleman.me&quot;&gt;osv.tallcoleman.me&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-end-result&quot;&gt;The End Result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the new version in all its glory - you can now use the Explore button to navigate around the chart and see the composer name and title for each piece:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script&gt;function alertsize(pixels, iframeID){pixels+=5;document.getElementById(iframeID).style.height=pixels+&quot;px&quot;;}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;iframe id=&quot;iframe-74528596&quot; title=&quot;Concert Format: TSO 2019/20 Season&quot; src=&quot;/assets/Graphs/tso1920formatTTI.html&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also made another version for fun, where the concerts are sorted by date instead of time to intermission:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script&gt;function alertsize(pixels, iframeID){pixels+=5;document.getElementById(iframeID).style.height=pixels+&quot;px&quot;;}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;iframe id=&quot;iframe-15688531&quot; title=&quot;Concert Format: TSO 2019/20 Season&quot; src=&quot;/assets/Graphs/tso1920formatCT.html&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m looking forward to using this in future posts - I have a couple data sets lined up already. If you think this is interesting, or potentially useful to you, &lt;a href=&quot;/about/#contact&quot;&gt;let me know&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><category term="Programming" /><category term="Music" /><summary type="html">In a previous post, I had made a diagram to show the common structure of orchestra concerts:</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Deep Dive: Composer Representation in Spotify Classical Playlists (Part One)</title><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/05/03/deep-dive-spotify-part-one.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deep Dive: Composer Representation in Spotify Classical Playlists (Part One)" /><published>2021-05-03T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-05-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/05/03/deep-dive-spotify-part-one</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/05/03/deep-dive-spotify-part-one.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-deep-dive-continues&quot;&gt;The Deep Dive Continues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To recap quickly from &lt;a href=&quot;/music/2021/03/01/deep-dive-apple-music.html&quot;&gt;my last post going through the Apple Music playlists&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My goal for this blog series was to write about ways to explore and enjoy orchestral music. So, as part of going over the Spotify and Apple Music stats in detail, I wanted to highlight the small number of composers in each playlist that were women, Black, Indigenous, and/or people of colour. This way, you can discover more about them and get to know their music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve just landed here, or haven’t read the Apple Music post, make sure to read &lt;a href=&quot;/music/2021/03/01/deep-dive-apple-music.html#using-201920-orchestra-seasons-as-a-benchmark&quot;&gt;the notes explaining the “Average US Orchestra” comparator&lt;/a&gt; I’m using below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;spotify&quot;&gt;Spotify&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Representation of composers on Spotify was a bit better than on Apple Music, especially for composers of colour. The other thing that is notably different between the two platforms is that Spotify has historically had a much stronger focus on mood-themed playlists, so there are more streaming-first artists in some of the playlists I examined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;classical-essentials&quot;&gt;Classical Essentials&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Classical Essentials&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;If Average US Orchestra&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Tracks&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;172&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Women&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;7 (4.1%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;14&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Black / People of Colour&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;3 (1.7%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Women of Colour&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;none&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Living&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;20 (11.6%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;28&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compared to the &lt;a href=&quot;/music/2021/03/01/deep-dive-apple-music.html#classical-essentials&quot;&gt;equivalent playlist on Apple Music&lt;/a&gt;, Spotify &lt;em&gt;Classical Essentials&lt;/em&gt; has a slightly higher representation of women composers, and actually has some composers who are Black or people of colour. The proportion of living composers is also significantly higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;samuel-coleridge-taylor-symphonic-variations-on-an-african-air-op63&quot;&gt;Samuel Coleridge-Taylor: Symphonic Variations on an African Air, Op.63&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samuel_Coleridge-Taylor&quot;&gt;Samuel Coleridge-Taylor&lt;/a&gt; (15 August 1875 – 1 September 1912) was an English composer and conductor.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Of mixed race birth, Coleridge-Taylor achieved such success that he was referred to by white New York musicians as the “African Mahler” when he had three tours of the United States in the early 1900s. He was particularly known for his three cantatas on the epic poem, Song of Hiawatha by American Henry Wadsworth Longfellow. Coleridge-Taylor premiered the first section in 1898, when he was 22.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to write a whole post on this piece at some point. There are a lot of interesting choices to make in a theme and variations format and I think Coleridge-Taylor does a good job of transforming a spiritual (&lt;em&gt;I’m Troubled in Mind&lt;/em&gt;) into several different styles of music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to listen to a version of the source material, you can check out this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=POSaaCOJiq0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;recording by the Southern University Quartet&lt;/a&gt;. Also important to note that &lt;em&gt;I’m Troubled in Mind&lt;/em&gt; is not the same as &lt;em&gt;Trouble In Mind&lt;/em&gt;, which is a blues standard, though &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trouble_in_Mind_(song)#Lyrics_and_composition&quot;&gt;it seems like the two songs are related&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;astor-piazzolla-libertango&quot;&gt;Astor Piazzolla: Libertango&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Astor_Piazzolla&quot;&gt;Astor Pantaleón Piazzolla&lt;/a&gt; (March 11, 1921 – July 4, 1992) was an Argentine tango composer, bandoneon player, and arranger. His works revolutionized the traditional tango into a new style termed Nuevo tango, incorporating elements from jazz and classical music. A virtuoso bandoneonist, he regularly performed his own compositions with a variety of ensembles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will perhaps be unsurprised to learn that this song by  “the world’s foremost composer of Tango music” will make you want to dance. The track on Spotify is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/track/0mcgXc8P5GyGtP9aY7zir6?si=hWvtm1sbQcarPSoTJbBfgg&quot;&gt;trumpet version by Alison Balsom&lt;/a&gt; but I also highly recommend &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nIN3IE3DHqc&quot;&gt;Grace Jones’ cover&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;takashi-yoshimatsu-saxophone-concerto-op-59-cyber-bird-i-bird-in-colors-allegro&quot;&gt;Takashi Yoshimatsu: Saxophone Concerto, Op. 59, “Cyber-bird”: I. Bird in Colors: Allegro&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Takashi_Yoshimatsu&quot;&gt;Takashi Yoshimatsu&lt;/a&gt; (吉松 隆, Yoshimatsu Takashi) (born March 18, 1953) is a contemporary Japanese composer of classical music. He is well known for composing the 2003 remake of Astro Boy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bsomusic.org/stories/infographic-the-hierarchy-of-solo-instruments.aspx&quot;&gt;The majority of concertos performed are for piano, violin, and to a slightly lesser extent, cello&lt;/a&gt;. So I would absolutely buy tickets to see this, especially with a name as cool as “Cyber Bird”. It’s an excellent concerto. Also: Yoshimatsu has a bird-themed album with fantastic cover art. How could I not be a fan?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Cover Art - Yoshimatsu Symphonic Exhibition of Birds.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tori no Kyohten - Symphonic Exhibition of Birds&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;jess-gillam-merry-christmas-mr-lawrence-arr-metcalfe&quot;&gt;Jess Gillam: Merry Christmas Mr. Lawrence (Arr. Metcalfe)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jess_Gillam&quot;&gt;Jess Gillam&lt;/a&gt; (born 24 May 1998) is a British saxophonist and BBC radio broadcaster from Ulverston, Cumbria. Gillam hosts This Classical Life on BBC Radio 3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe I spent too much time in high school band, but I don’t usually think of Saxophone as a “light and airy” instrument. A really incredible performance here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;germaine-tailleferre-string-quartet-i-modere&quot;&gt;Germaine Tailleferre: String Quartet: I. Modere&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Germaine_Tailleferre&quot;&gt;Germaine Tailleferre&lt;/a&gt; (born Marcelle Germaine Taillefesse; 19 April 1892 – 7 November 1983) was a French composer and the only female member of the group of composers known as Les Six.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The melodies in this quartet are a little abstract for my taste, but I do really like how it feels like a story told through a number of sometimes-complex emotional states. The history of &lt;em&gt;Les Six&lt;/em&gt; is also pretty fascinating, including their role in popularizing &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Le_Boeuf_sur_le_Toit_(cabaret)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Le Boeuf sur le Toit&lt;/em&gt;, a bar that was “the epicenter of the Paris of the Roaring Twenties”&lt;/a&gt;. This bar apparently originated the French expression for musicians to jam together: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.collinsdictionary.com/dictionary/english-french/jam&quot;&gt;“faire un boeuf”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;nadia-boulanger-3-pieces-for-cello-and-piano-no-1-modere&quot;&gt;Nadia Boulanger: 3 Pieces for cello and piano: No. 1. Modere&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nadia_Boulanger&quot;&gt;Juliette Nadia Boulanger&lt;/a&gt; (16 September 1887 – 22 October 1979) was a French composer, conductor, and teacher. She is notable for having taught many of the leading composers and musicians of the 20th century. She also performed occasionally as a pianist and organist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this is really beautiful, and it makes excellent use of the cello’s upper range. The other two parts of the &lt;em&gt;3 Pieces&lt;/em&gt; are also worth a listen: #2 is lyrical and sweet, and #3 is energetic and fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nadia’s &lt;em&gt;Lux Aeterna&lt;/em&gt; was also featured on the &lt;a href=&quot;/music/2021/03/01/deep-dive-apple-music.html#lili-boulanger--nadia-boulanger-lux-aeterna-for-voice-harp-violin-and-cello&quot;&gt;Apple Music Classical Essentials playlist&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;louise-farrenc-nonet-in-e-flat-major-op-38-iii-scherzo-vivace&quot;&gt;Louise Farrenc: Nonet in E-Flat Major, Op. 38: III. Scherzo. Vivace&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louise_Farrenc&quot;&gt;Louise Farrenc&lt;/a&gt; (née Jeanne-Louise Dumont; 31 May 1804 – 15 September 1875) was a French composer, virtuoso pianist and teacher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nine is an interesting number of musicians to have — you can blur the line between chamber and small-orchestra music. Farrenc’s Nonet, which uses the most common instrumentation of combining a wind quintet with a string quartet (with a double bass instead of a second violin) is essentially a symphony, with fewer players. She wrote it after already completing three symphonies, and I think it shows in her talented use of form and different instrumental voices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listening to this made me think about one of the things that’s interesting about orchestral music, which is that instruments can serve so many different roles during one piece. Sometimes it’s establishing rhythm, sometimes it’s providing harmony, sometimes it’s playing the melody, and other times it’s playing for accent or effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;jessica-curry-finding-the-pattern&quot;&gt;Jessica Curry: Finding the Pattern&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jessica_Curry&quot;&gt;Jessica Curry&lt;/a&gt; (born c. 1973) is an English composer, radio presenter and former co-head of the British video game development studio The Chinese Room. She won a BAFTA award in 2016 for her score for the video game &lt;em&gt;Everybody’s Gone to the Rapture&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the most popular track from the &lt;em&gt;Everybody’s Gone to the Rapture&lt;/em&gt; video game (on Spotify anyway). I’ll have to ask my girlfriend nicely to borrow her Windows computer so I can play this game. Several of the reviews I read about it mention how good the music is and how well it was used to emphasize emotional moments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It must have been bittersweet to win a BAFTA after &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20160402170520/http://www.thechineseroom.co.uk/blog/blog/why-im-sort-of-leaving-the-chinese-room&quot;&gt;announcing she would be distancing herself from The Chinese Room&lt;/a&gt; because of her health and because her experiences as a woman in the video game industry were so awful. However, judging by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jessicacurry.co.uk/&quot;&gt;the projects listed on her website&lt;/a&gt;, it looks like she was successful in broadening her music-making beyond video games, with a number of interesting standalone pieces and commissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After The Chinese Room went through a rebirth and new ownership, Curry composed music for their 2020 game, &lt;em&gt;Little Orpheus&lt;/em&gt;, which was released on Apple Arcade. Unfortunately, like with &lt;em&gt;Everybody’s Gone to the Rapture&lt;/em&gt;, I don’t have the right device to play it: my iPhone is too old &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and I haven’t upgraded my mac to Catalina yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; After more than five years of dutiful service, my iPhone 6 died, so I was able to play a couple levels of &lt;em&gt;Little Orpheus&lt;/em&gt; on my new phone. The soundtrack is pretty good, and you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/album/4IA6Bfoh3204cQrL58aqtK?si=kJPIfwZhRGWAa6PPCQr38A&quot;&gt;listen to it on Spotify&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although you can find a soundtrack album for most video games, sometimes part of the experience is missing if you just listen to the music and haven’t played the game before. If you’ve played the game, your memories of the entire experience, including the gameplay and the visuals, become part of the listening experience. In addition, sometimes there’s clever integration of the gameplay with the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, (if I remember correctly), there’s a part where you’re hiding in a giant eggshell and trying to cross a bridge without being seen by a guard. When the guard is looking away, and you need to move, the music gets louder and more energetic. When the guard looks over at the bridge — and you need to drop down and hide yourself under the egg — it becomes very quiet, adding to the tension of trying not to be discovered. I think the track from the soundtrack album is &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/track/5eOK2lcWoMBSjCDo3zaQJs?si=5e22f618498748b6&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stealing Eggs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Either the shift in dynamics is programmatically triggered, as is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.musicnotes.com/now/omg/adaptive-video-game-scores/&quot;&gt;common in video game music&lt;/a&gt;, or the music is perfectly timed to the gameplay cycle. Either way, it’s a neat effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;amy-beach-young-birches-op-128-no-2&quot;&gt;Amy Beach: Young Birches, Op. 128, No. 2&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amy_Beach&quot;&gt;Amy Marcy Cheney Beach&lt;/a&gt; (September 5, 1867 – December 27, 1944) was an American composer and pianist. She was the first successful American female composer of large-scale art music. Her “Gaelic” Symphony, premiered by the Boston Symphony Orchestra in 1896, was the first symphony composed and published by an American woman. She was one of the first American composers to succeed without the benefit of European training, and one of the most respected and acclaimed American composers of her era. As a pianist, she was acclaimed for concerts she gave featuring her own music in the United States and in Germany.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is actually part of a set of three nature-themed piano pieces (the other two are about a chipmunk and a hummingbird, respectively). I love program music and Amy Beach does a great job of capturing the essence of these animals and plants in this trio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;barbara-strozzi-amor-dormiglione&quot;&gt;Barbara Strozzi: Amor dormiglione&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barbara_Strozzi&quot;&gt;Barbara Strozzi&lt;/a&gt; (also called Barbara Valle; baptised 6 August 1619  – 11 November 1677) was an Italian singer and composer of the Baroque Period. During her lifetime, Strozzi published eight volumes of her own music, having more music in print than any other composer of the era. This was made possible without any support from the Church or consistent patronage of the nobility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not usually a fan of Baroque music, but I like this piece. It has big folk song energy. Apparently the title means something along the lines of “sleepy cupid”; you can read a &lt;a href=&quot;https://barbarastrozzi.com/piece/amor-dormiglione/&quot;&gt;translation of the lyrics&lt;/a&gt; if you’re interested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barbara Strozzi is one of several women composers profiled in Anna Beer’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://oneworld-publications.com/sounds-and-sweet-airs-pb.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sounds And Sweet Airs: The Forgotten Women Of Classical Music&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is a book I was able to read part of before having to return it to the library. I’ll have to take it out again soon and re-read the Strozzi chapter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ai-cant-make-up-for-missing-metadata&quot;&gt;AI can’t make up for missing metadata&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that’s true about nearly all of the pieces listed here (but that I only noticed with the Amy Beach piece) — you can really see the effect of placement on an official playlist. Amy Beach’s &lt;em&gt;Young Birches&lt;/em&gt; has nearly 2 million plays, whereas &lt;em&gt;A Peterboro Chipmunk&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;A Humming Bird&lt;/em&gt; only average about 2,000 each. Similar orders of magnitude can be found for the other tracks that are part of a larger work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a quick experiment, I tried looking through the song radio for some of the tracks on this playlist to see if the other movements would show up. In a couple cases they did (e.g. the second movement of Nadia Boulanger’s &lt;em&gt;3 Pieces&lt;/em&gt; is #11 on song radio for the first movement), but in most cases, the other movements from the same piece were absent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A large part of this may be due to the fact that Spotify has no metadata to describe multi-movement pieces of music (Apple Music does, which is why movements from the same symphony are grouped in their UI). Perhaps if they did, it would be a useful signal for song radio. Goodness knows - if they can generate a logistic variable for “danceability”, they can probably manage a field or two to indicate tracks that should be grouped together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;up-next&quot;&gt;Up next&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part two of the Spotify deep dive will look at the &lt;em&gt;Orchestra 100: Spotify Picks&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;playlist-methodology-and-data&quot;&gt;Playlist, Methodology, and Data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can listen to all of the pieces featured in this playlist analysis series here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/playlist/6vQwkvRqWbGEF5IKZmC6na?si=1829c2da26b84f03&quot;&gt;Spotify: Classical Deep Dive - Spotify &amp;amp; Apple Music&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full methodology notes for all my music posts can be found via the &lt;a href=&quot;/exploring-orchestral-music-methodology/&quot;&gt;Main Methodology Page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Details and data for the streaming service playlists analysis can be found on the &lt;a href=&quot;/exploring-orchestral-music-methodology/streaming-service-demographic-analysis.html&quot;&gt;Streaming Analysis Methodology Page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More details about how I used the data from the Institute for Composer Diversity to create the comparison to US orchestra mainstage seasons can be found on the &lt;a href=&quot;/exploring-orchestral-music-methodology/ICD-orchestra-season-analysis.html&quot;&gt;ICD 2019/20 Season Analysis Methodology Page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;My iPhone 6 has had a longer useful life than the Nokia brick I had as a teenager, which is pretty impressive. I’m going to hold on to that headphone jack for as long as I can. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><category term="Music" /><summary type="html">The Deep Dive Continues</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A Google Docs Word Counter for Grant Writers</title><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/programming/2021/04/25/a-google-docs-word-counter-for-grant-writers.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Google Docs Word Counter for Grant Writers" /><published>2021-04-25T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-04-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/programming/2021/04/25/a-google-docs-word-counter-for-grant-writers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tallcoleman.me/programming/2021/04/25/a-google-docs-word-counter-for-grant-writers.html">&lt;p&gt;My girlfriend uses Scrivener for fiction writing, and I was recently checking out the features again because miraculously, Scrivener 3 was finally released for Windows and she bought it. (This is a big deal - Scrivener 3 for Mac came out in 2017 and there were times when it seemed like a Windows version might never ship.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scrivener is designed really well for solo writing, but when it comes to collaborative writing and commenting, Google Docs is much, much better. This makes it ideal for grant writing, and I’ve had very few complaints using Google Docs as my main writing tool. However, there is one feature from Scrivener that would be really nice to have for grant writing: a way of setting a word count and word limit for each question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/Scrivener Example.png&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot of the Scrivener application showing sections with word count targets&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Scrivener’s outline view allows you to get a quick overview of how your writing is coming along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good thing about Google Apps is that is has pretty extensive scripting support, so I was able to make a script to create wordcounts for each section in a document. You can find the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/tallcoleman/heading-word-counter&quot;&gt;script and its instructions on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, but I also made a quick demonstration video:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;video controls=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;&gt;&lt;source src=&quot;/assets/Videos/exampleclip.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/video&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, you can put a word limit in parentheses in the heading, and it will then add and update a word count within those parentheses as well. The word count also gets a highlight colour to serve as a quick visual indicator of how close you are to the word limit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that’s a bit frustrating is that, unlike in Google Sheets, there’s no trigger you can set up in Google Docs to run the script after you make an edit. So the best I was able to do for now is to provide a menu to run the script on command; in addition, the script will run on a time trigger every minute. (Once per minute is as often as Apps Script allows).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the trigger limitations, it works pretty well, and I’m going to try using it and try to make additional refinements over time. I’m also going to dig deeper into different word count algorithms so that I can make sure the word count used in the script handles some of the odd edge cases in the same way that Google Docs does. I’ve also encountered some cases where grant portals count words slightly differently than google docs, and it would be interesting to try to figure out why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re looking for a session word count target as a writing motivator (another well-loved Scrivener feature), you can check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://workspace.google.com/marketplace/app/word_counter_max_for_google_docs/364683295233?hl=en&amp;amp;pann=docs_addon_widget&quot;&gt;Word Counter Max add-on&lt;/a&gt;, which looks like it would also be a pretty useful tool for grant writers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><category term="Programming" /><summary type="html">My girlfriend uses Scrivener for fiction writing, and I was recently checking out the features again because miraculously, Scrivener 3 was finally released for Windows and she bought it. (This is a big deal - Scrivener 3 for Mac came out in 2017 and there were times when it seemed like a Windows version might never ship.)</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Deep Dive: Composer Representation in Apple Music Classical Playlists</title><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/03/01/deep-dive-apple-music.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deep Dive: Composer Representation in Apple Music Classical Playlists" /><published>2021-03-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-03-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/03/01/deep-dive-apple-music</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/03/01/deep-dive-apple-music.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-deep-dive&quot;&gt;The Deep Dive&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal for this blog series was to write about ways to explore and enjoy orchestral music. So, as part of going over the Spotify and Apple Music stats in detail, I wanted to highlight the small number of composers in each playlist that were women, Black, Indigenous, and/or people of colour. This way, you can discover more about them and get to know their music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a really interesting range of artists featured on both streaming services, ranging from composers from as early as the 17th century to some modern musicians who have built careers in and around the streaming platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;using-201920-orchestra-seasons-as-a-benchmark&quot;&gt;Using 2019/20 orchestra seasons as a benchmark&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To provide a benchmark, each playlist below is compared to a hypothetical playlist where the number of composers who are women; Black, Indigenous, or people of colour; or both is proportional to how often these composers are programmed by the average US orchestra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This “average US orchestra” calculation is based on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.composerdiversity.com/orchestra-seasons&quot;&gt;2019/20 season analysis of 120 US orchestras from the Institute for Composer Diversity&lt;/a&gt;. The ICD analysis found that only 7.9% of works on mainstage programs were by women composers, and only 5.6% were by composers from underrepresented racial, ethnic, or cultural heritages. A full summary of their findings is included in the table below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Full ICD List&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;“Top 21” from ICD List &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Orchestras&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;120&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;21&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Works Programmed&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;4075&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;1490&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Women&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;321 (7.9%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;104 (7.0%)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;BIPOC &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;236 (5.8%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;67 (4.5%)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;BIPOC Women&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;77 (1.9%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;24 (1.6%)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Living&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;658 (16.1%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;241 (16.2%)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;annotation-wrapper&quot; anchorid=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;annotation-wrapper&quot; anchorid=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#methodology&quot;&gt;More information about the methodology behind these numbers.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- Needs some fiddling with the CSS to make it work (e.g. H2 adds its own padding under the heading div) --&gt;
&lt;!-- also needs inclusion of footer; add to post template --&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;panel panel-warning&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;panel-warning panel-heading&quot;&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Labels for Composers who are Black, Indigenous, or People of Colour&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Since the intention of the BIPOC acronym is to specifically highlight the unique experiences of Black and Indigenous people, and not to be a catch-all for people who are not white, I’ve only used it in acronym form when talking about a group that includes all of the identities the acronym implies and when the acronym is warranted due to space limitations.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;When talking about a group that does not include all the identities that BIPOC implies, I’ve written out the specific identities that are included. When talking about an individual artist, I’ve tried to use their specific identity, as they describe it.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The NPR podcast &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/transcripts/918418825&quot;&gt;Code Switch had a good episode on the BIPOC acronym&lt;/a&gt; and
the various opinions people have about it.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;One important thing to note is that the labels used in the tables below only describe the specific identities of the composers actually featured in each playlist. However, the &lt;em&gt;Average US Orchestra&lt;/em&gt; numbers should always be understood to imply the potential for broader representation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;apple-music&quot;&gt;Apple Music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apple Music is often seen as a streaming platform that cares more about the experience of classical music listeners. Their app does a better job of displaying pieces of music that have multiple movements, and their metadata is more suited to the genre. Unlike Spotify, &lt;a href=&quot;/exploring-orchestral-music-methodology/streaming-service-demographic-analysis.html#analysis&quot;&gt;they have a pretty reliable “composer” field for most tracks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this increased attention to the genre hasn’t resulted in composer representation that keeps up with the field, as you can see in the playlists examined below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;classical-essentials&quot;&gt;Classical Essentials&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Classical Essentials&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;If Average US Orchestra&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Tracks&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;101&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Women&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;3 (3.0%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;People of Colour&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Women of Colour&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Living&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;4 (4.0%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;16&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, there are no composers of colour represented on this playlist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interesting thing about all of the three women composers on this playlist is that they are partially known for having deep musical and personal relationships with another person: Fanny Mendelssohn with her brother Felix, Nadia Boulanger, with her sister Lili, and Clara Schumann with her husband Robert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;fanny-mendelssohn-string-quartet-in-e-flat-major-i-adagio-ma-non-troppo&quot;&gt;Fanny Mendelssohn: String Quartet in E-Flat Major: I. Adagio ma non troppo&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fanny_Mendelssohn&quot;&gt;Fanny Mendelssohn&lt;/a&gt; (14 November 1805 – 14 May 1847), later Fanny [Cäcilie] Mendelssohn Bartholdy and, after her marriage, Fanny Hensel, also referred to as Fanny Mendelssohn Hensel, was a German composer and pianist of the early Romantic era. Her compositions include a piano trio, a piano quartet, an orchestral overture, four cantatas, more than 125 pieces for the piano, and over 250 lieder, most of which went unpublished in her lifetime. Although praised for her piano technique, she rarely gave public performances outside her family circle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first movement of this string quartet is really good - I see why they chose it for the playlist. Apparently she never formally learned to play any string instruments, and also &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fanny_Mendelssohn#Compositions&quot;&gt;was self-deprecating about this particular piece&lt;/a&gt;, which I think is sad:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;She was also undoubtedly hampered by the fact that, unlike her brother, she had never studied or played any string instruments, experience which would have assisted her in writing chamber or orchestral works… After completing her string quartet, she wrote to Felix in 1835, “I lack the ability to sustain ideas properly and give them the needed consistency. Therefore lieder suit me best, in which, if need be, merely a pretty idea without much potential for development can suffice.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;lili-boulanger--nadia-boulanger-lux-aeterna-for-voice-harp-violin-and-cello&quot;&gt;Lili Boulanger &amp;amp; Nadia Boulanger: Lux Aeterna (For Voice, Harp, Violin And Cello)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nadia_Boulanger&quot;&gt;Juliette Nadia Boulanger&lt;/a&gt; (16 September 1887 – 22 October 1979) was a French composer, conductor, and teacher. She is notable for having taught many of the leading composers and musicians of the 20th century. She also performed occasionally as a pianist and organist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lili_Boulanger&quot;&gt;Marie-Juliette Olga “Lili” Boulanger&lt;/a&gt; (21 August 1893 – 15 March 1918) was a French composer, and the first female winner of the Prix de Rome composition prize. Her older sister was the noted composer and composition teacher Nadia Boulanger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The history of this piece is quite interesting — in an article titled &lt;em&gt;Nadia and Lili Boulanger: Sister Composers&lt;/em&gt;, Dr. Caroline Potter notes that &lt;em&gt;Lux Aeterna&lt;/em&gt; is the second version of the song; the first was &lt;em&gt;Cantique&lt;/em&gt;, a setting of a poem from a play named &lt;em&gt;Soeur Béatrice&lt;/em&gt; by Belgian playwright Maurice Maeterlinck &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Dr. Potter observes that &lt;em&gt;Cantique&lt;/em&gt; is heavily influenced by Gabriel Fauré’s &lt;em&gt;Lydia&lt;/em&gt; and has very similar opening chords &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Nadia Boulanger later re-orchestrated &lt;em&gt;Cantique&lt;/em&gt; and set it to the text of the &lt;em&gt;Lux Aeterna&lt;/em&gt; for a mass commemorating Lili’s (early) death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Apple Music credits the song to both sisters, this seems to be incorrect. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2011126201.html&quot;&gt;Library of Congress credits Nadia as the sole composer&lt;/a&gt;, though it notes that she intended to have her orchestration match Lili’s &lt;em&gt;Pie Jesu&lt;/em&gt; in the reworking of the song. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.naxos.com/mainsite/blurbs_reviews.asp?item_code=8.223636&amp;amp;catNum=223636&amp;amp;filetype=About%20this%20Recording&amp;amp;language=English&quot;&gt;liner notes for the album&lt;/a&gt; note that “Since 1918, Nadia’s &lt;em&gt;Lux Aeterna&lt;/em&gt; and Lili’s &lt;em&gt;Pie Jesu&lt;/em&gt; have been sung every 15th March at a memorial Mass in Paris”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;clara-schumann-scherzo-no-2-in-c-minor-op-14&quot;&gt;Clara Schumann: Scherzo No. 2 in C Minor, Op. 14&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clara_Schumann&quot;&gt;Clara Josephine Schumann&lt;/a&gt; (née Wieck; 13 September 1819 – 20 May 1896) was a German pianist, composer and piano teacher. Regarded as one of the most distinguished pianists of the Romantic era, she exerted her influence over a 61-year concert career, changing the format and repertoire of the piano recital from displays of virtuosity to programs of serious works. She also composed solo piano pieces, a piano concerto (her Op. 7), chamber music, choral pieces, and songs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like this piece, Isata Kanneh-Mason recorded a whole &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/album/7Jt7TzZQgrMsJgI7CPyApE?si=DPiJdpJoQ-qiRhorHxMP2A&quot;&gt;album of pieces by Clara Schumann&lt;/a&gt; in 2019, including this one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;relaxing-classical&quot;&gt;Relaxing Classical&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Relaxing Classical&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;If Average US Orchestra&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Tracks&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;50&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Women&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;2 (4.0%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;People of Colour&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Women of Colour&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Living&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;2 (4.0%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, no composers of colour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While researching both of the women composers featured on this playlist, I came across the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.swedishmusicalheritage.com/&quot;&gt;Swedish Musical Heritage Website&lt;/a&gt;, which is a project initiated by The Royal Swedish Academy of Music. Thanks to this site, you can read detailed biographies for both composers and even download a lot of their sheet music for free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;helena-munktell-kleines-trio-ii-andante-espressivo&quot;&gt;Helena Munktell: Kleines Trio: II. Andante espressivo&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Helena_Munktell&quot;&gt;Helena Mathilda Munktell&lt;/a&gt; (24 November 1852 – 10 September 1919) was a Swedish composer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the &lt;a href=&quot;https://bis.se/helena-munktell-violin-sonata-dix-melodies-kleines-trio&quot;&gt;liner notes&lt;/a&gt;: “The third work on this disc is a small-scale piano trio, probably an early work and possibly composed for performance at one of the musical salons at the Munktell family home in Stockholm.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were no works by Munktell included in the League analysis of 120 US orchestra mainstage programs, however, there is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/album/7FyUzdTN1C8U1uekkOLsZU?si=su8cZTqpTtqCo16MNjNfOA&quot;&gt;2005 album of her orchestral works by the Gälve Symphony Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;. An untapped opportunity for orchestras looking to increase the number of women on the program, perhaps. Despite the fact that I spent a lot of a &lt;a href=&quot;/music/2020/12/30/exploring-orchestral-music-race-gender-representation-composers.html&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; talking about how women and people of colour should be programmed more in the back half of orchestra programs, I think her symphonic poem &lt;em&gt;Bränningar&lt;/em&gt; (Breaking Waves) would make a great opener.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.swedishmusicalheritage.com/composers/munktell-helena/&quot;&gt;Biography of Helena Munktell on Swedish Musical Heritage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;amanda-rontgen-maier-violin-sonata-in-b-minor-ii-andantino&quot;&gt;Amanda Rontgen-Maier: Violin Sonata in B Minor: II. Andantino&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amanda_R%C3%B6ntgen-Maier&quot;&gt;Amanda Röntgen-Maier&lt;/a&gt; (20 February 1853 – 15 July 1894) was a Swedish violinist and composer. She was the first female graduate in music direction from the Royal College of Music in Stockholm in 1872.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favourite fact about this Sonata, according to her biography, is that when she submitted it to the Swedish Art Music Society, one of the three men who reviewed it suggested she change the slow movement. To which she basically said “no, I like it too much the way it is”. The result: “The sonata was printed without any alterations and published in 1878.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.swedishmusicalheritage.com/composers/maier-rontgen-amanda/&quot;&gt;Biography of Amanda Röntgen-Maier on Swedish Musical Heritage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-a-list-classical&quot;&gt;The A-List: Classical&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;The A-List: Classical&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;If Average US Orchestra&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Tracks&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;51&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Women&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;2 (3.9%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Black / People of Colour&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;2 (3.9%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Women of Colour&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Living&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;5 (9.8%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I understand it, Apple Music’s “A-List” playlists are where they program new releases. The kinds of music on this playlist range from new recordings of the kinds of classical composers you might see on an orchestra program to instrumental streaming artists who primarily make their living based on placement on mood-themed playlists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of the two composers of colour that were featured on this playlist are in the latter category of musicians who have made careers primarily as streaming artists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;sofiane-pamart-san-francisco&quot;&gt;Sofiane Pamart: San Francisco&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sofiane_Pamart&quot;&gt;Sofiane Pamart&lt;/a&gt; is a French pianist, based in Paris and originally from Hellemmes in the suburbs of Lille. He is known to the French public for breaking the elitist codes of classical piano.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every track on Pamart’s &lt;em&gt;Planet Gold&lt;/em&gt; album is geographically-named, so consider this a fun way to get the thrill of travelling while staying safe at home. &lt;em&gt;San Francisco&lt;/em&gt; in particular I thought was pretty hypnotic and cinematic. It reminded me a lot of Christopher Larkin’s very popular &lt;a href=&quot;https://christopherlarkin.bandcamp.com/album/hollow-knight-original-soundtrack&quot;&gt;Hollow Knight soundtrack&lt;/a&gt;, which I think speaks to Pamart’s ability to create a strong sense of atmosphere that really fuels your imagination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;alexis-ffrench-a-time-for-giving&quot;&gt;Alexis Ffrench: A Time for Giving&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexis_Ffrench&quot;&gt;Alexis Ffrench&lt;/a&gt; (born 1970) is a British classical soul pioneer, composer, producer and pianist. Not only is Ffrench the UK’s biggest selling pianist of 2020, he has headlined London’s Royal Albert Hall, collaborated with fashion houses Miyake and Hugo Boss, played Latitude Festival, worked with Paloma Faith, composed several film scores and shares the same management team as Little Mix and Niall Horan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This reminds me of the kinds of music my mum used to play on the piano while people were coming in to church. Which makes sense in a certain way — &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.voice-online.co.uk/article/im-always-trying-retain-spirituality-my-music&quot;&gt;Alexis Ffrench often talks about how he grew up playing the organ at church and the role that spirituality has in his music&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like this song, you should also check out his &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3_YNupMR6A4&quot;&gt;performance of the Bluebird Suite with orchestra at the Classic BRIT Awards 2018&lt;/a&gt;, which also features South African singer Pretty Yende.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;streaming-artists-and-their-audience&quot;&gt;Streaming Artists and Their Audience&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Artists who have been able to make a career on streaming platforms playing classical instruments often get asked in interviews some variant of a question “how do you feel about the fact that you’re not making &lt;em&gt;serious&lt;/em&gt; classical music?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the implication is that their talent is being wasted on an audience who is primarily assumed to be writing emails while listening, other times it’s a nastier implication that they make simple, uncomplicated music with little “high art” merit. I don’t think it’s a particularly fair or meaningful question, but I do find that the variety of responses that these artists give is interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best answers seem to turn the question on its head: instead of being about “is your art valuable” (as judged by the existing gatekeepers), it becomes about the relationship each artist has with their audience, and the value that the audience gets from their music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://panm360.com/en/interviews-panm360/les-mondes-de-sofiane-pamart/&quot;&gt;Sofiane Pamart talks about this&lt;/a&gt; in a recent interview:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;How do you respond to the classical purists, who remain unconvinced?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;… The important thing is to touch, to be moved. That goes beyond the technical repertoire. That comes later. It’s interesting to understand how an artist creates, but that comes later. I’m very happy to move away from that. If it does you good to tell you that there are winks at Debussy, I’m very happy, and if you have no classical references and it makes you think of film music or something else, I’m very comfortable with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.standard.co.uk/culture/alexis-ffrench-interview-classical-music-needs-to-be-more-provocative-to-survive-a3866271.html&quot;&gt;Alexis Ffrench has a good answer too&lt;/a&gt;, I think:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Crucially, this means “breaking down perceived barriers”, therefore the power of the three-and-a-half-minute message should not be underestimated. “You can write 40-minute symphonies, but it’s more important to me to connect with people at this stage.” All of his singles on Spotify are under four minutes long and his new album is “tuneful,” despite many classical artists seeing this a “dirty word”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.standaard.be/cnt/dmf20210108_97760578?adh_i=&amp;amp;imai=&amp;amp;articlehash=CCA16B79E2A7BEBE80A47827F93058CF1FD977FAC79F5EF802575F1CBE816ED8D09D95989DDD769F6DBA00D6A10D290093FC25920ABB3BD55ECF2D337719A86D&quot;&gt;the most entertaining answer I found was from streaming artist Jef Martens&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Doesn’t it bother that the compositions you work so hard on are often listened to as background music?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;‘There are also Debussy arrangements, or pieces by Vikingur Olafsson. Just because people use them as a background doesn’t mean the music is bad. And apart from that: is one listener worth more than another? When I bring someone to a transcendental metaphysical insight with my music, I love it. And if I can help an official through his first tax check on a Monday morning, that’s fine.’
&lt;br /&gt;[Via Google Translate - the original article is in Dutch]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/11/25/arts/music/peter-gelb-met-opera.html&quot;&gt;Even Peter Gelb answers emails while listening to the Met Opera rehearse&lt;/a&gt;. That’s the great thing about music: it can be enjoyed many different ways. Sometimes it can bring joy to your life in the background, and sometimes it can be an all-encompassing artistic experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;milana-zilnik-dicembre&quot;&gt;Milana Zilnik: Dicembre&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.milana.ws/biography/&quot;&gt;Milana&lt;/a&gt; is a multi-award winning pianist, composer and singer-songwriter, who has been a performing and recording artist since her childhood. A strong lyricist and composer in her own right, Milana’s style is reminiscent of Tori Amos, Sarah McLachlan, Michael Nyman, Keith Jarret and Chick Corea. Milana enjoys playing by ear, improvising and using whatever inspires her to create her own style of playing. She is known as an adept improviser, catching melodies on the fly and expanding them into her own creations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Canadian!! I too would write sad piano music if I lived in Ottawa year-round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;amanda-rontgen-maier-violin-sonata-in-b-minor-ii-andantino-1&quot;&gt;Amanda Rontgen-Maier: Violin Sonata in B Minor: II. Andantino&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This track was &lt;a href=&quot;#amanda-rontgen-maier-violin-sonata-in-b-minor-ii-andantino&quot;&gt;also featured in Apple Music’s &lt;em&gt;Relaxing Classical&lt;/em&gt; playlist&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;classical-kids&quot;&gt;Classical Kids&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Classical Kids&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;If Average US Orchestra&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Tracks &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;50&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Women&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;People of Colour&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Women of Colour&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Living&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;9 (18.0%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;annotation-wrapper&quot; anchorid=&quot;fn:5&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theoretical underpinning of this whole exercise is “what classical music do new listeners find on streaming platforms”, and no listeners are newer than children. Pretty disappointing that this whole playlist has no women or people of colour at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, music for children has the same representation issues as music for any other audience. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.billboard.com/articles/news/awards/9506870/childrens-music-album-grammy-nominees-withdraw-lack-diversity/&quot;&gt;Billboard recently reported&lt;/a&gt; that “three of this year’s five Grammy nominees for best children’s music album asked the Recording Academy to withdraw their nominations to signal their disappointment that all the nominees in the category are white and only one is female.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;next-up-spotify&quot;&gt;Next Up: Spotify&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Spotify classical playlists were longer than those on Apple Music, and had greater representation of composers who are women and composers who are Black, Indigenous, or people of colour. So I’ll split my Spotify deep dive into two or three posts so that I can talk about all the tracks in proper detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;playlist-methodology-and-data&quot;&gt;Playlist, Methodology, and Data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can listen to all of the pieces featured in this playlist analysis series here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/playlist/6vQwkvRqWbGEF5IKZmC6na?si=1829c2da26b84f03&quot;&gt;Spotify: Classical Deep Dive - Spotify &amp;amp; Apple Music&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full methodology notes for all my music posts can be found via the &lt;a href=&quot;/exploring-orchestral-music-methodology/&quot;&gt;Main Methodology Page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Details and data for the streaming service playlists analysis can be found on the &lt;a href=&quot;/exploring-orchestral-music-methodology/streaming-service-demographic-analysis.html&quot;&gt;Streaming Analysis Methodology Page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More details about how I used the data from the Institute for Composer Diversity to create the comparison to US orchestra mainstage seasons can be found on the &lt;a href=&quot;/exploring-orchestral-music-methodology/ICD-orchestra-season-analysis.html&quot;&gt;ICD 2019/20 Season Analysis Methodology Page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This subgroup of 21 of the largest US orchestras will come up later when I talk about the ICD analysis in more detail. It is the original group analyzed by the Baltimore Symphony for the 2014/15 season and the group that has continued to be analyzed by Women’s Philharmonic Advocacy from 2016/17 to the present. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The designation used by the Institute for Composer Diversity is “Composers from Underrepresented Racial, Ethnic, or Cultural Heritages”. My understanding is that this comprises composers who are Black, Indigenous, or people of colour. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Potter, Caroline. “Nadia and Lili Boulanger: Sister Composers.” The Musical Quarterly, vol. 83, no. 4, 1999, pp. 536–556. JSTOR, www.jstor.org/stable/742616. Accessed 24 Jan. 2021. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The key difference between the openings of Fauré’s &lt;em&gt;Lydia&lt;/em&gt; and Boulanger’s &lt;em&gt;Cantique&lt;/em&gt;, according to Dr. Potter, is that Fauré used the Lydian mode as a musical pun. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Of these 50, three of the tracks are nursery rhymes with no known composer, one did not have an identifiable composer listed (&lt;em&gt;Classical Piano Music for Baby Sleep&lt;/em&gt; by Baby Lullaby Academy), and one was not a piece of music, but rather an audiobook chapter read by Michael Morpurgo. These unknown composers are not omitted for the percentage calculations — &lt;a href=&quot;/exploring-orchestral-music-methodology/streaming-service-demographic-analysis.html#unknown-composers&quot;&gt;see the methodology section for more details&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><category term="Music" /><summary type="html">The Deep Dive</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Representation of Composers in Top Classical Playlists on Spotify and Apple Music</title><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/02/07/spotify-apple-music-classical-playlists-representation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Representation of Composers in Top Classical Playlists on Spotify and Apple Music" /><published>2021-02-07T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-02-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/02/07/spotify-apple-music-classical-playlists-representation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tallcoleman.me/music/2021/02/07/spotify-apple-music-classical-playlists-representation.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction-the-rise-of-streaming&quot;&gt;Introduction: The Rise of Streaming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Streaming is now the primary way that most people listen to music. &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@RIAA/charting-a-path-to-musics-sustainable-success-12a5625bbc7d#8e10&quot;&gt;According to the Recording Industry Association of America&lt;/a&gt;, streaming now accounts for 79% of U.S. music industry revenues &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Classical music has lagged behind in the overall trend towards streaming: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/news/entertainment-arts-46861984&quot;&gt;a report covered by the BBC in 2019&lt;/a&gt; showed that in the UK, CD sales were still dominant (and growing) in the classical genre. Classical streaming was much smaller as a proportion of the UK market (about a quarter of sales compared to two thirds overall) but catching up quickly. In fact, year over year growth in classical streaming was reported to be 42% compared to 33% for streaming overall. A recent article from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ludwig-van.com/toronto/2020/03/10/report-streaming-music-the-song-economy-classical-music/&quot;&gt;Ludwig van Toronto exploring the same figures in-depth&lt;/a&gt; speculated that “those figures are generally recognized to represent existing classical music lovers. Streaming is the way to get that new blood the classical music world is always looking for.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So — continuing the train of thought &lt;a href=&quot;/music/2020/12/30/exploring-orchestral-music-race-gender-representation-composers.html&quot;&gt;from my last post&lt;/a&gt; — when someone searches for “classical” in their streaming service of choice, what do they find?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they’re listening to some of the most popular classical or orchestral playlists on Spotify or Apple Music, you won’t hear many pieces by composers of colour, or women composers. In some cases you won’t hear them at all. In many cases, your chances of hearing such composers is two to three times higher at a local US symphony than it is on the top classical playlists on these major streaming platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary-classical-playlist-analysis&quot;&gt;Summary: Classical Playlist Analysis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this analysis, I examined top classical playlists — four from Apple Music, and four from Spotify — that you might find by searching “classical” or “orchestral” in each service and picking from the top results. I compared the number of composers that were women, Black, Indigenous, and people of colour in these playlists with similar numbers from the recent mainstage programs of 120 US orchestras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;us-orchestra-mainstage-seasons&quot;&gt;US Orchestra Mainstage Seasons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The comparator I’m using is from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.composerdiversity.com/orchestra-seasons&quot;&gt;Institute for Composer Diversity&lt;/a&gt;. From their 2019/20 season analysis, this is the representation of composers by number of times their pieces were programmed by orchestras:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Women&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;BIPOC&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;120 US Orchestras&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;7.9%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;5.8%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;21 “Top” US Orchestras&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;7.0%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;4.5%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;apple-music-summary&quot;&gt;Apple Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Official classical playlists on Apple Music consistently had about half the number of women composers compared to the average US orchestra mainstage season, and only their new releases playlist, &lt;em&gt;The A-List: Classical&lt;/em&gt;, had any pieces by composers of colour (one track by Sofiane Pamart and another by Alexis Ffrench). Apple Music’s &lt;em&gt;Classical Kids&lt;/em&gt; playlist in particular exclusively featured white men composers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Apple Music Playlist&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Women&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Black / POC&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Classical Essentials&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;3.0%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;none&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Relaxing Classical&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;4.0%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;none&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;The A-List: Classical&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;3.9%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;3.9%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Classical Kids&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;none&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;none&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full figures and composer details for Apple Music playlists can be found in the &lt;a href=&quot;/music/2021/03/01/deep-dive-apple-music.html&quot;&gt;Apple Music Deep Dive post&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spotify-summary&quot;&gt;Spotify&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spotify’s classical playlists were slightly better, but still lagged US orchestras in representation. Most of their playlists had — at best — about half the number of women composers or composers of colour compared to the average US orchestra mainstage season. The one exception was Spotify’s &lt;em&gt;Classical New Releases&lt;/em&gt; playlist, which had nearly comparable representation of women composers, and slightly greater representation of composers of colour. &lt;em&gt;Classical New Releases&lt;/em&gt; also holds the distinction of having the only track written by an Indigenous composer (Yorta Yorta woman Deborah Cheetham).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Spotify Playlist&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Women&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;BIPOC&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Classical Essentials&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;4.1%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;1.7%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Classical Sleep&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;4.2%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;2.8%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Classical New Releases&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;7.1%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;8.6%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Orchestra 100: Spotify Picks&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;2.0%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;2.0%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full figures and composer details for Spotify playlists to come in a future post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-what&quot;&gt;So What?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of these platforms have made repeated commitments to improve representation of women and people of colour on their platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After mass protests in response to racism and police brutality, in particular the police killings of George Floyd, Ahmaud Arbery, and Breonna Taylor, &lt;a href=&quot;https://newsroom.spotify.com/2020-06-01/spotify-stands-with-the-black-community-in-the-fight-against-racism-and-injustice/&quot;&gt;Spotify announced on Blackout Tuesday that it “Stands With the Black Community in the Fight Against Racism and Injustice”&lt;/a&gt;, and outlined a number of measures to amplify Black musicians and podcasts on its platform. Two weeks later, it pledged to donate USD $10 million to “organizations that are focused on the fight against racism, injustice, and inequity around the world”. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2020/6/1/21277501/spotify-blackout-tuesday-george-floyd-racism-police-brutality-violence-protest&quot;&gt;Apple Music made some similar symbolic changes to its platform&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2020/05/31/apple-ceo-tim-cook-email-to-employees-about-george-floyd.html&quot;&gt;Apple pledged to make unspecified donations to racial justice organizations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, many months later, pieces by Black composers remain scarce on classical playlists on both platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to commitments to support movements for racial justice, these platforms have also tried to position themselves as being on the vanguard of sharing the wealth of music offered by global multicuturalism. In 2018, &lt;a href=&quot;https://newsroom.spotify.com/2018-09-28/discover-hits-from-around-the-world-with-spotifys-global-cultures-initiative/&quot;&gt;Spotify launched their Global Cultures Initiative&lt;/a&gt;, “which promotes and advances culturally diverse music, surfacing hits from different countries around the world”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, just over a year later, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.musicbusinessworldwide.com/spotifys-head-of-african-music-tunde-ogundipe-leaves-service-alongside-indian-music-expert-himanshu-suri/&quot;&gt;Spotify disbanded the original Global Cultures curatorial team&lt;/a&gt;. Although they pledged to continue the initiative with “a larger, region-specific editorial team of experts”, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rollingstone.com/pro/features/spotify-global-cultures-initiative-892762/&quot;&gt;the change elicited negative reactions from many artists, as reported by Rolling Stone&lt;/a&gt;. Rolling Stone also noted that the disbanding coincided with an exodus of several high-profile curators who are people of colour, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2020/12/03/how-spotify-hopes-to-win-the-podcasting-wars.html&quot;&gt;a nearly-billion dollar shift towards podcasting&lt;/a&gt; — which has largely been to the benefit of creators and businesspeople who are white and established.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Underrepresentation of women has also been an issue on streaming platforms for many years. In 2019, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rollingstone.com/music/music-country/martina-mcbride-spotify-country-music-882401/&quot;&gt;country singer Martina McBride posted about her frustration with overwhelmingly male-dominated algorithmic recommendations&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nbcnews.com/think/opinion/country-music-radio-has-ignored-female-artists-years-we-have-ncna1137571&quot;&gt;a genre that is well known for being hostile to female artists&lt;/a&gt;. Musicologist &lt;a href=&quot;https://songdata.ca/2019/10/01/reflecting-on-spotifys-recommender-system/&quot;&gt;Dr. Jada E. Watson also found similar results when testing the algorithmic song recommendations&lt;/a&gt; for country music fans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even earlier, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thebaffler.com/latest/discover-weakly-pelly&quot;&gt;writer Liz Pelly used Spotify’s absurd “Smirnoff Equalizer” marketing campaign to show that the platform had a distinct male bias&lt;/a&gt; that was “subtly shifting us back toward a more homogenous and overtly masculine pop music culture”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I listened almost exclusively to a sampling of the most popular entries: Today’s Top Hits, New Music Friday, Rock This, Rap Caviar, Hot Country, ¡Viva Latino!, and more. Every week, for one month, I downloaded a spreadsheet of the playlist data and analyzed the gender disparity. In the interest of not misgendering artists on the basis of their appearance or sound, I focused on confirming how artists self-identify on their Spotify “about” pages or other verified bios.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The result of this experiment: I found Spotify’s most popular and visible playlists to be staggeringly male-dominated. Not only this, I approached the project by listening from a brand new account in order to confirm that gender bias would be reproduced by way of algorithmic recommendations—that when a user listens to mostly male-dominated playlists, what is produced are yet more male-dominated playlists. Indeed, the sexist music industry status quo is upheld widely by Spotify, even as the platform exploits the woke optics of playlists like Feminist Friday and advertising schemes like the Smirnoff Equalizer to further benefit its brand recognition and bottom line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all likelihood, human–algorithmic curation that reinforces bias against cis women is even more inhospitable for trans and non-binary musicians. Despite looking through hundreds of songs, Liz Pelly reported that she “encountered no artists on Spotify’s top playlists who did not identify as a man or woman”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the platforms could argue that classical music is such a small niche that it’s just been overlooked by their efforts to feature diverse artists. Or that the lack of representation in their playlists reflects a lack of representation in a historically-white genre. But neither of these reactions would hold up to much scrutiny. Wouldn’t a genuine commitment to diversity be reflected in all curatorial decisions; in official playlists of all sizes? If the genre is to blame, why do most of the playlists have at best half the number of women composers or composers of colour compared to an average US orchestra season?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Playlist diversity compared to orchestra mainstage programming is not a hard benchmark to exceed. Most orchestras are literally-eurocentric, small-c conservative institutions. And yet, the meager steps taken by US orchestras — at least a full year before the pandemic &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; — to program more composers from the likes of Florence Price, Gabriela Lena Frank, Jennifer Higdon, and Anna Clyne have put them much further ahead than the current efforts of these two tech companies &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to see progress in orchestra programming continue and pick up speed. If streaming platforms lived up to their diversity commitments, perhaps a new generation of audience members who discover classical composers online would act as a catalyst, demanding orchestra programs that better represent the communities that ensembles work in. As it is, these platforms are cementing the status quo; investing in unseen curators and algorithms who spend their time tending to a musical monoculture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-better-options&quot;&gt;Some Better Options&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For people looking to find ways to listen to a more diverse range of classical music composers, there are some options:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For US listeners, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.composerdiversity.com/media&quot;&gt;Institute for Composer Diversity has a partnership with Pandora&lt;/a&gt; to curate channels that feature a diverse mix of composers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Canadian listeners, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbc.ca/listen/live-radio/2-4278-tempo&quot;&gt;CBC’s &lt;em&gt;Tempo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; seems to be a good choice. There are also a number of Canadian composers who are women or people of colour featured on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://cmccanada.org/product-category/recordings/centrediscs/&quot;&gt;Canadian Music Centre’s Centredisks Label&lt;/a&gt;. (Centredisks albums are also on the major streaming services, e.g. you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/album/4YJETJz7W99jMXRlEHPWJb?si=pLfDSybqRbiSB6chYt0x4g&quot;&gt;listen to Alexina Louie’s &lt;em&gt;Take the Dog Sled&lt;/em&gt; on Spotify&lt;/a&gt;. While I’m at it, I should shill a little bit and note that you can also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yYvegcavM9k&quot;&gt;listen to her Triple Concerto&lt;/a&gt; on the TSO’s YouTube channel.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the major streaming services themselves, there are some playlists designed to specifically showcase women composers, e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/playlist/37i9dQZF1DX5hL1aT2vhMb&quot;&gt;Spotify’s &lt;em&gt;Women of Classical&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://music.apple.com/ca/playlist/women-in-classical-music/pl.03392dae73604942b02ab8e53c482ae0&quot;&gt;Apple Music’s &lt;em&gt;Women in Classical Music&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I couldn’t find official playlists on either service specifically for classical composers of colour, but you can certainly find third party playlists, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/playlist/67avQ7fZ1zvEk1RDI9C3sd?si=ydgJJhfnQ1OCiRCjv3A7Pg&quot;&gt;this playlist on Spotify made by NAXOS for Black History Month&lt;/a&gt;. I’ll also give an honourable mention to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uoftfomara.org/&quot;&gt;University of Toronto Faculty of Music Anti-Racism Alliance&lt;/a&gt; who made this &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/playlist/7KsIccKNvDyftVlxWWPEdQ?si=7d886f70c97b420b&quot;&gt;Centring BIPOC Musicians Playlist&lt;/a&gt; (It has a much broader selection of genres than orchestral/classical, but I think it’s very good).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, although the numbers of women composers and composers who are Indigenous, Black, or people of colour on streaming services are low, I researched over 650 tracks for this project &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, so the list of people who &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; represented is still fairly long and interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So those will be the next posts - doing a deep dive into the specific composers represented on the Apple Music and Spotify playlists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;playlist-methodology-and-data&quot;&gt;Playlist, Methodology, and Data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can listen to all of the pieces featured in this playlist analysis series here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/playlist/6vQwkvRqWbGEF5IKZmC6na?si=1829c2da26b84f03&quot;&gt;Spotify: Classical Deep Dive - Spotify &amp;amp; Apple Music&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full methodology notes for all my music posts can be found via the &lt;a href=&quot;/exploring-orchestral-music-methodology/&quot;&gt;Main Methodology Page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Details and data for the streaming service playlists analysis can be found on the &lt;a href=&quot;/exploring-orchestral-music-methodology/streaming-service-demographic-analysis.html&quot;&gt;Streaming Analysis Methodology Page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More details about how I used the data from the Institute for Composer Diversity to create the comparison to US orchestra mainstage seasons can be found on the &lt;a href=&quot;/exploring-orchestral-music-methodology/ICD-orchestra-season-analysis.html&quot;&gt;ICD 2019/20 Season Analysis Methodology Page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If you’ve read any feature piece about the past and future of the music industry, you’ve probably seen the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.riaa.com/u-s-sales-database/&quot;&gt;RIAA’s graph of how revenue sources have changed over time&lt;/a&gt;. As someone who went to high school in the late 2000s, my favourite thing about this graph is looking at the “Era of Paying for Ringtones” between about 2005 and 2010. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Orchestras are known for having long planning timelines. For the 2019/20 season, conductors and soloists might have been booked two or three years ahead of their performances.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;The latest a piece could have been confirmed would have been December 2018 (maybe January 2019 at a stretch), since marketing teams then need to prepare materials for a mid-winter subscription on-sale that usually launches at least half a year in advance of the first performance. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;The dates that tracks were added to a Spotify playlist are visible in the metadata, so we know when curatorial decisions were published:&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;All of the tracks in &lt;em&gt;Classical Essentials&lt;/em&gt; were added on October 2, 2020&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;The tracks in &lt;em&gt;Classical New Releases&lt;/em&gt; were added between December 18, 2020 and January 1, 2021&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;All of the tracks in &lt;em&gt;Classical Sleep&lt;/em&gt; were added on January 1, 2021&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Orchestra 100: Spotify Picks&lt;/em&gt; by contrast, hasn’t been actively curated since 2017; most of the tracks were added in May of 2016&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Apple Music’s metadata has “Date Modified” and “Date Added” fields, but both appear to be blank when exporting data from official playlists. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It’s actually 666 tracks exactly, which feels very ominous. Maybe I should throw out the one track on Apple Music’s &lt;em&gt;Classical Kids&lt;/em&gt; where Michael Morpurgo just reads a book on the basis of not being music so that I can say it’s 665… &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><category term="Music" /><summary type="html">Introduction: The Rise of Streaming</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>