<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-01-26T21:55:01-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">tallcoleman</title><subtitle>A Blog on Politics and Nature
</subtitle><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><entry><title type="html">Toronto Beltline Trail via BikeShare</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/cycling/2018/08/26/toronto-beltline-trail-via-bikeshare.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Toronto Beltline Trail via BikeShare" /><published>2018-08-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-08-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/cycling/2018/08/26/toronto-beltline-trail-via-bikeshare</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/cycling/2018/08/26/toronto-beltline-trail-via-bikeshare.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/Ronald-Ave-Station.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Image of Bikeshare Bike next to sign titled Ronald Avenue Station&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ronald Ave E - The Turning Around Point&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-stats&quot;&gt;Key Stats:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 1h 45m - 2h, depending on how often you take breaks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distance:&lt;/strong&gt; about 26km&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hills:&lt;/strong&gt; Moderate, unless you take Milkman’s Lane&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On August 15, Bike Share Toronto &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thestar.com/news/city_hall/2018/08/15/torontos-bike-share-system-expanding-again.html&quot;&gt;announced that they were expanding their network again&lt;/a&gt;, with 75 new stations across Toronto. One of the interesting new additions was a station on the Kay Gardiner Beltline Trail, which is a great trail for an afternoon bike ride. Naturally, I thought I would try it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-couple-important-caveats&quot;&gt;A couple important caveats:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Keep an eye on the time - especially for the first part of the journey. I use a timer set to 25 minutes to make sure I don’t go over 30 minutes for each part of the trip.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Don’t do this route with a BikeShare bike if it’s raining or has recently rained. They have pretty smooth tires and you don’t want to get the bike dirty. Remember–someone else will be using it later.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you grab a bike, make sure it has a working bell, well-functioning brakes, and one of the new seats. (They don’t have a suspension, so the new seat thing is important.)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-i---castle-frank-to-oriole-park&quot;&gt;Part I - Castle Frank to Oriole Park&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/Map-Part-I.png&quot; alt=&quot;Map of route from Castle Frank Station to Oriole Park&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the longest part of the trip, and also the most uphill. If you want to avoid the treacherous ride down Milkman’s Lane, there’s a ramp down from Crescent Road and Mount Pleasant Road that takes you north. You can go down there and enter the ravine at Mount Pleasant and Roxborough. This part takes 22 minutes, or 27 if you avoid Milkman’s Lane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Optional Diversion (especially on the way back) - if you want to stop at the Don Valley Brickworks, you can exit through Chorley Park and there’s a rack right at the top of the hill on Douglas Drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tips&quot;&gt;Tips:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once the trail stops being side-by-side with Bayview Ave, there’s a big fork. Take the larger trail on the left (the other one goes to the Brickworks parking lot)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you don’t want to go through the cemetery, or can’t because of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mountpleasantgroup.com/Locations/Cemeteries/Mount-Pleasant.aspx&quot;&gt;gate hours&lt;/a&gt;, you can go west on Moore Ave and North on Mount Pleasant Rd. Once you hit Merton St, you can go back south slightly and catch the trail again.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The rack in Oriole Park is slightly off the trail, but you should be able to see it when you cross the road.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/Davisville-Yard.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of the Davisville TTC Yard taken from the trail bridge&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Once you see the Davisville TTC Yard, you’re almost at Oriole Park.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-ii---oriole-park-to-memorial-park&quot;&gt;Part II - Oriole Park to Memorial Park&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/Map-Part-II.png&quot; alt=&quot;Map of route from Oriole Park to Memorial Park&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the shortest part of the trip. It’s slightly uphill, but pretty easy. It should take just under 10 minutes. The rack at Memorial Park is right on the trail, so it’s hard to miss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are park washrooms on the outside of the Arena, so if you need a bathroom break, this is a good spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/Memorial-Park-Dock.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Image of the Bike Rack at Memorial Park&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The rack by Memorial Park. Currently the northern-most rack in the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-iii---memorial-park-to-the-york-beltline-trail-and-back-again&quot;&gt;Part III - Memorial Park to the York Beltline Trail and Back Again&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/Map-Part-III.png&quot; alt=&quot;Map of route from Memorial Park westward&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no other BikeShare racks after this, so &lt;strong&gt;make sure you set a timer to tell you when to turn around!&lt;/strong&gt; I set mine for a safe 13 minutes, but you could do 14.5 minutes if you like to live life on the edge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a small section where this trail hops up to Elm Ridge Dr/Roselawn Ave to get over the Allen Expressway, but it’s short and has good signs to get you back to the trail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I managed to get to Ronald Ave E before turning around. I think if you really cut it close and went fast you could get to the end of the trail… but that’s an experiment for another day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/York-Beltline-View.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of the York Beltline Trail&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Enjoy the paved trail while it lasts! If you have time, check out all the historical signs–they’re great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-iv---memorial-park-to-oriole-park&quot;&gt;Part IV - Memorial Park to Oriole Park&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the same as part II, but going back. Enjoy going slightly downhill!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to take a different route, you can head leave the trail south at Russell Hill Rd and head downtown. There are racks all over north downtown within a 30 minute ride (Spadina Station is just under 20 minutes, for example.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/Kay-Gardiner-Beltline-View.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of the Kay Gardiner Beltline Trail Park&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The shade on this part of the trail is fantastic on a hot day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-v---oriole-park-to-castle-frank-station&quot;&gt;Part V - Oriole Park to Castle Frank Station&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avoid going up Milkman’s Lane unless you want to be completely exhausted, especially since the bikes only have one low gear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t make the same mistake that I did and go into the Cemetery before Mount Pleasant and then take the trail from the West side. That trail has stairs, and the BikeShare bikes are &lt;em&gt;heavy&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the whole Milkman’s Lane thing, this part is mostly downhill. Keep an eye on the time if you’re tired. If you’re running out of time getting out of the ravine, there’s a rack in Rosedale Park a couple minutes to the north.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy the ride!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/Ronald-Ave-Station.JPG" /></entry><entry><title type="html">TIFF Blog Post: 2167 Indigenous VR</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/tiff/2017/11/26/2167-Indigenous-VR.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TIFF Blog Post: 2167 Indigenous VR" /><published>2017-11-26T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-11-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/tiff/2017/11/26/2167-Indigenous-VR</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/tiff/2017/11/26/2167-Indigenous-VR.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been spending a lot of time recently writing internal-facing reports, so it’s nice to be able to write something to share with the world. TIFF has a publication of sorts called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tiff.net/action-report/&quot;&gt;ACTION report&lt;/a&gt;, which is an excellent showcase of how our funding makes a difference in the moving image arts&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- footnote --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tiff.net/action-report/fall2017/indigenous-virtual-futures/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/TIFF-Action-Report-Fall-2017.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The ACTION report page&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was lucky enough to be able to write about &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tiff.net/events/2167/&quot;&gt;2167&lt;/a&gt;, an indigneous VR exhibit that’s been housed at TIFF for about the past half-year (and travelled around–it’s been to Yellowknife!). There are “VR Experiences” on show, and I spoke to the creator/director of one titled &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tiff.net/exhibitions/the-hunt/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Hunt&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Her name is Danis Goulet, and she is a Cree/Métis filmmaker, TIFF Short Cuts programmer, and an absolute pleasure to interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To see all of the interesting things that she said about VR, Sci-Fi, and Indigenous filmmaking, go and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tiff.net/action-report/fall2017/indigenous-virtual-futures/&quot;&gt;read the interview&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;The Review&lt;/em&gt;, another great TIFF publication also did an excellent interview with Danis and some of the other VR filmmakers that you can &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tiff.net/the-review/indigenous-existence-is-resistance/&quot;&gt;read here&lt;/a&gt;. It talks a lot more about the actual filmmaking and the art behind VR, so it’s a fantastic read if you’re into those elements of the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for this blog, there’s one tidbit I didn’t have space for in the piece that I wanted to share:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In her interview, Danis talks about getting started as a casting director and how her experiences during casting motivated her to make her own films. While I was doing my pre-interview research, I found out that one of the gigs she had was doing the Canadian casting for &lt;em&gt;Mean Girls&lt;/em&gt;, which meant casting all the extras and many of the smaller roles. Apparently the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9KY8WU0oa3I&quot;&gt;Kevin Gnapoor rap&lt;/a&gt; is burned into her brain now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That being said, after I asked her all my &lt;em&gt;Mean Girls&lt;/em&gt; questions, I did do the real interview with her, which you can read on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tiff.net/action-report/fall2017/indigenous-virtual-futures/&quot;&gt;TIFF Website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It’s annoying how tech can make things more difficult. 10 or 20 years ago, “film” might be an OK descriptor of TIFF’s wheelhouse. However, these days an artist might make an augmented reality experience (think Pokemon GO, but artsy), and that would be something TIFF would care about. Would you call that a “film”? Probably not. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><summary type="html">I’ve been spending a lot of time recently writing internal-facing reports, so it’s nice to be able to write something to share with the world. TIFF has a publication of sorts called ACTION report, which is an excellent showcase of how our funding makes a difference in the moving image arts1. It’s annoying how tech can make things more difficult. 10 or 20 years ago, “film” might be an OK descriptor of TIFF’s wheelhouse. However, these days an artist might make an augmented reality experience (think Pokemon GO, but artsy), and that would be something TIFF would care about. Would you call that a “film”? Probably not. &amp;#8617;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mac Setup</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/technology/2017/08/07/mac-setup.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mac Setup" /><published>2017-08-07T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/technology/2017/08/07/mac-setup</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/technology/2017/08/07/mac-setup.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Updated: April 28, 2018&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought a new computer (Mac) recently and wanted to make a list of all the tools I find useful in case other people find them useful too. I used to use a Windows computer, so a lot of these are things I used on Windows too, or equivalents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here it is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;new-airdrop-location-selection&quot;&gt;New: AirDrop Location Selection&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find that AirDrop is often the fastest way to transfer individual files over to my computer. However, if you want to choose where the files end up, you’ll have to use an Automator Script. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.idownloadblog.com/2017/03/03/change-airdrop-destination-folder-mac/&quot;&gt;This site&lt;/a&gt; has a good description of how to set that up (ignore the phony notification request). I would suggest one twist: for the “Move Finder Items” action, click “Options” and check “Show this action when the workflow runs”. That way, you can select a specific folder every time you receive an AirDrop file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;window-management&quot;&gt;Window Management&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is something Windows does better natively than Mac (in my opinion). However, as long as you’re comfortable with using your keyboard, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spectacleapp.com/&quot;&gt;Spectacle&lt;/a&gt; does a good job of bringing OSX up to par.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One small note: if you use the keyboard shortcut for footnotes in Word (⌘ + ⌥ + F), you might want to remap the “fullscreen” shortcut in Spectacle’s preferences so they don’t conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;spotify-notifications&quot;&gt;Spotify Notifications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why isn’t this a thing that the Spotify app already does!? Anyway, in the meantime, you can see the title of each new song with &lt;a href=&quot;https://spotify-notifications.citruspi.io/&quot;&gt;this app&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;flux&quot;&gt;Flux&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Screw night shift. &lt;a href=&quot;https://justgetflux.com/&quot;&gt;Flux&lt;/a&gt; is &lt;a href=&quot;https://9to5mac.com/2017/03/28/flux-developer-says-apples-new-competitive-macos-night-shift-feature-falls-short/&quot;&gt;better&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;battery-lifetime&quot;&gt;Battery Lifetime&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the newer versions of OSX &lt;a href=&quot;https://9to5mac.com/2016/12/13/why-apple-is-removing-time-remaining-battery-life-estimates-macbook-pro/&quot;&gt;don’t have the battery time remaining indicator&lt;/a&gt;, I think this &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/app/battery-diag/id836505650?mt=12&quot;&gt;Battery Monitor App (App Store Link)&lt;/a&gt; is pretty useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;trackball-scrolling&quot;&gt;Trackball scrolling&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a Logitech M570 Trackball Mouse and I like to use the trackball to scroll. It’s amazing and I don’t know why the Logitech software doesn’t allow you to do this already since it’s 1000% better than using the scroll wheel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got the trackball scrolling working using a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hammerspoon.org/&quot;&gt;hammerspoon&lt;/a&gt; script from this thread:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/tekezo/Karabiner/issues/814&quot;&gt;https://github.com/tekezo/Karabiner/issues/814&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has options for keybinding to start the scroll mode, or you can press a button on the mouse, which is what I do. I only changed two parts of the mouse button script:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Line 4:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;local &lt;/span&gt;scrollmult &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The negative number makes it non-natural scrolling. I prefer the natural scrolling, but this helps me switch back to Windows, which I have to use at work. I also tamped down the speed a bit, from 4 to 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Line 13:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;local &lt;/span&gt;shouldScroll &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; 2 &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; pressedMouseButton
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changed the button to OSX button 3 (middle button). I also remapped the fifth button (“forward”) in Logitech Options to be the middle button, which is how I had it set up in Windows. I find it easier to click than the mouse wheel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than that, I kept the rest of the script the same. Works better than the Windows AHK script I was using.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;typewriter-scrolling-in-ms-word&quot;&gt;Typewriter Scrolling in MS Word&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Windows, I had an AHK script that kept the active line in Microsoft Word in the middle of the screen, instead of wandering to the bottom (a.k.a. “typewriter scrolling”). Since I occasionally do transcription, this is really useful, since it improves the ergonomics of typing for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t find a script that did the same thing using Hammerspoon, so I wrote one using AppleScript. It’s not elegant… but it works!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Link: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/tallcoleman/MacWordTypewriterScroll&quot;&gt;View on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><summary type="html">Updated: April 28, 2018</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rouge Park Bioblitz 2017</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ecology/2017/06/28/Rouge-Park-Bioblitz-2017.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rouge Park Bioblitz 2017" /><published>2017-06-28T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-06-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ecology/2017/06/28/Rouge-Park-Bioblitz-2017</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ecology/2017/06/28/Rouge-Park-Bioblitz-2017.html">&lt;p&gt;Last weekend I helped out at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://bioblitzcanada.ca/events_flagships-toronto.aspx&quot;&gt;Rouge Park Canada Bioblitz&lt;/a&gt;. It was a boatload of fun, all the groups found a lot of species despite the weather, and I saw lots of &lt;em&gt;cool birds&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/Bioblitz-2017-Morning-Sky.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of Morning Sky&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My volunteer shift started at 5:30 a.m. so I was up early. Most of the people that shared the bus ride with me to Scarborough were clearly coming back from clubbing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/Bioblitz-2017-River-Landscape-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of River Landscape from Vista Trail&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I think this was taken from the Orchard Trail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/Bioblitz-2017-Cedar-Waxwing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of Cedar Waxwing&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Blurry photo of a Cedar Waxwing taken through binoculars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/Bioblitz-2017-Blurry-Turtle.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of Snapping Turtle&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Blurry photo of a snapping turtle sunning itself on a rock, also taken through binoculars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/Bioblitz-2017-River-Landscape.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of River Landscape&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Photo of River Landscape taken from the East end of Zoo Road. About an hour later it poured down and our gazebo tent almost flew away!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not pictured: Baltimore Oriole, and Indigo Bunting, both of which were too quick for my binocular-iPhone camera “set-up”.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><category term="Rouge Park" /><category term="Canada Bioblitz" /><summary type="html">Last weekend I helped out at the Rouge Park Canada Bioblitz. It was a boatload of fun, all the groups found a lot of species despite the weather, and I saw lots of cool birds.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bloor-Yorkville BIA Blog Posts - 2017</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/bloor-yorkville%20bia/2017/05/20/Bloor-Yorkville-BIA-Blog-Posts-2017.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bloor-Yorkville BIA Blog Posts - 2017" /><published>2017-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/bloor-yorkville%20bia/2017/05/20/Bloor-Yorkville-BIA-Blog-Posts-2017</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/bloor-yorkville%20bia/2017/05/20/Bloor-Yorkville-BIA-Blog-Posts-2017.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a list of Blog posts I wrote for the Bloor-Yorkville Business Improvement Area in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-best-fountain-pens-toronto-has-to-offer-are-at-laywines&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bloor-yorkville.com/best-fountain-pens-toronto-laywines/&quot;&gt;The Best Fountain Pens Toronto Has to Offer are at Laywine’s&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/Ajoto-Pens-on-Display-Board-1024x428.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of Ajoto Pens on a Wooden Display Board&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love the Instagram photo of the elephant pencil holder in this article. I love cute things and I love the rock in the Village of Yorkville Park, and it has both!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also wish I had taken a picture of the back room of the store, because it looks like Ollivander’s wand shop, except all the long boxes have pens in them. Such a cool place to visit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toronto-bees-find-a-new-home-at-the-colonnade&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bloor-yorkville.com/toronto-bees-find-new-home-colonnade/&quot;&gt;Toronto Bees Find a New Home at the Colonnade&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/2017-06-09-bee-hat-photo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of Ben Coleman wearing a beekeeper mesh hat&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was such a fun post to write! Kelly and I got to go up to the roof, chill with the bees, and wear cool hats (see above). What more can you ask for?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you find the business behind bees interesting, I would also highly recommend this &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.econtalk.org/archives/2013/12/wally_thurman_o.html&quot;&gt;episode of the EconTalk podcast&lt;/a&gt;, which is also a good look at how the Varroa mite has impacted the commercial practices of beekeepers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;paul-pecorella-hair-salon--spa-celebrates-their-35-year-anniversary-in-bloor-yorkville&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bloor-yorkville.com/paul-pecorella-hair-salon-spa-35-year-anniversary/&quot;&gt;Paul Pecorella Hair Salon &amp;amp; Spa Celebrates Their 35-Year Anniversary in Bloor-Yorkville&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/Photo-of-Paul-2017-1-1024x576.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of Paul&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love meeting people who worked in Yorkville when it was a hippie hangout. I got to do this last year with &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;the Scollard Deli&lt;/a&gt;, and this year it was a real treat to meet everyone in the Pecorella family. They’ve been in Yorkville for 35 years, and they have lots of stories to tell about it. My half-hour interview with them felt like I had joined in a family hangout to reminisce. It was a lovely time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-betty-hemmings-yorkville-guide-to-luxury-leather-goods&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bloor-yorkville.com/betty-hemmings-guide-luxury-leather-goods/&quot;&gt;The Betty Hemmings Yorkville Guide to Luxury Leather Goods&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/Collage-of-Magnifying-Glass-Close-ups-1024x768.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image of two close-ups&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is among the longest articles I’ve written. Even still, there were more sections I could have included: a whole intro to what to look for in wallets, more details about some of the luggage, and so on. It was also my first attempt at including some video, with a short, motion-stabilized spur-of-the-moment cellphone capture of a fantastic moment in salesmanship. I think the guy who sold my parents their vacuum cleaner stood on it first too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal was to try and take a more practical angle for this piece. Part of my thinking was making the article fun and easy to write, and part of it was becuase the usual profile-type piece that we often do in the Bloor-Yorkville Blog would be redundant given the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thehogtownrake.com/?p=2587&quot;&gt;well-written profile done last year by fashion blogger Pedro Mendes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;unique-in-yorkville-the-sassoon-salon&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bloor-yorkville.com/unique-in-yorkville-sassoon-academy/&quot;&gt;Unique in Yorkville: The Sassoon Salon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To write this story, I interviewed one of the academy’s instructors, Wesley Hanlon. I love interviewing people—my goal is to try to find the question that breaks people out from the mould of what they planned to say and organically reveals their own passion and personality. I had a lot of fun talking with Wesley and learning about the Academy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;its-bird-migration-season-what-you-can-do-to-care-for-and-prevent-injured-birds&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bloor-yorkville.com/bird-migration-prevent-injured-birds/&quot;&gt;It’s Bird Migration Season! What You Can Do To Care For and Prevent Injured Birds&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/FLAP Annual Photo 2016.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;FLAP Canada’s 2016 Bird Layout&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love birds, as you can probably tell by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/ecology/saskatchewan-birds/&quot;&gt;other pages on this website dedicated to writing about them&lt;/a&gt;. This article is mostly a compilation of fantastic tips from FLAP Canada and some information I pulled together about development proposals in the Bloor-Yorkville area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also read the post here: &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/bloor-yorkville%20bia/2017/05/04/its-bird-migration-season-prevent-injured-birds.html&quot;&gt;http://localhost:4000/bloor-yorkville%20bia/2017/05/04/its-bird-migration-season-prevent-injured-birds.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><category term="Portfolio" /><category term="Bloor-Yorkville 2017" /><summary type="html">This is a list of Blog posts I wrote for the Bloor-Yorkville Business Improvement Area in 2017.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">It’s Bird Migration Season! What You Can Do To Care For and Prevent Injured Birds</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/bloor-yorkville%20bia/2017/05/04/its-bird-migration-season-prevent-injured-birds.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="It’s Bird Migration Season! What You Can Do To Care For and Prevent Injured Birds" /><published>2017-05-04T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-05-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/bloor-yorkville%20bia/2017/05/04/its-bird-migration-season-prevent-injured-birds</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/bloor-yorkville%20bia/2017/05/04/its-bird-migration-season-prevent-injured-birds.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This article originally appeared on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://bloor-yorkville.com/blog/&quot;&gt;Bloor-Yorkville BIA Blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/FLAP Annual Photo 2016.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;FLAP Canada’s 2016 Bird Layout&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;FLAP Canada’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flap.org/museum-program.php&quot;&gt;2016 Bird Layout&lt;/a&gt;. Image courtesy of FLAP Canada&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;birds-in-the-city-a-rough-and-tumble-life&quot;&gt;Birds in the City: A Rough-and-Tumble Life&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toronto is a migratory bird hotspot: we are visited by birds flying
north in the spring (and south again in the fall) from both the Atlantic
and Mississippi flyways. Like many human Torontonians, migrating birds
love our high-quality lakefront properties, including the lush Toronto
Island and bustling Tommy Thompson Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, migratory birds get confused, injured, and killed by two things
found in abundance in downtown Toronto—artificial light and glass.
Problems with birds and glass are well-known: unlike us, birds don’t
understand that what they see in a window is a reflection. As a result,
thousands fly into city windows thinking that a reflected surface is a
restful tree or open sky. At high speed, the collision is usually fatal.
The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www1.toronto.ca/wps/portal/contentonly?vgnextoid=c5f20621f3161410VgnVCM10000071d60f89RCRD&amp;amp;vgnextchannel=f6ce5d0a02148410VgnVCM10000071d60f89RCRD&quot;&gt;City of Toronto’s best practices guide for bird-friendly
glass&lt;/a&gt;
cites a study that estimated that in Canada, about 25 million birds die
each year from colliding with windows. It is a huge and pressing
problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Less well-known are the problems caused by artificial light. Many
migratory birds fly at night when it is cooler and safer from predators,
using the moon and stars for navigation. Light coming from our cities
confuses and attracts these birds, drawing them into the city where they
are at risk of being harmed by busy roads or reflective surfaces. This
phenomena is called “Fatal Light Attraction.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One group trying to solve these problems is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flap.org/index.php&quot;&gt;Fatal Light Awareness
Program (FLAP) Canada&lt;/a&gt;. This
Toronto-based group and its volunteers run an emergency bird rescue
program out of Metro Hall at 55 John Street. They also educate
Torontonians about the dangers faced by migratory birds and advocate for
policies and architecture that helps to protect them. While rescuing
birds, they also collect data about when and where different species of
birds are killed to emphasize the importance of taking action. There are
20 types of birds listed under the &lt;em&gt;Species at Risk Act&lt;/em&gt; on their record
of species that have been found dead after colliding with glass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;city-planning-to-reduce-bird-deaths&quot;&gt;City Planning to Reduce Bird Deaths&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www1.toronto.ca/wps/portal/contentonly?vgnextoid=f85552cc66061410VgnVCM10000071d60f89RCRD&quot;&gt;Toronto Green
Standard&lt;/a&gt;
is a checklist for developers that helps to create more sustainable
buildings. It has two tiers, and a variety of measures that can be
implemented, ranging from improvements to energy efficiency to
protections for migrating birds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first tier is mandatory for new developments. Among many other
requirements, it specifies that new buildings must treat at least 85% of
all exterior glass within the first 12 meters of a building in a way
that prevents confusing reflections. This can be done using materials
that are low-reflecting and opaque, or visual markers such as
“fritting”—the application of ceramic dots to the glass during
manufacturing. You can see these methods being used in planned
developments in Bloor-Yorkville:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/75 Yorkville Plan-COLLAGE-annotated.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Development proposals in Bloor-Yorkville with bird-friendly
glass&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Development proposals in Bloor-Yorkville with bird-friendly
glass marked in green: Top – 75 Yorkville Ave, Bottom – 848 Yonge
Street.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second tier of the Toronto Green Standard is optional, but the City
offers financial incentives for developers who meet this higher level of
sustainability. Bird protection measures in this tier include a
requirement to point architectural illumination downwards and turn it
off completely between 11 p.m. and 6 a.m. during the migratory season so
that the light does not confuse migrating birds. There is also an option
to increase the coverage of bird-friendly glass to 95% of the building’s
first 12 meters. So far, tier two buildings are rare (the City’s website
lists about 10), but hopefully one will be planned for Bloor-Yorkville
soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-you-can-help&quot;&gt;How You Can Help:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Turn off unnecessary lights at home and at work – especially when
you are leaving work at the end of the day. (A timer plug extension
might help).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the outside of your building, place visual markers on
window-glass (5 cm apart) or hang ribbons or strings in front of
windows (10 cm apart). (See &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flap.org/commercial_new.php&quot;&gt;FLAP’s tips on
window-markers&lt;/a&gt;—the small
details do matter.) It’s OK to be a little creative with window
markers: the Pan-Am aquatic center has small graphics of athletes
instead of dots and it complements their overall branding.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Speak with your property manager about using lights that turn off
automatically and installing special film outside of windows to
reduce reflection.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Place bird feeders close to your windows (less than half a metre
away) so birds leaving the feeder cannot hit your window at high
speed if they go in the wrong direction.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flap.org/volunteer.php&quot;&gt;Volunteer with FLAP Canada&lt;/a&gt; to
help with bird rescue and research.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Take action tips from City of Toronto Communications.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;strategies-that-dont-work&quot;&gt;Strategies That &lt;em&gt;Don’t&lt;/em&gt; Work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Predator Bird Decals: Many people think that large stickers of
birds-of-prey will scare off smaller birds from windows, but
experiments have shown that it doesn’t work! Smaller markers that
are close together, such as dot stickers 5 cm apart, work much
better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/IMG_1648-COLLAGE.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Picture of Two types of decals: small dot markers about 5cm
apart and bird-of-prey decals, which are ineffective&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Two types of decals: Left – small dot markers about 5cm
apart. Right – bird-of-prey decals, which are ineffective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Angled Glass: The updated City of Toronto Bird-Friendly Guidelines
has removed angled glass as a strategy due to a lack of supporting
scientific evidence. Birds fly in all directions, so it makes sense
that this would not reduce the impact of collisions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Interior Blinds: Markers never disappear, and they sit on the
outside of a window. Blinds are designed to be taken up and down,
and sit behind the glass. To be effective, window applications or
coverings need to be on the outside so they block or obscure any
confusing reflections.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tinted Glass: Like angled glass, there isn’t enough evidence to say
that tinted glass helps reduce collisions. There are anti-reflective
applications listed in the Toronto Green Standard that will work.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Interior Screens: Like blinds, these sit behind the glass. There is
a lack of evidence that putting interior screens behind windows will
help prevent birds from colliding with the glass.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Strategies to avoid taken from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www1.toronto.ca/wps/portal/contentonly?vgnextoid=c5f20621f3161410VgnVCM10000071d60f89RCRD&amp;amp;vgnextchannel=f6ce5d0a02148410VgnVCM10000071d60f89RCRD&quot;&gt;Bird-Friendly Development Guideline:
Best Practices – Glass
(2016)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-to-do-if-you-find-a-dead-or-injured-bird&quot;&gt;What to Do If You Find a Dead or Injured Bird:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you see a bird knocked out from colliding with a window or if you
find an injured bird on the ground, this is what you should do:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Try to handle the bird as little as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gently place the bird in an un-waxed paper bag or cardboard box.
Keep the container closed (you can poke some air holes in the top).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do not&lt;/strong&gt; give the bird water or food.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Roll clean tissues or paper towel into a donut shape and put it in
the container as a perch for the bird to sit upright.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Temporarily keep the bag or box in a safe, quiet location.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you hear the bird fluttering inside the container within an hour,
take it to a park, ravine, or any other area away from hazards, such
as windows, buildings, or busy roads, and slowly open the container
to let the bird fly out.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Contact the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.torontowildlifecentre.com/&quot;&gt;Toronto Wildlife
Centre&lt;/a&gt; for more
instructions if the bird has not shown any activity after one hour.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Recuperation tips from FLAP Canada. See &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flap.org/faqs.php&quot;&gt;their website for more
Frequently Asked Questions&lt;/a&gt; about helping
birds.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><category term="Bloor-Yorkville 2017" /><category term="Urban Ecology" /><category term="Fatal Light Attraction" /><category term="Injured Birds" /><summary type="html">This article originally appeared on the Bloor-Yorkville BIA Blog</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Liberating My Media Files From Wordpress</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/website%20setup/2017/03/27/liberating-my-media-files-from-wordpress-dot-com.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Liberating My Media Files From Wordpress" /><published>2017-03-27T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-03-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/website%20setup/2017/03/27/liberating-my-media-files-from-wordpress-dot-com</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/website%20setup/2017/03/27/liberating-my-media-files-from-wordpress-dot-com.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll has lots of good importers for migrating posts from WordPress sites, but the task of bringing over your assets (files, images, etc.) is something you have to do yourself. If you plan on keeping your WordPress site running, your migrated posts will still be able to serve their assets correctly, but it’s much better to have assets fully integrated into your site, instead of being served from an external URL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post has instructions for one simple-ish way of getting all the files that are used in your WordPress posts. It works for Linux and should be pretty easy in OSX (you might have to install tools like wget if you don’t have that already.) Sorry Windows users–I know Jekyll is already hard for you&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Once you have downloaded all the files, you can choose how you want to integrate them into your Jekyll site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setup&quot;&gt;Setup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, you need to migrate your posts from WordPress. There are multiple ways to do this listed on the Jekyll website for both &lt;a href=&quot;http://import.jekyllrb.com/docs/wordpress/&quot;&gt;self-hosted WordPress&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://import.jekyllrb.com/docs/wordpressdotcom/&quot;&gt;WordPress.com blogs&lt;/a&gt;. I used &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/thomasf/exitwp&quot;&gt;exitwp&lt;/a&gt; since I had a WordPress.com blog and wanted to keep all my metadata.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;extracting-the-assets-used-in-your-posts&quot;&gt;Extracting the Assets Used in Your Posts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start by navigating to the directory that contains all your migrated WordPress posts. You’ll need to figure out the general structure of asset links in the posts. For me, the asset links looked like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;- [U of T Publications with Intl Coauthors](http://tallcoleman.files.wordpress.com/2014/05/u-of-t-publications-with-intl-coauthors2.png?w=625)

- [Letter from Brad Duguid](http://tallcoleman.files.wordpress.com/2014/02/signedcopy-262605.pdf)

- [Transcription of John Tory Interview](http://tallcoleman.files.wordpress.com/2013/10/transcription-of-john-tory-interview-03.docx)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;grep-asset-urls&quot;&gt;Grep Asset URLs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To pull out all the asset links, I used grep, with the output streamed to a text file. In this case it looks for links that start with the asset base url and end with either &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;)&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;?&lt;/code&gt;. Another way to do it would be to use a list of file extensions to find the end of each link.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;grep&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-rio&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;http://tallcoleman.files.wordpress.com[^&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\)\?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;]*[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\)\?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;]&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; WpFileLinks1.txt
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were two image links ending in ‘”&amp;lt;’ that I missed but no big deal. In my case, there were no https links so if you have those, try “http[s]:// …” instead to catch both http:// and https:// asset links.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;processing-the-grep-output&quot;&gt;Processing the Grep Output&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t remember why I ran this command. Something to do with line breaks, I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sed &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'s/.$//'&lt;/span&gt; WpFileLinks1.txt &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; WpFileLinks2.txt
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote in my notes “There is a recursiveness problem which I don’t quite know how to fix.” I can’t remember what that meant, but I’ll try this all again at some point to finish writing up proper instructions. In any case, it shouldn’t prevent you from continuing on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This command removes the file references from the grep output. I’m sure there must be a better way of doing this, but this (mostly) worked for me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sed &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'s|.*:h\(.*\)|\1|'&lt;/span&gt; WpFileLinks2.txt &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; WpFileLinks3.txt
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to go add the h’s back in using find-and-replace to substitute ‘ttp://’ with ‘http://’. (I told you it’s not a very good method). I should go learn the proper syntax for &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sed&lt;/code&gt; later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;downloading-your-files&quot;&gt;Downloading Your Files&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now the &lt;strong&gt;magic&lt;/strong&gt; happens:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;wget &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-i&lt;/span&gt; ~/Documents/tallcoleman.github.io/WpFileLinks3.txt
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-i&lt;/code&gt; flag tells wget to get the list of URLs from our file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nice folder of files!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/Screenshot from 2017-03-27 21-40-45.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of downloaded Wordpress Files&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll have to decide later if I want to fully integrate them with my separated assets folder, or just keep them in the same folder to make swapping out the links easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-step-swap-out-the-asset-links-in-your-imported-wordpress-posts&quot;&gt;Final Step: Swap Out the Asset Links in Your Imported WordPress Posts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What worked for me so far was doing find and replace using regex in Atom:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;http://tallcoleman.files.wordpress.com/[0-9]&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;4&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;/[0-9]&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;2&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;/
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Replace:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;http://localhost:4000/assets/WpAssets/
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are still some php suffixes remaining but Jekyll just ignores them, so I’ve only removed them if I catch them in the wild, though finding them with regex shouldn’t be too hard if you want to make sure you’ve removed them all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have suggestions for ways I can do this less badly, hit me up at ben[dot]coleman[at]mail[dot]utoronto[dot]ca or on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/tallcoleman&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I actually run Windows, but honestly it’s easier to run Ubuntu in a VM than to get Ruby to play nice with Windows. Works well enough for me, and since I deployed the site in github pages, I can still write posts in the browser on github or push them from Windows without running &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt; locally. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><summary type="html">Introduction</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Letter to Business Board RE: International Tuition Fees</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/letters/2017/02/25/Letter-to-Business-Board.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Letter to Business Board RE: International Tuition Fees" /><published>2017-02-25T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-02-25T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/letters/2017/02/25/Letter-to-Business-Board</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/letters/2017/02/25/Letter-to-Business-Board.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Files/2017.02.20 Letter to Business Board_Public.pdf&quot;&gt;Download this letter in PDF format&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ben Coleman&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Undergraduate Student,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business Board Member&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;February 25th, 2017&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RE:&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;strong&gt;Undergraduate International Student Tuition Fees – Where Are We Going?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dear Fellow Business Board Members,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all know that undergraduate international tuition is at a historic high, and increasing. This month, item 1(a) on our agenda is asking us to increase undergraduate international tuition fees by an average of 5.9%. Tuition for students coming to UofT from abroad next year will start at $45,690. The year after that, it will start at $49,800&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The larger trend is that since 2010, entering international tuition has almost doubled. So I ask you to consider: if we continue on this trajectory, where are we going, and what are the consequences?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before beginning, I would like to note some historical context. International tuition fees were deregulated in the mid-90s. Between that point and 2004, the UofT policy was to set fees for international students at a rate equivalent to 100% of the cost of their education: domestic tuition, plus the amount of the provincial per-student operating grant.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The university received operating grants only for domestic students, so the extra amount charged to international students was intended to compensate for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/Entering Year Tuition Fees - Arts and Science Bachelor Adjusted to 2016 Dollars.png&quot; alt=&quot;Entering Year Tuition Fees - Arts and Science Bachelor Adjusted to 2016 Dollars&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Entering-year Undergraduate International Tuition Fees – Arts and Science Bachelor&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source: University of Toronto Fee Schedules (2001–2018). 2019–2021 projected based on current rates of increase.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;All numbers adjusted for inflation (CPI-Canada) and presented in 2016 CAD Dollars.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2004, when international tuition was $11,276 for incoming students, the administration successfully argued that larger increases should be approved by this board (and Governing Council) for 2005 and into the future. This was done in light of two factors: the tuition freeze that was to be in effect from 2004 to 2006 for domestic students, and persistent underfunding of the provincial operating grant, which had caused the university to be “under-funded by some 36%”.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Since that point in 2004, international student tuition has skyrocketed: first with increases of 5% per year for all international students, then with 10% increases per year for first-year international students and 5% increases for upper-years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-does-business-board-usually-evaluate-tuition-fee-increases&quot;&gt;How Does Business Board Usually Evaluate Tuition Fee Increases?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's easy to view the decision on how much to increase international tuition fees as the result of a simple business equation—the &quot;steady-state&quot; budget on page 29 of the budget report makes this argument in a simple and striking way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the steady-state budget:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/Structural Budget Challenge at the University of Toronto.png&quot; alt=&quot;Structural Budget Challenge at the University of Toronto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Structural Budget Challenge at the University of Toronto (“Steady-State Budget”)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source: Budget Report 2017-18 and Long Range Budget Guidelines 2017-18 to 2021-22, page 29. (Agenda Item 2)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we want to slow down the escalation of international tuition fees, we have to be able to increase or decrease one of these other main categories to compensate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the expense side, compensation is the largest portion and increases the most. There are lots of things to debate about how compensation should be managed, but with a net-zero stance from the University in bargaining and the previous regime of executive compensation freezes, there are few medium-term fixes that our administration would find palatable. As for &quot;other expenses&quot;—operational costs have already been aggressively reduced with the efforts of Prof. Mabury's department, and I would find it hard to argue for reducing spending on IT and library costs, since they directly support the academic mission. Finally, as a student, I can not argue for a reduction in the essential category of student aid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about revenue? Operating grants are essentially frozen, and the province is still running deficit budgets, frustrating any lobbying effort to increase them. This is unlikely to change without a significant change in provincial leadership. Domestic tuition has also been rising above inflation for a long period of time, and it should not rise faster still. Like &quot;other expenses&quot;, &quot;other revenue&quot; includes many opportunities that already being aggressively pursued by our administration. And to top it all off, the first 0.6% of any improvements in all these factors is slated to go towards bringing the steady state to balance, so that when enrollment levels off in the next decade, the University does not start running deficits. &lt;em&gt;Maybe&lt;/em&gt; after that, this administration would consider easing off the tuition gas pedal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope that five years down the road, the administration will have brought the steady state budget to balance. By then, many of the hidden impacts of exorbitant international tuition fees will already have taken deep root. And if the current regime continues, international fees will have increased to about $64,500 by 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are serious consequences of allowing this to happen, consequences that should stop us from allowing these fees to escalate so far. But unless we want to begin running deficits, something has to give in order to conform to the steady-state budget. There are some viable options to consider, but first we should examine the effects and dangers of high international fees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-hidden-impact-of-international-tuition-fee-decisions&quot;&gt;The Hidden Impact of International Tuition Fee Decisions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decision that Business Board has made repeatedly over the past decade—the decision to increase international fees at a rate far above the rate of inflation—is not just a business decision. It has hidden effects on the academics, mission, and culture of this institution, and Business Board should make its decision on international fees with a full weighing of these consequences. In some cases, the effects are clear. In other cases, we don't know enough to understand or fully grasp these consequences; a problem in itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;academics&quot;&gt;Academics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Broadly speaking, one academic trend of the past decade has been a decline in enrolment in programs such as the Humanities and Education, while programs such as Business, Computer Sciences, Architecture, and Engineering have grown. Both domestic and international students are choosing these fields due to broader market forces, but international students choose these fields with a much stronger preference than domestic students (see below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Undergraduate international enrolment has almost tripled in the past decade.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Even without tuition increases, this would have a strong effect on academic departments, since even in 1992 international students generally preferred some fields at higher rates than domestic students. The tuition increases compound this in multiple ways. Due to our budget model, the revenue from international students’ exorbitant tuition flows mostly to the fields they enrol in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/Distribution of international and Canadian students 1992 and 2008.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Distribution of international and Canadian students 1992 and 2008&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distribution of international and Canadian students, by field of study, Canada, 1992 and 2008&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source: Statistics Canada, Postsecondary Student Information System (PSIS).&lt;/em&gt; [^_5_]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, the shifts in preference from 1992 to 2008 suggest that higher tuition fees probably exacerbate the difference between academic programs chosen by international students compared to those chosen by domestic students. We don’t have a very detailed picture of why this is, but it’s easy to imagine that students and their parents have a very strong incentive to pick well-earning technical fields when fees are over $45,000 per year. The sum of these effects is that the decisions made by Business Board and Governing Council to increase international fees above inflation has shifted our academic landscape. If you look at the governance path for item 1(a), you can see that the tuition decision is made without a vote from Academic Board or its subsidiaries, even though it clearly affects academic planning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, notice that the graph above represents data from Canada as a whole, and from 2008. How much stronger are the preferences for different fields of study in 2017, at the University of Toronto, where international undergraduate fees are the highest in Canada?&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; We don’t know. The kind of data needed to understand this issue aren’t easily available, and is not included in the information accompanying the motion for a fee increase. The best I can offer is anecdotal evidence: I attended a town hall for the statistics department last November, which is where I learned that the department’s undergraduate enrolment has &lt;em&gt;quadrupled&lt;/em&gt; in size over the last several years. The chair expressed that coping with the staggering increase in enrolment and demands from students for a practical curriculum that was well-suited for employment had been major challenges in the last several years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary: the high tuition and enrollment numbers for international students have a profound impact on our academic departments. Our duty is to carry out good governance. I believe it is a failure of that duty to not have the information to grasp the extent of the impact, and to insufficiently weigh how it is affecting our academic units.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mission&quot;&gt;Mission&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our policy states that the University of Toronto commits to “enrolling a broad mix of international students in its programs”.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This policy, the Statement of Commitment Regarding International Students, emphasizes the richness that international students bring to our community: “contributions to the cultural life of the community” and “lasting relationships” of benefit to everyone. How has the university responded to the challenge of supporting international students and welcoming them into the wider community? Does the tuition that international students pay translate into an equivalent educational experience?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is hard to engage with the wider community when existing academic resources are lacking. In order to properly enable the sharing of cultural experiences, international students need proper support. It is clear that many international students turn to their own communities for support. As an example, the Chinese Students and Scholars Association provides a handbook that goes over academic resources and basics such as how to plan a timetable, and appears to provide WeChat groups for studying and socializing. The Chinese Undergraduate Association creates a guide similar to the old Arts and Science Student Union Anti-Calendar with notes and tips from students for specific courses. How can we justify that the burden of creating these resources appears to have been shouldered by international students themselves?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a high-profile and controversial issue when I was President of the UTSU last year. We responded by expanding our health and dental information into written Chinese (and other languages) for the first time, and increasing funding for Chinese student clubs by a third. Chinese-language campaigning in the student union election caused the most conflict, but we ended the year with a change in the rules to have the student union hire translators so that students could campaign to a broader audience, using the same platform in multiple languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see in the budget report that the university has committed to hiring 15 additional FTE staff for international &lt;em&gt;recruitment&lt;/em&gt; and exchange abroad programs—but where is the commitment to provide academic and student life support to existing international students? Since the restriction on Canadian citizenship was lifted from the University of Toronto act, at least two undergraduate student governors have been elected with primarily Chinese-language campaigns. But unlike the UTSU, this year the governing council election rules were restricted, not opened, so that candidates can now only campaign openly in English and French. The university does support international students in various ways, but is it enough to live up to the mission of our policy: to benefit from cultural exchange on our own campuses?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a final note, we might consider why it is that the mix of countries that our international enrolment originates from is so concentrated. 63% of our international undergraduate students now come from one country.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Countries such as China figure prominently in Canadian enrollment overall, but the trends in national enrollment show that international enrollment from different countries are more evenly “spread out” than it is here. There must be many complex factors at play, including recruitment, but tuition is surely one of them: if international fees are so high, we might be “pricing out” some applicants from countries that haven’t had the rapid economic growth seen by Brazil, India, South Korea and China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&amp;quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/Top 15 countries of origin for international students University of Toronto (left\) and Canada (right\) in 2014.png&amp;quot;&quot; alt=&quot;Top 15 countries of origin for international students University of Toronto left and Canada right in 2014&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;TODO Check to see if image works&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top 15 countries of origin for international students, University of Toronto (left) and Canada (right) in 2014.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sources: Facts and Figures, 2014 (University of Toronto) &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; , Canadian Bureau for International Education (Canada)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:10&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:10&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;institutional-culture-and-mission&quot;&gt;Institutional Culture and Mission&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of our highest goals is to have the students at the University of Toronto succeed: learn, grow, and graduate. This is why we guarantee that “no student offered admission to a program at the University of Toronto should be unable to enter or complete the program due to lack of financial means.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:11&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:11&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But this does not apply to international students. In 2004, when the current regime of international fee increases was first introduced, the extent to which the university will support international students if their finances take a turn for the worse was outlined by then-Vice-Provost, Students David Farrar (emphasis added):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Invited to comment, Professor Farrar said that it &lt;strong&gt;was a condition of international students’ entry to Canada that they demonstrate their ability to pay their tuition fees and to meet their other costs during their first year&lt;/strong&gt;. If a student’s circumstances changed, the University would consider the matter. While there was no formal policy, the University would make every effort to find support for students who were relatively close to completion of their programs. &lt;strong&gt;Support was less likely to be found for students in their first years of study.&lt;/strong&gt;** &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:12&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:12&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;**&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The effect of this is that international students are treated by this institution differently: as if they are a revenue driver, not part of our reason for existing. If they suffer a financial catastrophe in their first year, or beyond what can be covered with the limited pool of international needs-based aid, then they are on their own. I wish I could size up the adequacy of needs-based aid for international undergraduates, but with the current information available, it’s difficult. In the Annual Report on Student Financial Support, needs-based grants for international undergraduate and graduate students are lumped together. Overall, needs-based grants available to international students total about $2.78 million, a small amount compared to the total amount of fees paid.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:13&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:13&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also the issue that because of high international fees, the education we provide is inaccessible to foreign students who are unable to put up the required money through loans, family sacrifice, or wealth. An undergraduate international student entering next year has to show that they have $55,690 in cash (or equivalent) to receive a visa to study at this university, a significant sum.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:14&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:14&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; We do provide a limited number of fully-paid international scholarships (formerly the MasterCard Foundation Scholars Program, now the Lester B. Pearson International Scholarships) that allow us to enroll international students who would be unable to afford to come here on their own. The university has worked to expand this program, so that by 2021 there will be 150 such students enrolled out of the 13,531 projected total undergraduates in 2021.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:15&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:15&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This is commendable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as long as international tuition still functions to fill a hole in the steady-state budget, this can only ever be a token effort. At one point, international tuition was below the total program cost, but now it has surely passed over into net revenue—revenue that the university relies on to avoid having to cut short academic growth. If the revenue is needed to balance the budget, only a small portion of it can ever be made available to expand access. I would love to see an institutional culture where our budget shows that students are our primary passion and why we exist. But the reality of our budget seems to indicate a more cold-hearted attitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-business-impact-of-international-tuition-fee-decisions&quot;&gt;The Business Impact of International Tuition Fee Decisions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have seen that increasing international tuition fees the way we have been doing for the past decade has hidden impacts on the academics, mission, and culture of the University of Toronto. Some of these effects are difficult to understand with our current, limited information. However, there are business impacts that flow from these decisions as well, and they are more plainly observed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;revenue-share-risk&quot;&gt;Revenue Share Risk&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because undergraduate international tuition is so much higher compared to domestic tuition, it can represent an outsized share of a division's revenue, making the university's revenue sheet riskier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take, for example, the Faculty of Arts and Sciences. Data indicates that in 2015, international students comprised 25% of the student population.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:16&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:16&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; We don’t know what the breakdown is in this faculty between undergraduate and graduate international enrolment, but we can estimate from the university-wide numbers that the ratio was about 1.17:1 undergraduate:graduate for international enrolment share in 2015.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:17&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:17&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; We know that in November 2015 there were 21,240 undergraduate FTEs and 3,776 graduate FTEs in the Faculty of Arts and Science.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:18&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:18&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  We &lt;em&gt;estimate&lt;/em&gt; that this works out to about 825 international graduate students (21.8% of FTE enrollment) and about 5429 international undergraduate students (25.6% of FTE enrollment).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:19&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:19&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Making the conservative assumption that enrollment is evenly allocated among all four years of undergraduate study, we can estimate that the average international undergraduate tuition paid in 2015 was $35,950&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:20&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:20&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Making another conservative assumption, we can estimate the average FTE graduate tuition for 2015 using the doctoral stream rate, which was $19,550.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:21&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:21&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these conservative assumptions, this works out to an estimate of about $211 million in revenue from international student tuition for the Faculty of Arts and Science&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:22&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:22&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, or 37% of the faculty's attributed revenue for 2015.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:23&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:23&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Attributed revenue includes much more than just tuition and operating grants, so it's likely that the portion of enrollment-driven revenue from international students is just under half—yet this large portion only comes from a quarter of the faculty's enrollment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two important things to notice from this exercise. First, this large portion of the faculty's revenue is risky: subject to currency fluctuations, the domestic and foreign policy of foreign governments, and the University of Toronto's position in international rankings. Compared to other Ontario universities, this risk is magnified &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; because of how many international students we have, but &lt;em&gt;because we charge them such high tuition&lt;/em&gt;. Second, it's incredibly difficult to get a precise handle on how large the revenue portion is for different divisions and departments of the university with the information we currently have. It took me four different sources to generate a very rough estimate for only &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; division. It shouldn't be this hard to understand one of the biggest revenue drivers in our budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;exchange-rate-risks&quot;&gt;Exchange Rate Risks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the tuition fee schedule that we receive every year, the administration often refers to foreign exchange rates to show that the perceived cost of tuition is lower (or higher) than we would perceive from the Canadian dollar price tag. I remember seeing a graph to this effect in the budget presentation in 2015. While it may be comforting to know that in some years the 10% entering and 5% continuing increases are partly offset by exchange rate fluctuations, is this a good metric to consider for the purpose of planning and governance? We can't confidently predict foreign exchange rates five years ahead, and over a longer period of time I would consider them more of a source of potential volatility than a reliable tuition &quot;discount&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can also cause serious problems for our international students—in November 2014, the Russian rouble dropped about a third of its value compared to the Canadian dollar&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:24&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:24&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, meaning that students from that country had to pay a third more than they were expecting to pay off the balance of their tuition. I personally heard abut the pain and frustration of this problem from a number of Russian international students when I was a governor. Currency fluctuations can be good or bad for our international students, but we do not have enough financial aid available to always have the ability to support students when there is a catastrophe. Over the long run, exchange rates are a source of risk for our students and for our budget, and not a reliable discount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;enrollment-mix-risks&quot;&gt;Enrollment Mix Risks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compounding the risks from revenue share and exchange rates is the fact that the University of Toronto relies on a smaller number of countries for most of our international enrollment compared to other Canadian universities. We have already looked at the differences between the make-up of our international enrollment and Canadian trends. I think it would suffice to say that if you think about the large estimated revenue share from international students, and how most of them come from a small handful of countries, it is clear that a change in a single exchange rate, a single foreign economy, or a single country's policies could quickly put a hole in our budget. I have already seen other governors and commenters express concerns about this before, so I believe this is a concern that you are all already aware of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;which-risky-path-do-we-take&quot;&gt;Which Risky Path Do We Take?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When concerns about the risks of balancing the budget with high international tuition fees have been brought up before, there have been two main responses, highlighting how the university is saving up for potentially difficult times ahead. First, there is an emphasis on putting extra revenue towards capital projects, investments that will benefit the university for a long time. Second, the university is being cautious, and saving money in reserve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can observe the effect of this strategy by looking at the financial statements over time, with cash reserves for future spending likely to top $1 billion next year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/Net Income or Loss vs Cash Reserves.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cash Reserves for Future Spending vs. Net Income or Loss&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cash Reserves for Future Spending vs. Net Income or Loss&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source: University of Toronto Financial Statements, 1997–2016.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2017 net income is projected to be CAD $178.4 Million&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:25&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:25&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one way to prudently plan for the future, but it still has downsides. Enrolment growth for both domestic and international students is expected to level off in the future, leaving us much more reliant on tuition increases to maintain revenue growth. The revenue share, exchange rate, and enrollment mix risks are structural, not ephemeral, so if things turn for the worse, what will the university do once the reserves are depleted? If we climb up to $64,500 tuition in 2021, it will be much harder to reverse course, and the hidden impacts on our institution’s values and mission will have taken deep root.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, we can choose to take another risk: to lower our plans for international tuition so that we have a more balanced revenue share and enrollment. We will save less money in reserve, but if we make ourselves a more inclusive international institution, with more affordable international tuition, we can spread out the risk of a sudden shock in a single currency or the economy and policies of a single foreign country. We can also start to live up to the goals of our own policies: to take charge of which academic programs expand or shrink, to create a welcoming, broad community of cross-cultural scholarship, and to share our education more openly with the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can comfort ourselves with knowing that our international tuition fees are comparable to other highly-ranked institutions in the US, but we may not have the same reserves, endowment, and exchange rates as they do as we continue on this risky path. More importantly, our role is determine what is best for this institution, in alignment with &lt;em&gt;our own values&lt;/em&gt;. If we decide to follow the pack, it should only be if we have decided for ourselves that doing so fits with our mission and principles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, there are two risky plans we can take: the first is to continue on our current trajectory and hope that our reserve funds will be enough when things turn for the worse. The second is to have a plan for lower international tuition to address the structural risks we have introduced by relying on international fees to balance our budget, and hope that the reduced risk will compensate for lower reserves. I prefer the latter, so that our finances do not warp our purpose away from education and the students we serve.  We need to ask our administration for the information to understand these issues, we need them to evaluate the risks and benefits of different possible plans, and we need them to present a real choice so that Governing Council has the opportunity to decide what kind of institution the University of Toronto should become.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sincerely,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ben Coleman&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;recommendations&quot;&gt;Recommendations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some suggestions for action and information based on the issues I have discussed in this letter. Not all of them are within the scope of this board, but I think they are all worth mentioning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;action&quot;&gt;Action&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Direct the administration to evaluate the risks and benefits of a long-term plan for lower international tuition fees; to be reported to governance in a reasonable time frame for a decision.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Investigate the academic and co-curricular needs of international students, with the goal of providing adequate support.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Investigate the potential to broaden the University of Toronto's international enrolment with lower fees and changes to recruitment; to be reported to governance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Investigate the possibility of ensuring that all international students who enroll at the university receive a guarantee that they can complete their studies regardless of financial challenges during their degree; to be reported to governance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Direct the administration to make sure that diversified funding for the Lester B. Pearson scholarship program is secured, including from advancement.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Investigate how the level of international fees and international enrolment projections might affect the growth and needs of academic departments in the university. To be reported to Academic Board for further consideration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;information&quot;&gt;Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Provide detailed, granular information on the needs-based aid available to international students to be made available to Governing Council at their next meeting in conjunction with the tuition fee schedule, and to be included in annual reporting in the future.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Provide information about the revenue share per faculty and department, with a breakdown and 5-year projection of domestic tuition and government operating grants compared to international tuition. To be made available to Governing Council at their next meeting in conjunction with the tuition fee schedule if possible, and to be included in annual reporting in the future.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Provide an estimate of the per-student cost of education compared to the international tuition rates, similar to information provided in 2003-2004, and 2004-2005.  To be made available to Governing Council at their next meeting in conjunction with the tuition fee schedule if possible, and to be included in annual reporting in the future.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Include a high-level projection of international and domestic tuition rates along with the 5-year projections in the budget report, in the future.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Provide information about the preferences of international and domestic students at this university for fields of study, including information about how fee level affects preferences.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Include an analysis of how exchange rates affect international tuition rates on a risk basis, along with existing examples of how exchange rates affect affordability in different countries, for annual reporting in the future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to Katrina Vogan for her assistance editing.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have chosen to use the example of Arts and Science tuition fees to illustrate changes over time. The full picture is more complex, but since they are the most representative example, I have chosen not to go into lengthy detail about changes in international fees for other programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1(b)        In light of these considerations, the Governing Council has adopted the Statement of Commitment Regarding International Students which commits the University to enrolling a broad mix of international students in its programs, and which articulates the basic principles that will guide their admission to the University, arrangements for their financial support, right of access to academic courses and programs, and provision of services to address their particular needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exact figures are as follows: in 2015-2016, 18.9% of undergraduate students were international, and 16.1% of graduate students were international. These numbers are for the university as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chart indicates that the percentages are based on headcount. Since part-time students are almost entirely domestic students, this probably means that international students as a % of FTE is underestimated, making the total estimate of international tuition revenue more conservative than it already is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fees for professional masters' programs are generally higher than those in the doctoral stream (research masters and PhD programs). So it's an underestimate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Tuition Fee Schedule for Publicly-funded Programs 2017-18, page 28. Item 1(a) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Report number 133 of the Business Board, April 14, 2004, page 13. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.governingcouncil.utoronto.ca/Assets/Governing+Council+Digital+Assets/Boards+and+Committees/Business+Board/2003/r0414.pdf&quot;&gt;http://www.governingcouncil.utoronto.ca/Assets/Governing+Council+Digital+Assets/Boards+and+Committees/Business+Board/2003/r0414.pdf&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Report number 133 of the Business Board, April 14, 2004, page 13. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In 2005-2006, international undergraduate enrolment was 4,982, 8.6% of total undergraduate enrolment. In 2015-2016, it was 15,931, 28.2% of total undergraduate enrollment.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Source: University of Toronto Facts and Figures 2006, page 40; and [https://www.utoronto.ca/about-u-of-t/quick-facts](https://www.utoronto.ca/about-u-of-t/quick-facts) (Accessed February 22, 2017, showing numbers for 2015-2016).
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.univcan.ca/universities/facts-and-stats/tuition-fees-by-university/&quot;&gt;http://www.univcan.ca/universities/facts-and-stats/tuition-fees-by-university/&lt;/a&gt;, numbers for 2016-2017. Accessed February 22, 2017. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Statement of Commitment Regarding International Students, 2005, Section 1(b). &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.governingcouncil.utoronto.ca/Assets/Governing+Council+Digital+Assets/Policies/PDF/ppmar302005.pdf&quot;&gt;http://www.governingcouncil.utoronto.ca/Assets/Governing+Council+Digital+Assets/Policies/PDF/ppmar302005.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;The full clause is as follows:
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Enrolment Report for 2016-17, page 6. Item 1(d) &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.governingcouncil.lamp4.utoronto.ca/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/a0227-1di-2016-2017bb.pdf&quot;&gt;http://www.governingcouncil.lamp4.utoronto.ca/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/a0227-1di-2016-2017bb.pdf&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;University of Toronto Facts and Figures, 2014, page 34. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.utoronto.ca/sites/default/files/Facts_Figures_2014_Entire_Book_online_versionNew.pdf&quot;&gt;https://www.utoronto.ca/sites/default/files/Facts_Figures_2014_Entire_Book_online_versionNew.pdf&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:10&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&quot;Facts and Figures&quot;. &lt;a href=&quot;http://cbie.ca/media/facts-and-figures/&quot;&gt;http://cbie.ca/media/facts-and-figures/&lt;/a&gt; Accessed February 25, 2017. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:10&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:11&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Governing Council Policy on Student Financial Support, approved April 1998. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:11&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:12&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Report Number 133 of the Business Board – April 14, 2004, page 17. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.governingcouncil.utoronto.ca/Assets/Governing+Council+Digital+Assets/Boards+and+Committees/Business+Board/2003/r0414.pdf&quot;&gt;http://www.governingcouncil.utoronto.ca/Assets/Governing+Council+Digital+Assets/Boards+and+Committees/Business+Board/2003/r0414.pdf&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:12&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:13&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Annual Report on Student Financial Support, 2015-16, page 15, Item 1(c).&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Total merit and needs based aid for international students totaled \$10.3 Million, with 73% going to merit-based aid.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:13&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:14&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Citizenship and Immigration Canada. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cic.gc.ca/english/study/study-how-documents.asp#doc3&quot;&gt;http://www.cic.gc.ca/english/study/study-how-documents.asp#doc3&lt;/a&gt; Accessed February 25, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;A prospective student has to show that they have tuition + \$10,000 for the 12-month period, or more if a family member is applying to live with them.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:14&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:15&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Total projected number from page 11 of the Enrolment Report. 150 Lester B. Pearson scholarship students announced on page 16 of the Report on Student Financial Support. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:15&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:16&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“About” page, Faculty of Arts and Science Website. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.artsci.utoronto.ca/main/about&quot;&gt;http://www.artsci.utoronto.ca/main/about&lt;/a&gt; Accessed February 24th , 2017. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:16&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:17&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Enrolment Report for 2016-17, page 31 (Table 15: International Enrolment) Item 1(d). &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.governingcouncil.lamp4.utoronto.ca/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/a0227-1di-2016-2017bb.pdf&quot;&gt;http://www.governingcouncil.lamp4.utoronto.ca/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/a0227-1di-2016-2017bb.pdf&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:17&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:18&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Facts and Figures, 2015, page 32, &quot;Enrolment by Campus and Faculty/College&quot;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.utoronto.ca/sites/default/files/Facts_Figures_2015_online_entire_book.pdf&quot;&gt;https://www.utoronto.ca/sites/default/files/Facts_Figures_2015_online_entire_book.pdf&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:18&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:19&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I'm not going to display the arithmetic here, but it's a classic two-equation substitution problem. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:19&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:20&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Tuition Fee Schedule for Publicly Funded Programs, 2015-2016, page 31 and 36 (graduate). &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.governingcouncil.utoronto.ca/AssetFactory.aspx?did=10976&quot;&gt;http://www.governingcouncil.utoronto.ca/AssetFactory.aspx?did=10976&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:20&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:21&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Tuition Fee Schedule for Publicly Funded Programs, 2015-2016, page 36. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:21&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:22&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The exact number is $211,301,300. Since it's an estimate, rounded to the nearest million makes more sense. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:22&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:23&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Budget Report 2015-2016 and Long-Range Budget Guidelines 2015-16 to 2019-20, page 33 (Appendix A, Schedule 4). &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.governingcouncil.utoronto.ca/AssetFactory.aspx?did=11080&quot;&gt;http://www.governingcouncil.utoronto.ca/AssetFactory.aspx?did=11080&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Total attributed revenue for the Faculty of Arts and Science was budgeted at \$577,708,868. Broadly speaking, attributed revenue includes student fees, provincial general operating grants, investment income, sales &amp;amp;amp; services, recovery from Canada Research Chair grants, and funding for indirect research costs. It does not include research grants directly flowing to divisions, capital funds, funds going into the endowment, etc.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:23&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:24&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Generally, the exchange rate dropped from about 0.3 CAD per RUB to 0.2 CAD per RUB. Source: Yahoo Finance &lt;a href=&quot;http://finance.yahoo.com/quote/RUBCAD=X?ltr=1&quot;&gt;http://finance.yahoo.com/quote/RUBCAD=X?ltr=1&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:24&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:25&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Forecast of University Financial Results at April 30, 2017, prepared as of January 4, 2017. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.governingcouncil.lamp4.utoronto.ca/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/a0123-7i-2016-2017bb.pdf&quot;&gt;http://www.governingcouncil.lamp4.utoronto.ca/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/a0123-7i-2016-2017bb.pdf&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:25&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><summary type="html">Download this letter in PDF format</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bloor-Yorkville BIA Blog Posts - 2016</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/bloor-yorkville%20bia/2016/09/10/Bloor-Yorkville-BIA-Blog-Posts.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bloor-Yorkville BIA Blog Posts - 2016" /><published>2016-09-10T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-09-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/bloor-yorkville%20bia/2016/09/10/Bloor-Yorkville-BIA-Blog-Posts</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/bloor-yorkville%20bia/2016/09/10/Bloor-Yorkville-BIA-Blog-Posts.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a list of Blog posts I wrote for the Bloor-Yorkville Business Improvement Area in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;6th-annual-yorkville-exotic-car-show-raises-record-55000-for-prostate-cancer-canada&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bloor-yorkville.com/6th-annual-yorkville-exotic-car-show-raises-record-55000-for-prostate-cancer-canada/&quot;&gt;6th Annual Yorkville Exotic Car Show Raises Record $55,000 for Prostate Cancer Canada!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bloor-yorkville.com/6th-annual-yorkville-exotic-car-show-raises-record-55000-for-prostate-cancer-canada/&quot;&gt;Link to Article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The text for this post was mostly based off of a template from previous years, but I had complete freedom to make up my own graphics to thank the partners and sponsors, such as this one:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/YECS-Wrap-Up-Contest-Sponsors-Graphic.png&quot; alt=&quot;Contest Sponsors Graphic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;unique-in-yorkville-carrera-y-carrera&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bloor-yorkville.com/unique-in-yorkvillecarrera-y-carrera/&quot;&gt;Unique in Yorkville: Carrera y Carrera&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bloor-yorkville.com/unique-in-yorkvillecarrera-y-carrera/&quot;&gt;Link to Article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is about a fairly unique jewellery boutique in Yorkville that opened recently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Their Bloor-Yorkville boutique brings a different flair to the local jewellery market—&lt;em&gt;Carrera y Carrera&lt;/em&gt; doesn’t really make jewellery. Its artisans consider its pieces to be miniature sculptures of gold and precious stones, a philosophy driven home by the signature piece in the Manuel Carrera Private Collection: a pendant of solid gold and diamonds depicting a woman and man’s embrace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/Old-York-Lane.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of Old York Lane&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;in-yorkvilles-taz-hair-salon-stylist-norm-wright-is-starting-a-small-environmnetal-revolution&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bloor-yorkville.com/in-yorkvilles-taz-hair-salon-stylist-norm-wright-is-starting-a-small-environmental-revolution/&quot;&gt;In Yorkville’s TAZ Hair Salon, Stylist Norm Wright is Starting a Small Environmnetal Revolution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bloor-yorkville.com/in-yorkvilles-taz-hair-salon-stylist-norm-wright-is-starting-a-small-environmental-revolution/&quot;&gt;Link to Article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was an immensely fun assignment. What I really wanted was to show the magazine cover that featured Norm’s stunning color work, but alas I’m not sure what magic combination of words will get your call returned by a style magazine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is because Norm Wright and colleague Frank Cini are the inventors of &lt;a href=&quot;http://biodegradablebeauty.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Biodegradable Beauty&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a fully-compostable foil alternative for doing colour and highlights. They soft-launched the product about a year ago as a small step towards reducing the alarming amount of waste they saw in salons all over North America. “I’ve been doing this for 30 years” Norm says, as he mixes colour at his bench. “The first piece of foil I’ve used on somebody’s hair is still in the garbage somewhere. So, when you add the numbers up, 420,000 hair salons in North America—the quantity of waste—is ridiculous.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-timeless-scollard-deli&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bloor-yorkville.com/the-timeless-scollard-deli/&quot;&gt;The Timeless Scollard Deli&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bloor-yorkville.com/the-timeless-scollard-deli/&quot;&gt;Link to Article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/Patio-Mural-768x576.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Patio at the Scollard Deli&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things that makes the Bloor-Yorkville neighborhood interesting is how rapidly it has changed over the years. I’m reminded of this when I look at all the development applications in the area, or look at photos of Bloor street before all the sleek granite was installed. Scollard Deli is a holdout of past days, when not everything was a condo, and the neighborhood was dotted with beautiful restaurant patios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pearl-miller-la-chance-owner-dress-superhero&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bloor-yorkville.com/pearl-miller-la-chance-owner-dress-superhero/&quot;&gt;Pearl Miller: La Chance Owner, Dress Superhero&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bloor-yorkville.com/pearl-miller-la-chance-owner-dress-superhero/&quot;&gt;Link to Article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/La-Chance-Cover-Photo-Edited-1766031170.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cover Photo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think Pearl Miller was my favourite interviewee. She’s an incredibly funny and deeply impressive person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also read the post here: &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/bloor-yorkville%20bia/2016/09/08/Pearl-Miller-La-Chance-Owner-Dress-Superhero.html&quot;&gt;http://localhost:4000/bloor-yorkville%20bia/2016/09/08/Pearl-Miller-La-Chance-Owner-Dress-Superhero.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><category term="Portfolio" /><category term="Bloor-Yorkville 2016" /><summary type="html">This is a list of Blog posts I wrote for the Bloor-Yorkville Business Improvement Area in 2016.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pearl Miller: La Chance Owner, Dress Superhero</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/bloor-yorkville%20bia/2016/09/08/Pearl-Miller-La-Chance-Owner-Dress-Superhero.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pearl Miller: La Chance Owner, Dress Superhero" /><published>2016-09-08T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-09-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/bloor-yorkville%20bia/2016/09/08/Pearl-Miller-La-Chance-Owner-Dress-Superhero</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/bloor-yorkville%20bia/2016/09/08/Pearl-Miller-La-Chance-Owner-Dress-Superhero.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/La-Chance-Cover-Photo-Edited-1766031170.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cover Photo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This article originally appeared on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://bloor-yorkville.com/pearl-miller-la-chance-owner-dress-superhero/&quot;&gt;Bloor-Yorkville BIA Blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pearl Miller almost missed her calling. After separating from her husband, the continued boredom of a fourteenth year working for the federal government was off the table, as she found herself wanting to do something more ambitious. She started staying up late, making batches of clothes in her house, and throwing a party every couple of months to sell them to friends. Yet, when she finally made her move and quit her job, fashion wasn’t the first thing she had in mind for her business:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I went to the bank one day and I spoke to the manager” she tells me. “I said ‘I want to have a very unique little restaurant’ he said ‘oh, I don’t know, restaurants are very… lots of failures. What else are you interested in?’ I said ‘Fashion? That’s my next thing.’ So he said ‘I know somebody on Charles Street who’s closing their business. Would you like to open up at number 5? A little tiny place.’ So he left the bank and brought me down to 5 Charles Street West. And I said ‘I think this is ideal. This is exactly what I want to do!’ and he had me speak to the woman who owned it, and in a very short time, I opened my shop in April 1988. In the midst of the &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; recession.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/Pearl-and-Photo-Book-1024x768.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of Pearl with a Photo Album of Dresses&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Pearl with her photo collection: dresses and clients from over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She asks me if I remember the ’88 recession. I don’t. She and her friend laugh. At that point, I was just a doodle on a love note I found as a teenager, in one of my mother’s university textbooks. However, Black Monday, the savings and loans crisis—that defined my birth (in Barbados because engineering jobs in Canada were scarce in the early 90’s). It defined the birth of La Chance as well: Pearl tells me a friend suggested the name while they were shopping, looking for some hats to sell in the store:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I said ‘I don’t even have a name for the store!’ I have no idea, I just wanted something Japanese or whatever, and she was from France, and she was really nice, and I said ‘everyone’s telling me it’s a bad time to open a business in ’88, and the recession is really deep… but I think this is the right time’ and she said ‘you need something that says &lt;em&gt;luck&lt;/em&gt;’, which is ‘La Chance’ [in French] and that’s how the name came to be.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it’s luck that La Chance, with a stunning array of hand-made gowns, skirts, and blazers is still going strong today. I choose to believe it’s Pearl’s creative mind and immense talent for customer service. “I love people. I’m good with people” she tells me. This is an understatement. She’s showing a shimmering green dress to a customer while I interview her, and despite my interruptions, she’s clearly helping the woman fall deeply in love with it. When the woman leaves, her parting words are “I am so glad that I discovered this shop.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/Store-Display-Mannequins-1024x768.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of Dresses on display at the front of the store&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Dresses on display at the front of the store&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pearl mentions that she once made a whole wardrobe for a customer who went on a cruise. I call the customer later: “Her service is amazing. It’s a very special store. I’m quite a shopper—if it’s not with Pearl, it’s at Holt Renfrew or Andrew’s. It’s that level of store.” The cruise wardrobe that Pearl created for her wasn’t just a simple collection either: it had “ball gowns and costumes for 99 days, with 33 formal nights and 10 or 12 themes that you needed costumes for. I was certainly the star of the ship.” She says that pearl knows her customers so well, that once you’re a regular, you can just walk in and Pearl will show you things that she’s already been thinking will look good on you. “You know, I’ve never gone in there and bought nothing.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My real mission is to see Pearl’s workshop in the basement of her current location—13 Charles Street—and understand her creative process. She makes all of the garments from scratch, using her own designs. She leads me down the narrow staircase from the shop floor to show me where the clothes are made. She has three people working downstairs at the moment: one woman who travels in part time to help with the sewing, another at the cutting table setting out pattern pieces, and a third person working with the fabric. This invisible army is part of the shop’s unique approach to customer service: when you try on a dress, Pearl shows you how she’ll do the alterations so that it fits just right on your body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ask how she comes up with her designs. Unlike many designers, Pearl looks for the fabric first before making sketches. “You have to fall in love with the fabric. You have to really like it… to know what to do with it” she says. Often, she doesn’t know what to make out of a fabric she loves, but will wake up in the middle of the night with an idea and start sketching. She shows me a photo of a dress she made for an AIDS benefit years ago: a mostly see-through creation made of black chiffon with hoops and taping for structure. She tells me the fabric was a challenge at first, but after letting her mind wander, while waiting for a doctor’s appointment, she rushed back with inspiration and started sketching with her pattern-maker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pearl has participated in many charity events: from multiple benefits for people living with HIV/AIDS to a fashion show for domestic abuse survivors. She shows me some of her creations from the early 90’s: a flowing white dress and an absolutely bonkers all-denim dress with a ruffled, hooped skirt and a hat that is almost indescribable (and probably just as difficult to wear).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/La-Chance-Dress-COLLAGE-1024x768.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of Two dresses made by Pearl for an AIDS benefit&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Two dresses made by Pearl for an AIDS benefit&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I keep trying to ask questions that will help me explain how inspiring I find her story to be, but Pearl isn’t having it—she talks as if coming from Jamaica to Canada and starting a business, as a mother of two, mid-life is just something you wake up in the morning and do, so I try a different approach. What advice would she give to other aspiring small business owners?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Be organized. Know what you’re doing, know what your staff is doing, and be prepared… The second thing is client service. I really think that in order to stay in business you have to 200% look after your clients. They have to feel that when they come in here, this is a warm place, a comfortable place, and that you’re honest and truthful in what you’re telling them.” I ask if she would tell a customer if a dress wasn’t the right look for them. She would. “I never want a customer to come out of here with something that isn’t right for them” she says… [and] most of our customers have become friends. That’s really key.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ask Marcia, the lady on the floor, who has been joining in the interview and sharing our laughs and photos, if Pearl is a tough boss. “Um… I don’t really work here” she says with a laugh. “I’m just helping.” “But am I tough?” Pearl asks her. “Tell the truth!” “No, no she’s not…” she answers, which elicits a laugh from Pearl. “Well, I don’t think that’s what you say sometimes!” They both burst out laughing. “I am tactful” Pearl says, “but I expect people to perform. I expect a good day’s work for what they’re paid. But if I give them something to do, I’m not going to be over them all of the time.” She likes to treat her staff well, and be kind with criticism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/Pearl-is-Boss-1024x768.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of Pearl striking a commanding pose&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“But am I tough? … Tell the truth!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I leave, I ask her if she has anything in the store that reminds her of growing up in Jamaica. She shows me an old sewing machine on a front shelf that a customer gave to her. She tells me that her mother made clothes for her whole family on a machine that looks like this—for her, for her seven sisters, and for her two brothers—ten children in total. At the beginning of the interview, she had told me that her family was very close-knit. Her store has created a kind of family as well, with a house on 13 Charles Street West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you visit, she will find you something unique and beautiful to wear that will last for decades. You will feel at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/Old-Sewing-Machine-1024x768.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of an old sewing machine&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Pearl’s mother used to make clothes for her whole family of 10 children using a machine like this one. According to Pearl, her mother later got a foot-pedal operated machine, which she really liked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;views-from-the-la-chance-workshop&quot;&gt;Views From the La Chance Workshop&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/La-Chance-Workshop-Thread.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of Spools of thread next to the ironing board&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/La-Chance-Workshop-Patterns.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of The pattern-making table&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Images/La-Chance-Workshop-Sewing-Station.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of Pearl and one of her employees in the workshop at the sewing station&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><category term="Portfolio" /><category term="Bloor-Yorkville 2016" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>