<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-04-21T16:27:52-04:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/feed.xml</id><title type="html">tallcoleman</title><subtitle>A Blog on Politics and Nature
</subtitle><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><entry><title type="html">Formatting Restrictions in Grant Portals: Part I</title><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/writing/2019/04/07/Formatting-Restrictions-in-Grant-Portals-Part-I.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Formatting Restrictions in Grant Portals: Part I" /><published>2019-04-07T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-04-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/writing/2019/04/07/Formatting-Restrictions-in-Grant-Portals-Part-I</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tallcoleman.me/writing/2019/04/07/Formatting-Restrictions-in-Grant-Portals-Part-I.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-pains-of-plaintext&quot;&gt;The Pains of Plaintext&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my biggest frustrations with grant portals is that they make writing feel primitive. Most portals only allow you to submit answers in unformatted plaintext, taking away a lot of important formatting tools that good writers use to make their text easy to read and to understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t just take my word for it: some of the things in the standard formatting toolbox come recommended by the U.S. government! At &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.plainlanguage.gov&quot;&gt;plainlanguage.gov&lt;/a&gt; you can find a whole set of guidelines about how to be a clear and effective writer. These guidelines are designed for people in government who might write a regulation, a form, or a letter that is sent out to citizens, but the advice applies to a lot of technical writing. Grant writing is no exception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a selection of some of their tips:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.plainlanguage.gov/guidelines/organize/add-useful-headings/&quot;&gt;Add useful headings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.plainlanguage.gov/guidelines/design/highlight-important-concepts/&quot;&gt;Highlight important concepts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.plainlanguage.gov/guidelines/organize/use-lists/&quot;&gt;Use lists&lt;/a&gt; (with bullets or numbers)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.plainlanguage.gov/guidelines/design/use-tables-to-make-complex-material-easier-to-understand/&quot;&gt;Use tables to make complex material easier to understand&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.plainlanguage.gov/guidelines/design/consider-using-visuals/&quot;&gt;Consider using visuals&lt;/a&gt; (such as diagrams, maps, and images)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The descriptive text for “Highlight important concepts” is particularly fun to read:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You can … add &lt;strong&gt;bold&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;em&gt;italics&lt;/em&gt; to emphasize important concepts within a particular section …. Only emphasize important information, otherwise you’ll dilute its impact.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;PUTTING EVERYTHING IN CAPITAL LETTERS IS NOT A GOOD EMPHASIS TECHNIQUE. ALTHOUGH IT MAY DRAW THE USER’S ATTENTION TO THE SECTION, IT MAKES IT HARDER TO READ. AND ONLINE, IT’S CONSIDERED SHOUTING.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inspired by this fabulous &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/graphics/apple-still-hasnt-fixed-its-macbook-keyboard-problem/&quot;&gt;Wall Street Journal Article&lt;/a&gt;, I’m going to start removing these formatting techniques as I talk about them so that you can see what it looks like when you’re not able to use them in your writing&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem-1-organizing-complex-information-is-hard-without-headings&quot;&gt;Problem 1: Organizing Complex Information is Hard Without Headings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most grant applications, it’s not a huge deal that you can’t make your own headings because the application is structured for you, with headings and questions set out by the funder. However, I still find myself using headings all the time—usually in one of two cases:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;case-1---the-question-is-incredibly-long&quot;&gt;Case 1 - The Question Is Incredibly Long&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most grant application questions have word limits in the range of 100–500 words. Since a full page of single-spaced writing is usually about 500 words, this makes things very manageable, and ensures that there’s usually at least one heading on each page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there are some cases where questions can be much, much longer. In the Year 1 Canada Council for the Arts operating funding application, half of the questions are over 500 words, and the longest is a full 3,000 words, which is about &lt;em&gt;six full pages&lt;/em&gt; of text. For one question!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;case-2---the-question-has-multiple-parts&quot;&gt;Case 2 - The Question Has Multiple Parts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quite often, a question will ask you to talk about multiple things in the same answer. Take this question from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arts.on.ca/grants/general-granting-information/guide-to-operating-programs/operating-program-application-questions&quot;&gt;Ontario Arts Council operating funding application&lt;/a&gt;, for example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brief History&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Tell us about your organization, for example: the year you were founded, what you’re doing now, the communities you serve, important milestones in your development and how they have had an impact on your current programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This question has a 250-word limit, so instead of moving from topic to topic with transition sentences, you can just use simple headings instead like “Current Activities”, “Milestones”, and “Communities Served” to jump between topics without wasting words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make sure the reviewers don’t get lost in the sea of your 3,000 word answer or can follow along as you jump between different topics or time periods, you have to use headings, even though it’s not supported in plaintext. The best workaround I’ve found so far is to shout THIS IS A HEADING in all caps and put some extra space before it through judicious use of the enter key. It’s not ideal—it doesn’t help people who might use headings to navigate with a screen reader—and you can’t use bigger or smaller headings to organize your work in a sophisticated way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h2 class=&quot;noformat&quot;&gt;PROBLEM 2: YOU CAN'T HIGHLIGHT KEY POINTS OR ITALICIZE TITLES IN PLAINTEXT&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s try an experiment. Imagine you are skimming the following paragraph in an application. Where do your eyes land? How long does it take you to understand the main point of the paragraph?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Schools scoring in the top 25% of the &lt;strong&gt;Learning Opportunity Index (LOI)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; make up 40% of paid attendees, and schools in the bottom 25% only represent 10% of participants, showing that schools from lower-income neighbourhoods face barriers to attending our theatre programs. However, ABC Neighbourhood Theatre  has long run a targeted program offering complimentary tickets, with over 80% of free tickets going to schools with LOI scores in the bottom 25%. As a result, &lt;strong&gt;30% of our total attendees are from schools with LOI scores in the bottom 25%, demonstrating our commitment to serving schools that do not usually have good access to arts programs&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now skim it again without the formatting. What changes? Are you still able to figure out the main point in only a couple seconds?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Schools scoring in the top 25% of the Learning Opportunity Index (LOI) make up 40% of paid attendees, and schools in the bottom 25% only represent 10% of participants, showing that schools from lower-income neighbourhoods face barriers to attending our theatre programs. However, ABC Neighbourhood Theatre  has long run a targeted program offering complimentary tickets, with over 80% of free tickets going to schools with LOI scores in the bottom 25%. As a result, 30% of our total attendees are from schools with LOI scores in the bottom 25%, demonstrating our commitment to serving schools that do not usually have good access to arts programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you are able to put your key points in bold, you have much more flexibility to decide how to structure your writing. In this case, it allows you to use the following logical sequence…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Problem&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Solution&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Result&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…&lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; having the reader miss your key point at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you can’t use formatting for emphasis, you have to write &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; like a newspaper article—main point at the top, and less important information below. The only thing you can do to help out a skim reader is to put your paragraph breaks in the right places. IT’S NOT LIKE YOU CAN PUT YOUR KEY POINTS IN ALL CAPS INSTEAD. THEN YOU JUST COME ACROSS LIKE &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hmxAfAXhAYk&quot;&gt;“LOUD HOWARD” FROM DILBERT&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h3 class=&quot;noformat&quot;&gt;A WORKAROUND FOR ITALICS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As someone who has mostly written grants for arts organizations, one of the most frustrating limitations of grant portals is that you can’t use italics, since they are an essential part of writing titles of artistic works like movies and pieces of music. There’s an easy workaround for this, but let me illustrate the problem first:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine that there is a composer who writes a piece for orchestra called “My deepest, most horrible fantasy”. When I write my grant, I might write a sentence like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The orchestra performed &lt;em&gt;My deepest, most horrible fantasy&lt;/em&gt; in Salzburg last spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see that the italics really help make it clear that the orchestra did not commit any crimes or heinous acts on stage in Salzburg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution is pretty simple—use single quotes instead. So in most portals, I would write:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The orchestra performed ‘My deepest, most horrible fantasy’ in Salzburg last spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only challenges I sometimes come across are communicating this convention to my editors (I usually leave a note at the top saying something like “single quotes = italics”) and catching myself when I habitually italicize things in my answers. Fortunately, searching for italicized text is &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.office.com/en-us/article/find-and-replace-text-or-formatting-in-word-for-mac-ac12f262-e3cd-439a-88a0-f5a59875dcea&quot;&gt;actually quite easy in Microsoft Word&lt;/a&gt;, so you can just look for any italics that should be single quotes before the text is uploaded into a portal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there isn’t really a good replacement for using italics as a method of emphasis. You could use some plaintext alternatives, but they *very* often look _incredibly_ odd, and -unprofessional- to many readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h2 class=&quot;noformat&quot;&gt;PROBLEM 3: LIFE WITHOUT LISTS IS LACKING&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, I’ve shown you that  *without formatting*:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;- you can only use ALL CAPS for headings, which is a little off-putting, not very sophisticated, and not terribly accessible&lt;br&gt;
- you can't highlight key points to help skim readers, and you can't italicize titles of artistic works etc. and have to use single quotes instead&lt;br&gt;
- you can't use italics for emphasis, unless you want to look very _strange_.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1. Now it’s time to explore what it means to write without proper lists. As you can see above, without formatting, lists can start to look a little messy and become harder to read. If you want your list items to go on for multiple lines, then the numbering or bullets you use really don’t stand out as strongly as they should. I’ve numbered these paragraphs so you can see what that looks like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2. You can re-write your lists into paragraphs, but that will make them harder to read (there’s a reason listicles are so popular), it will probably increase your word count, and it won’t give you the benefit of providing some variety in the way you write your answers. The Canada Council application I mentioned earlier is about 22 pages long—can you imagine how much harder it would be to read 22 pages without the occasional list to spice things up a bit?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3. Lists are another great way to emphasize key points. If you want to talk about the three key parts of your strategic plan, a list will make it stand out. If it looks like the three paragraphs you just read, the effect is nowhere near as strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h2 class=&quot;noformat&quot;&gt;NEXT WEEK: TABLES, VISUALS, AND OTHER GRIPES&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have more formatting complaints to make, but those will have to wait for the next post. This is already pretty long, and I definitely need to look up how to make tables in markdown before I keep going…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a concluding thought to tie all these things together, when I tell people that I’m a grant writer, people often tell me that they think grant writing is uniquely difficult, with lots of traps you need to avoid and tricks and techniques you have to know to be successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an ideal world, it wouldn’t be like this. If you assume that funders want to give funding to the best organizations and the best ideas, then that should be possible without talented grant writers. Putting barriers in the way of clear communication only benefits established organizations who have grant writers on staff. List formatting and ALL CAPS HEADINGS may be small gripes, but they matter because they contribute to a system of giving out public money that is exclusionary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;To make sure this post is still navigable for people using screen readers, the “unformatted” headings are regular HTML headings with all the distinctive formatting removed. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;This is a real metric used by the Toronto District School Board: &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20190407190902/https://www.tdsb.on.ca/Portals/research/docs/reports/LOI2017.pdf&quot;&gt;tdsb.on.ca/Portals/research/docs/reports/LOI2017.pdf&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><summary type="html">The Pains of Plaintext</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Steps to Writing A Grant: Part II</title><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/writing/2019/03/10/Steps-to-Writing-a-Grant-Part-II.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Steps to Writing A Grant: Part II" /><published>2019-03-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-03-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/writing/2019/03/10/Steps-to-Writing-a-Grant-Part-II</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tallcoleman.me/writing/2019/03/10/Steps-to-Writing-a-Grant-Part-II.html">&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/writing/2019/03/04/Steps-to-Writing-a-Grant-Part-I.html&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt; we went through all the steps a grant writer goes through before they even type their first word. In this post, we’ll go through the rest of the steps, including typing your first word. Let’s assume that you’ve found a funding program, have done your research, and have made the decision to go for it and submit an application. What comes next?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-set-up-your-drafting-document&quot;&gt;4. Set up your drafting document&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like to live life dangerously, you could write your application right in the portal. For people who buy a cute puppy without researching food and vet costs first, or who apply makeup and/or shave while driving, this might be appealing. The rest of us usually open up our word processor of choice and get to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The frustrating part of this process is that most funders don’t provide a word doc version of their portal questions, so most grant writing starts with the dull drudgery of copy-pasting questions into a new document. I suppose some might be afraid of people who would try to apply by submitting the document in spite of any instructions saying “APPLY THROUGH THE PORTAL” in big bold text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Canada-Council-Application-Doc-Red-Text.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of a word document with application questions downloaded from the Canada Council for the Arts website.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Canada Council for the Arts is one of the few funders that will give you a word doc of the application questions. Note that they’ve made the “You must use the portal to apply” warning very big and very red.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The copy-paste process is not always straightforward either. Some portals like to trick you by implementing logic in their application forms. For example, in the Canada Summer Jobs application, there is a part where you pick skills from a list to indicate what your hired student is going to learn. For each skill that you pick in the list, a new text box pops up asking you to provide more details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you made your word doc based on the questions listed on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20190310031443/https://www.canada.ca/en/employment-social-development/services/funding/canada-summer-jobs/apply.html&quot;&gt;Canada Summer Jobs webpage&lt;/a&gt;, there isn’t really any indication that this is how the form works. If you are unlucky, you might write up your whole draft and only realize you have more writing to do at the very last minute when you’re pasting your answers into the form. I’ve seen this in Ontario Arts Council applications as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a precautionary measure, I now try and go through every question in an application form to make sure there aren’t any hidden surprises, clicking every potentially relevant drop-down in case a new text box pops up. Some forms will also check to make sure you’ve answered mandatory questions, so this sometimes requires the extra step of putting in fake answers so you can get through to the next page. While I’m doing these things, I also check how the portal formats text so that I know if it will add in automatic paragraph spacing or if I should double-press the enter key after each paragraph instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of all these foibles, grant writers have to start their work by doing a  bunch of pointless copy-pasting and playing around with the application form to make sure they’ve caught everything. It’s an incredibly frustrating waste of time, and it’s unavoidable because you need to use a proper word processor to do good grant writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if you use Word or Google Docs, here is a list of life-saving features that most grant portals don’t have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Robust spelling and grammar checking&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Track changes and comments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Robust back-ups and autosave&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some kind of version control (ranging in sophistication from saving word files with “Version X” in the file name up to Google Docs’ detailed document history)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find and replace&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Space to write drafting and research notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And most importantly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ability to highlight text that you know is bad so that you can put off fixing it until much later&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-research-the-evaluation-criteria&quot;&gt;5. Research the evaluation criteria&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you have a nice word doc with all the application questions in it. Time to start writing, right? Wrong! Before typing anything, you should take a look at how your application will be scored. I often like to find the evaluation criteria that are relevant to each question and write out some notes about them under every question. It’s a great way to make sure your writing stays focused and to ensure that your efforts are going to result in a high-scoring application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also paste the full criteria at the top of the document in case I need to refer to it quickly. This also helps people who will later edit your work—if the first thing they read is the scoring criteria, they’ll hopefully make their edits while keeping in mind what the funder is looking for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6-start-drafting&quot;&gt;6. Start drafting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s finally time to write! I often start with a bullet point outline and type it all out into prose later, but if you just want to let your keyboard fingers fly, that’s cool too. You’re all set up, so go ahead and start writing out your answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A small tip for grant writers who want to make the world a better place: cite your sources, both internal and external. Most grant applications don’t require citations (in the arts anyway—we’ll talk more about this in a later post). However, if you add footnotes/endnotes that detail where you got a specific fact, especially when you are writing annual operating funding applications, you will be doing a big solid for the person who has your job after you leave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;7-editing&quot;&gt;7. Editing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once at least part of your application is written up, you can start sharing it with your boss, friends, coworkers, etc. to start getting feedback. It might take a while to get to this stage, and I’ve usually found that it takes around 60-70% of the total project time to get to the first full draft. If possible,  try to get there with some time to spare, because the less you rush your editors, the better feedback they’ll give you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I strongly recommend having multiple people edit your draft, if possible. That being said, don’t go too overboard, because going through multiple sets of edits can be quite time-consuming. Ideally you want a small group who collectively tick off all the following boxes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Good writers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Good copy-editors (some people can’t write a good narrative, but they can spot a grammatical error from a mile away)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At least one person who has the authority to sign off on anything you’re promising in your application&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At least one person who knows your organization/field very well&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, you should also have at least one person who isn’t an expert on your organization/field and has the same level of background knowledge as the people who will end up reviewing your application. This person will help make sure you haven’t included any jargon or skipped explaining something because you’ve incorrectly assumed it’s “obvious”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you’ve finished incorporating the edits from all your reviewers, make sure to save time to go through the whole application one more time in case there are any errors that were missed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;8-submit&quot;&gt;8. Submit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve finished the editing process and you’ve done a last check of the whole thing, it’s time to log in to the portal and upload. &lt;em&gt;Ideally&lt;/em&gt; you should submit your application with some time to spare in case you run into any issues along the way. Some portals have also been known to crash under the load of everyone submitting their applications at the last minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve pasted all your answers into the portal, uploaded your supporting material, and double-checked that all the questions in the portal are answered, take a deep breath and click “submit”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re done!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we’ve gone through the grant writing steps, we can take a deeper look at where most portals fall short. In the next post, I’m going to write boldly about formatting and underline what some of the common limitations are. It’s going to be colourful!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><summary type="html">In the last post we went through all the steps a grant writer goes through before they even type their first word. In this post, we’ll go through the rest of the steps, including typing your first word. Let’s assume that you’ve found a funding program, have done your research, and have made the decision to go for it and submit an application. What comes next?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Steps to Writing a Grant: Part I</title><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/writing/2019/03/04/Steps-to-Writing-a-Grant-Part-I.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Steps to Writing a Grant: Part I" /><published>2019-03-04T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-03-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/writing/2019/03/04/Steps-to-Writing-a-Grant-Part-I</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tallcoleman.me/writing/2019/03/04/Steps-to-Writing-a-Grant-Part-I.html">&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/writing/2019/02/24/Grant-Portal-Limitations-Intro.html&quot;&gt;intro post&lt;/a&gt; I argued that grant portals are rarely designed to make life easier for the grant writer. But what if they were? There is a whole list of things that a grant writer has to do before they press “submit”, and grant portals can help or hinder that work at various points along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to describe the steps that most grant writing projects go through. Along the way, we can imagine how portals &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; make grant writing easier, and then we’ll take a look at the reality of how they mostly don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-discover-the-funding-program&quot;&gt;1. Discover the funding program&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To state the obvious, you have to know a funding program exists in order to apply for it. Funders usually advertise and describe their funding programs on their website. However, this is a difficult task, because they have to communicate lots of different things to different people. Eligibility, for example, varies by artistic discipline and organization type, but most grant writers want to be able to quickly drill down to the programs that are meant for them or their organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most organizations try to help with this by designing their websites with detailed menus to help you find relevant programs. See, for example, the website menu for the Ontario Arts Council (OAC):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ontario-Arts-Council-Website-Menu-Taken-2019-02-23.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of the arts.on.ca website showing the navigation menu for their grant programs. It has four columns, including one for different types of activities, one for artists from different disciplines, one for artists from different priority groups, such as Artists of Colour, and a final column for general information about grants.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or the less helpful website menu for the Canada Council for the Arts (CCA):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Canada-Council-Website-Menu-Taken-2019-02-23.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of the canadacouncil.ca website showing the navigation menu for their grant programs. The grant menu includes links to each of their funding programs which only have somewhat-descriptive names, such as Engage and Sustain. There is also a second column for general information about grants.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grant portals should have an advantage here—to use a grant portal, you usually have to create a detailed profile for you or your organization. This means that the portal should already know who you are and what programs you are eligible for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some organizations, such as the Canada Council for the Arts, do take advantage of this and provide a customized list of available funding programs within their portals. Others, such as the Ontario Arts Council seemingly do not. (For example, in my OAC account registered to an incorporated non-profit, it lists the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arts.on.ca/grants/discipline/visual-arts/exhibition-assistance&quot;&gt;Exhibition Assistance&lt;/a&gt; program which explicitly does not fund non-profit corporations.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given how much a portal already knows about you, there is a lot of potential here, but it is mostly untapped. For example, most portals do not send you emails when deadlines for eligible programs are coming up, meaning that even if a portal did the work of showing you eligible programs, you would still have to log in to see it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a lot of ways, it makes sense that the potential here is ignored. Most grant writers only visit the portal when they are going to write a grant, so unless you can send customized emails, the effort would probably go un-seen. Funders might also assume that most people who have gone to the trouble of setting up a portal account are probably familiar enough with their funding programs to know which ones they are eligible for. We’ll come back to that assumption later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-find-out-more-about-the-program&quot;&gt;2. Find out more about the program&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you’ve found a program you can apply to. Is it worth it to write an application? Part of being a good grant writer is being strategic about where you commit your time and the time of other people in your organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grant writers are fundraisers, and over the course of a year they have to try to pick applications that strike a balance between getting the most funding possible and getting dependable funding that will help them meet their revenue budget. If there’s only a 10% chance an application will be successful or if it only offers a small amount of money for the time invested, it’s probably not worth the effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More importantly, grants are dangerous, because they almost always come with obligations. Picking the wrong grant could make an organization’s finances worse–for example, if a grant only funds 50% of a project’s costs, and taking it forces you to spend the other 50% from money your organization doesn’t have. The wrong grant could also contribute to mission creep, forcing your organization to work on projects that are outside its core purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To weigh all these factors, a grant writer needs to be able to answer a lot of questions about a funding program. What kinds of projects and expenses will it fund? How much funding will it offer in total? What are the obligations and work that would come with taking the funding? How long will it take to put together a good application?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That last question can be quite tricky to answer. I’ve seen some portals where you can’t see what the application form looks like until quite close to the deadline. This often happens because you’re waiting for your registration to be approved, or because the funder only makes one type of application “live” in the portal at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually funders are nice and will &lt;del&gt;hide&lt;/del&gt; provide a PDF of the application questions on their website, though these don’t always give you all the little details, like whether you can put descriptions on supporting material, or if you just have to rely on writing meaningful file names. For some reason, information like “estimated writing time”, “total question word count”, and “list of appendices required” is usually not summarized for you, so you have to make your own summary to figure out how much work it’s going to take to apply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-decide-to-apply&quot;&gt;3. Decide to apply&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once all your questions about the funding program have been answered, the grant writer can decide whether an application is worth their time. More importantly, anyone else who would be affected needs to decide that it’s worth their time too. This needs to be a &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; decision—the kind where everyone is committed to whatever is promised in the application, including the worst and best possible scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has nothing to do with grant portals. It’s just a super important part of grant writing and I wanted to mention it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a lot of work already, and we haven’t even gotten to the &lt;em&gt;writing&lt;/em&gt; part. In fact, if I were going to hire a grantwriter, I wouldn’t ask them for a writing sample from an application. I would ask them to write a one-page briefing for program staff about a funding program, the kind of document you would write up for step #3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The writing part does come next though, and I’ll go through that… in the next post.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><summary type="html">In the intro post I argued that grant portals are rarely designed to make life easier for the grant writer. But what if they were? There is a whole list of things that a grant writer has to do before they press “submit”, and grant portals can help or hinder that work at various points along the way.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Grant Portal Limitations - Intro</title><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/writing/2019/02/24/Grant-Portal-Limitations-Intro.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Grant Portal Limitations - Intro" /><published>2019-02-24T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-02-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/writing/2019/02/24/Grant-Portal-Limitations-Intro</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tallcoleman.me/writing/2019/02/24/Grant-Portal-Limitations-Intro.html">&lt;p&gt;I strongly believe that if you have a blog, the best way to use it is to write about something incredibly specific, with the hope of enlightening or enriching the lives of the other nine people who care about that thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence my topic today: in the last several years, many government ministries and agencies who give out grants (I’ll call them “funders”) have transitioned away from using forms made in Microsoft Word or Adobe Acrobat and have started using web portals. As a grant writer, I spend a lot of time using these portals. And they generally suck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quality of most mass-market web applications creates a false sense of security. Google Docs is so consistent with saving your work that it takes effort to actually lose something you’ve written. Products like Dropbox have whole teams of user experience designers who work to ensure that their service is intuitive and easy to use. Grant Portals, on the other hand, are usually implemented by government agencies who do not have a lot of people and money to throw towards IT. If a grant portal is reasonably functional and reliable, it’s already doing well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Microsoft-Word-Canada-Council-Application.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Microsoft Word. The document being worked on is an application form for travel funding from the Canada Council for the Arts.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Microsoft Word: still the worst way to write a grant, except for all the others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the biggest problem for a grant writer is that most grant portals are not designed with them in mind. In a lot of ways, the most user-friendly grant application software is still Microsoft Word. No, grant portals are there because they are meant to make life easier for the &lt;em&gt;funder&lt;/em&gt;. It’s a lot easier to manage and sort through hundreds (or maybe even thousands) of applications if they’re in a database. It’s the same reason some employers have job application sites where you have to re-write out your resume into their online form. It makes their work simpler, at your expense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At surface level, I am going to gripe about all the things I find frustrating about grant portals. I have so many gripes, in fact, that I’ve decided to make this a multi-part series. Perhaps it will be enjoyable, cathartic reading if you too write grants. If you work for a funder, or design grant portal software, perhaps it will be useful user feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I have a loftier goal in mind. Even if you don’t write grant applications or give out grants, they are an incredibly important part of how our civil society functions. Through grant applications, government gives resources to all manner of people, companies, and non-profits. Grant applications are also one of the most common ways that government communicates with the people it gives money to and holds them accountable. The design of grant portals says a lot about who government gives priority to (and who it doesn’t) and what relationship they have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grant portals are also an interesting study in how technology shapes the way we communicate. The tools we use to communicate often change what we say, how we say it, and how it is received. I have lots of interesting examples of that to share with you later in this series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But before that… on with the gripes!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><summary type="html">I strongly believe that if you have a blog, the best way to use it is to write about something incredibly specific, with the hope of enlightening or enriching the lives of the other nine people who care about that thing.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Toronto Beltline Trail via BikeShare</title><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/cycling/2018/08/26/toronto-beltline-trail-via-bikeshare.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Toronto Beltline Trail via BikeShare" /><published>2018-08-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-08-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/cycling/2018/08/26/toronto-beltline-trail-via-bikeshare</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tallcoleman.me/cycling/2018/08/26/toronto-beltline-trail-via-bikeshare.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/Ronald-Ave-Station.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Image of Bikeshare Bike next to sign titled Ronald Avenue Station&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ronald Ave E - The Turning Around Point&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-stats&quot;&gt;Key Stats:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 1h 45m - 2h, depending on how often you take breaks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distance:&lt;/strong&gt; about 26km&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hills:&lt;/strong&gt; Moderate, unless you take Milkman’s Lane&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On August 15, Bike Share Toronto &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thestar.com/news/city_hall/2018/08/15/torontos-bike-share-system-expanding-again.html&quot;&gt;announced that they were expanding their network again&lt;/a&gt;, with 75 new stations across Toronto. One of the interesting new additions was a station on the Kay Gardiner Beltline Trail, which is a great trail for an afternoon bike ride. Naturally, I thought I would try it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-couple-important-caveats&quot;&gt;A couple important caveats:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Keep an eye on the time - especially for the first part of the journey. I use a timer set to 25 minutes to make sure I don’t go over 30 minutes for each part of the trip.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Don’t do this route with a BikeShare bike if it’s raining or has recently rained. They have pretty smooth tires and you don’t want to get the bike dirty. Remember–someone else will be using it later.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you grab a bike, make sure it has a working bell, well-functioning brakes, and one of the new seats. (They don’t have a suspension, so the new seat thing is important.)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-i---castle-frank-to-oriole-park&quot;&gt;Part I - Castle Frank to Oriole Park&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/Map-Part-I.png&quot; alt=&quot;Map of route from Castle Frank Station to Oriole Park&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the longest part of the trip, and also the most uphill. If you want to avoid the treacherous ride down Milkman’s Lane, there’s a ramp down from Crescent Road and Mount Pleasant Road that takes you north. You can go down there and enter the ravine at Mount Pleasant and Roxborough. This part takes 22 minutes, or 27 if you avoid Milkman’s Lane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Optional Diversion (especially on the way back) - if you want to stop at the Don Valley Brickworks, you can exit through Chorley Park and there’s a rack right at the top of the hill on Douglas Drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tips&quot;&gt;Tips:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once the trail stops being side-by-side with Bayview Ave, there’s a big fork. Take the larger trail on the left (the other one goes to the Brickworks parking lot)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you don’t want to go through the cemetery, or can’t because of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mountpleasantgroup.com/Locations/Cemeteries/Mount-Pleasant.aspx&quot;&gt;gate hours&lt;/a&gt;, you can go west on Moore Ave and North on Mount Pleasant Rd. Once you hit Merton St, you can go back south slightly and catch the trail again.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The rack in Oriole Park is slightly off the trail, but you should be able to see it when you cross the road.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/Davisville-Yard.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of the Davisville TTC Yard taken from the trail bridge&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Once you see the Davisville TTC Yard, you’re almost at Oriole Park.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-ii---oriole-park-to-memorial-park&quot;&gt;Part II - Oriole Park to Memorial Park&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/Map-Part-II.png&quot; alt=&quot;Map of route from Oriole Park to Memorial Park&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the shortest part of the trip. It’s slightly uphill, but pretty easy. It should take just under 10 minutes. The rack at Memorial Park is right on the trail, so it’s hard to miss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are park washrooms on the outside of the Arena, so if you need a bathroom break, this is a good spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/Memorial-Park-Dock.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Image of the Bike Rack at Memorial Park&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The rack by Memorial Park. Currently the northern-most rack in the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-iii---memorial-park-to-the-york-beltline-trail-and-back-again&quot;&gt;Part III - Memorial Park to the York Beltline Trail and Back Again&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/Map-Part-III.png&quot; alt=&quot;Map of route from Memorial Park westward&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no other BikeShare racks after this, so &lt;strong&gt;make sure you set a timer to tell you when to turn around!&lt;/strong&gt; I set mine for a safe 13 minutes, but you could do 14.5 minutes if you like to live life on the edge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a small section where this trail hops up to Elm Ridge Dr/Roselawn Ave to get over the Allen Expressway, but it’s short and has good signs to get you back to the trail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I managed to get to Ronald Ave E before turning around. I think if you really cut it close and went fast you could get to the end of the trail… but that’s an experiment for another day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/York-Beltline-View.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of the York Beltline Trail&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Enjoy the paved trail while it lasts! If you have time, check out all the historical signs–they’re great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-iv---memorial-park-to-oriole-park&quot;&gt;Part IV - Memorial Park to Oriole Park&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the same as part II, but going back. Enjoy going slightly downhill!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to take a different route, you can head leave the trail south at Russell Hill Rd and head downtown. There are racks all over north downtown within a 30 minute ride (Spadina Station is just under 20 minutes, for example.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/Kay-Gardiner-Beltline-View.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of the Kay Gardiner Beltline Trail Park&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The shade on this part of the trail is fantastic on a hot day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-v---oriole-park-to-castle-frank-station&quot;&gt;Part V - Oriole Park to Castle Frank Station&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avoid going up Milkman’s Lane unless you want to be completely exhausted, especially since the bikes only have one low gear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t make the same mistake that I did and go into the Cemetery before Mount Pleasant and then take the trail from the West side. That trail has stairs, and the BikeShare bikes are &lt;em&gt;heavy&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the whole Milkman’s Lane thing, this part is mostly downhill. Keep an eye on the time if you’re tired. If you’re running out of time getting out of the ravine, there’s a rack in Rosedale Park a couple minutes to the north.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy the ride!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ronald-Ave-Station.JPG" /></entry><entry><title type="html">TIFF Blog Post: 2167 Indigenous VR</title><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/tiff/2017/11/26/2167-Indigenous-VR.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TIFF Blog Post: 2167 Indigenous VR" /><published>2017-11-26T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-11-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/tiff/2017/11/26/2167-Indigenous-VR</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tallcoleman.me/tiff/2017/11/26/2167-Indigenous-VR.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been spending a lot of time recently writing internal-facing reports, so it’s nice to be able to write something to share with the world. TIFF has a publication of sorts called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tiff.net/action-report/&quot;&gt;ACTION report&lt;/a&gt;, which is an excellent showcase of how our funding makes a difference in the moving image arts&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- footnote --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tiff.net/action-report/fall2017/indigenous-virtual-futures/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/TIFF-Action-Report-Fall-2017.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The ACTION report page&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was lucky enough to be able to write about &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tiff.net/events/2167/&quot;&gt;2167&lt;/a&gt;, an indigneous VR exhibit that’s been housed at TIFF for about the past half-year (and travelled around–it’s been to Yellowknife!). There are “VR Experiences” on show, and I spoke to the creator/director of one titled &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tiff.net/exhibitions/the-hunt/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Hunt&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Her name is Danis Goulet, and she is a Cree/Métis filmmaker, TIFF Short Cuts programmer, and an absolute pleasure to interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To see all of the interesting things that she said about VR, Sci-Fi, and Indigenous filmmaking, go and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tiff.net/action-report/fall2017/indigenous-virtual-futures/&quot;&gt;read the interview&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;The Review&lt;/em&gt;, another great TIFF publication also did an excellent interview with Danis and some of the other VR filmmakers that you can &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tiff.net/the-review/indigenous-existence-is-resistance/&quot;&gt;read here&lt;/a&gt;. It talks a lot more about the actual filmmaking and the art behind VR, so it’s a fantastic read if you’re into those elements of the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for this blog, there’s one tidbit I didn’t have space for in the piece that I wanted to share:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In her interview, Danis talks about getting started as a casting director and how her experiences during casting motivated her to make her own films. While I was doing my pre-interview research, I found out that one of the gigs she had was doing the Canadian casting for &lt;em&gt;Mean Girls&lt;/em&gt;, which meant casting all the extras and many of the smaller roles. Apparently the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9KY8WU0oa3I&quot;&gt;Kevin Gnapoor rap&lt;/a&gt; is burned into her brain now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That being said, after I asked her all my &lt;em&gt;Mean Girls&lt;/em&gt; questions, I did do the real interview with her, which you can read on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tiff.net/action-report/fall2017/indigenous-virtual-futures/&quot;&gt;TIFF Website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It’s annoying how tech can make things more difficult. 10 or 20 years ago, “film” might be an OK descriptor of TIFF’s wheelhouse. However, these days an artist might make an augmented reality experience (think Pokemon GO, but artsy), and that would be something TIFF would care about. Would you call that a “film”? Probably not. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><summary type="html">I’ve been spending a lot of time recently writing internal-facing reports, so it’s nice to be able to write something to share with the world. TIFF has a publication of sorts called ACTION report, which is an excellent showcase of how our funding makes a difference in the moving image arts1. It’s annoying how tech can make things more difficult. 10 or 20 years ago, “film” might be an OK descriptor of TIFF’s wheelhouse. However, these days an artist might make an augmented reality experience (think Pokemon GO, but artsy), and that would be something TIFF would care about. Would you call that a “film”? Probably not. &amp;#8617;</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/TIFF-Action-Report-Fall-2017.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Mac Setup</title><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/technology/2017/08/07/mac-setup.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mac Setup" /><published>2017-08-07T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/technology/2017/08/07/mac-setup</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tallcoleman.me/technology/2017/08/07/mac-setup.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Updated: April 28, 2018&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought a new computer (Mac) recently and wanted to make a list of all the tools I find useful in case other people find them useful too. I used to use a Windows computer, so a lot of these are things I used on Windows too, or equivalents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here it is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;new-airdrop-location-selection&quot;&gt;New: AirDrop Location Selection&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find that AirDrop is often the fastest way to transfer individual files over to my computer. However, if you want to choose where the files end up, you’ll have to use an Automator Script. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.idownloadblog.com/2017/03/03/change-airdrop-destination-folder-mac/&quot;&gt;This site&lt;/a&gt; has a good description of how to set that up (ignore the phony notification request). I would suggest one twist: for the “Move Finder Items” action, click “Options” and check “Show this action when the workflow runs”. That way, you can select a specific folder every time you receive an AirDrop file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;window-management&quot;&gt;Window Management&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is something Windows does better natively than Mac (in my opinion). However, as long as you’re comfortable with using your keyboard, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spectacleapp.com/&quot;&gt;Spectacle&lt;/a&gt; does a good job of bringing OSX up to par.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One small note: if you use the keyboard shortcut for footnotes in Word (⌘ + ⌥ + F), you might want to remap the “fullscreen” shortcut in Spectacle’s preferences so they don’t conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;spotify-notifications&quot;&gt;Spotify Notifications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why isn’t this a thing that the Spotify app already does!? Anyway, in the meantime, you can see the title of each new song with &lt;a href=&quot;https://spotify-notifications.citruspi.io/&quot;&gt;this app&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;flux&quot;&gt;Flux&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Screw night shift. &lt;a href=&quot;https://justgetflux.com/&quot;&gt;Flux&lt;/a&gt; is &lt;a href=&quot;https://9to5mac.com/2017/03/28/flux-developer-says-apples-new-competitive-macos-night-shift-feature-falls-short/&quot;&gt;better&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;battery-lifetime&quot;&gt;Battery Lifetime&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the newer versions of OSX &lt;a href=&quot;https://9to5mac.com/2016/12/13/why-apple-is-removing-time-remaining-battery-life-estimates-macbook-pro/&quot;&gt;don’t have the battery time remaining indicator&lt;/a&gt;, I think this &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/app/battery-diag/id836505650?mt=12&quot;&gt;Battery Monitor App (App Store Link)&lt;/a&gt; is pretty useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;trackball-scrolling&quot;&gt;Trackball scrolling&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a Logitech M570 Trackball Mouse and I like to use the trackball to scroll. It’s amazing and I don’t know why the Logitech software doesn’t allow you to do this already since it’s 1000% better than using the scroll wheel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got the trackball scrolling working using a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hammerspoon.org/&quot;&gt;hammerspoon&lt;/a&gt; script from this thread:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/tekezo/Karabiner/issues/814&quot;&gt;https://github.com/tekezo/Karabiner/issues/814&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has options for keybinding to start the scroll mode, or you can press a button on the mouse, which is what I do. I only changed two parts of the mouse button script:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Line 4:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;local &lt;/span&gt;scrollmult &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The negative number makes it non-natural scrolling. I prefer the natural scrolling, but this helps me switch back to Windows, which I have to use at work. I also tamped down the speed a bit, from 4 to 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Line 13:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;local &lt;/span&gt;shouldScroll &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; 2 &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; pressedMouseButton
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changed the button to OSX button 3 (middle button). I also remapped the fifth button (“forward”) in Logitech Options to be the middle button, which is how I had it set up in Windows. I find it easier to click than the mouse wheel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than that, I kept the rest of the script the same. Works better than the Windows AHK script I was using.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;typewriter-scrolling-in-ms-word&quot;&gt;Typewriter Scrolling in MS Word&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Windows, I had an AHK script that kept the active line in Microsoft Word in the middle of the screen, instead of wandering to the bottom (a.k.a. “typewriter scrolling”). Since I occasionally do transcription, this is really useful, since it improves the ergonomics of typing for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t find a script that did the same thing using Hammerspoon, so I wrote one using AppleScript. It’s not elegant… but it works!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Link: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/tallcoleman/MacWordTypewriterScroll&quot;&gt;View on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><summary type="html">Updated: April 28, 2018</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ben-By-High-Park-Pond-Birdwatching.JPG" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Rouge Park Bioblitz 2017</title><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/ecology/2017/06/28/Rouge-Park-Bioblitz-2017.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rouge Park Bioblitz 2017" /><published>2017-06-28T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-06-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/ecology/2017/06/28/Rouge-Park-Bioblitz-2017</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tallcoleman.me/ecology/2017/06/28/Rouge-Park-Bioblitz-2017.html">&lt;p&gt;Last weekend I helped out at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://bioblitzcanada.ca/events_flagships-toronto.aspx&quot;&gt;Rouge Park Canada Bioblitz&lt;/a&gt;. It was a boatload of fun, all the groups found a lot of species despite the weather, and I saw lots of &lt;em&gt;cool birds&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/Bioblitz-2017-Morning-Sky.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of Morning Sky&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My volunteer shift started at 5:30 a.m. so I was up early. Most of the people that shared the bus ride with me to Scarborough were clearly coming back from clubbing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/Bioblitz-2017-River-Landscape-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of River Landscape from Vista Trail&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I think this was taken from the Orchard Trail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/Bioblitz-2017-Cedar-Waxwing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of Cedar Waxwing&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Blurry photo of a Cedar Waxwing taken through binoculars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/Bioblitz-2017-Blurry-Turtle.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of Snapping Turtle&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Blurry photo of a snapping turtle sunning itself on a rock, also taken through binoculars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/Bioblitz-2017-River-Landscape.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of River Landscape&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Photo of River Landscape taken from the East end of Zoo Road. About an hour later it poured down and our gazebo tent almost flew away!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not pictured: Baltimore Oriole, and Indigo Bunting, both of which were too quick for my binocular-iPhone camera “set-up”.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><category term="Rouge Park" /><category term="Canada Bioblitz" /><summary type="html">Last weekend I helped out at the Rouge Park Canada Bioblitz. It was a boatload of fun, all the groups found a lot of species despite the weather, and I saw lots of cool birds.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Bioblitz-2017-Morning-Sky.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Bloor-Yorkville BIA Blog Posts - 2017</title><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/bloor-yorkville%20bia/2017/05/20/Bloor-Yorkville-BIA-Blog-Posts-2017.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bloor-Yorkville BIA Blog Posts - 2017" /><published>2017-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/bloor-yorkville%20bia/2017/05/20/Bloor-Yorkville-BIA-Blog-Posts-2017</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tallcoleman.me/bloor-yorkville%20bia/2017/05/20/Bloor-Yorkville-BIA-Blog-Posts-2017.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a list of Blog posts I wrote for the Bloor-Yorkville Business Improvement Area in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-best-fountain-pens-toronto-has-to-offer-are-at-laywines&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bloor-yorkville.com/best-fountain-pens-toronto-laywines/&quot;&gt;The Best Fountain Pens Toronto Has to Offer are at Laywine’s&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/Ajoto-Pens-on-Display-Board-1024x428.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of Ajoto Pens on a Wooden Display Board&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love the Instagram photo of the elephant pencil holder in this article. I love cute things and I love the rock in the Village of Yorkville Park, and it has both!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also wish I had taken a picture of the back room of the store, because it looks like Ollivander’s wand shop, except all the long boxes have pens in them. Such a cool place to visit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toronto-bees-find-a-new-home-at-the-colonnade&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bloor-yorkville.com/toronto-bees-find-new-home-colonnade/&quot;&gt;Toronto Bees Find a New Home at the Colonnade&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/2017-06-09-bee-hat-photo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of Ben Coleman wearing a beekeeper mesh hat&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was such a fun post to write! Kelly and I got to go up to the roof, chill with the bees, and wear cool hats (see above). What more can you ask for?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you find the business behind bees interesting, I would also highly recommend this &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.econtalk.org/archives/2013/12/wally_thurman_o.html&quot;&gt;episode of the EconTalk podcast&lt;/a&gt;, which is also a good look at how the Varroa mite has impacted the commercial practices of beekeepers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;paul-pecorella-hair-salon--spa-celebrates-their-35-year-anniversary-in-bloor-yorkville&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bloor-yorkville.com/paul-pecorella-hair-salon-spa-35-year-anniversary/&quot;&gt;Paul Pecorella Hair Salon &amp;amp; Spa Celebrates Their 35-Year Anniversary in Bloor-Yorkville&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/Photo-of-Paul-2017-1-1024x576.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of Paul&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love meeting people who worked in Yorkville when it was a hippie hangout. I got to do this last year with &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;the Scollard Deli&lt;/a&gt;, and this year it was a real treat to meet everyone in the Pecorella family. They’ve been in Yorkville for 35 years, and they have lots of stories to tell about it. My half-hour interview with them felt like I had joined in a family hangout to reminisce. It was a lovely time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-betty-hemmings-yorkville-guide-to-luxury-leather-goods&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bloor-yorkville.com/betty-hemmings-guide-luxury-leather-goods/&quot;&gt;The Betty Hemmings Yorkville Guide to Luxury Leather Goods&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/Collage-of-Magnifying-Glass-Close-ups-1024x768.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image of two close-ups&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is among the longest articles I’ve written. Even still, there were more sections I could have included: a whole intro to what to look for in wallets, more details about some of the luggage, and so on. It was also my first attempt at including some video, with a short, motion-stabilized spur-of-the-moment cellphone capture of a fantastic moment in salesmanship. I think the guy who sold my parents their vacuum cleaner stood on it first too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal was to try and take a more practical angle for this piece. Part of my thinking was making the article fun and easy to write, and part of it was becuase the usual profile-type piece that we often do in the Bloor-Yorkville Blog would be redundant given the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thehogtownrake.com/?p=2587&quot;&gt;well-written profile done last year by fashion blogger Pedro Mendes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;unique-in-yorkville-the-sassoon-salon&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bloor-yorkville.com/unique-in-yorkville-sassoon-academy/&quot;&gt;Unique in Yorkville: The Sassoon Salon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To write this story, I interviewed one of the academy’s instructors, Wesley Hanlon. I love interviewing people—my goal is to try to find the question that breaks people out from the mould of what they planned to say and organically reveals their own passion and personality. I had a lot of fun talking with Wesley and learning about the Academy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;its-bird-migration-season-what-you-can-do-to-care-for-and-prevent-injured-birds&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bloor-yorkville.com/bird-migration-prevent-injured-birds/&quot;&gt;It’s Bird Migration Season! What You Can Do To Care For and Prevent Injured Birds&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/FLAP Annual Photo 2016.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;FLAP Canada’s 2016 Bird Layout&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love birds, as you can probably tell by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/ecology/saskatchewan-birds/&quot;&gt;other pages on this website dedicated to writing about them&lt;/a&gt;. This article is mostly a compilation of fantastic tips from FLAP Canada and some information I pulled together about development proposals in the Bloor-Yorkville area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also read the post here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://tallcoleman.me/bloor-yorkville%20bia/2017/05/04/its-bird-migration-season-prevent-injured-birds.html&quot;&gt;https://tallcoleman.me/bloor-yorkville%20bia/2017/05/04/its-bird-migration-season-prevent-injured-birds.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><category term="Portfolio" /><category term="Bloor-Yorkville 2017" /><summary type="html">This is a list of Blog posts I wrote for the Bloor-Yorkville Business Improvement Area in 2017.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/Ajoto-Pens-on-Display-Board-1024x428.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">It’s Bird Migration Season! What You Can Do To Care For and Prevent Injured Birds</title><link href="https://tallcoleman.me/bloor-yorkville%20bia/2017/05/04/its-bird-migration-season-prevent-injured-birds.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="It’s Bird Migration Season! What You Can Do To Care For and Prevent Injured Birds" /><published>2017-05-04T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-05-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://tallcoleman.me/bloor-yorkville%20bia/2017/05/04/its-bird-migration-season-prevent-injured-birds</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tallcoleman.me/bloor-yorkville%20bia/2017/05/04/its-bird-migration-season-prevent-injured-birds.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This article originally appeared on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://bloor-yorkville.com/blog/&quot;&gt;Bloor-Yorkville BIA Blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/FLAP Annual Photo 2016.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;FLAP Canada’s 2016 Bird Layout&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;FLAP Canada’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flap.org/museum-program.php&quot;&gt;2016 Bird Layout&lt;/a&gt;. Image courtesy of FLAP Canada&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;birds-in-the-city-a-rough-and-tumble-life&quot;&gt;Birds in the City: A Rough-and-Tumble Life&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toronto is a migratory bird hotspot: we are visited by birds flying
north in the spring (and south again in the fall) from both the Atlantic
and Mississippi flyways. Like many human Torontonians, migrating birds
love our high-quality lakefront properties, including the lush Toronto
Island and bustling Tommy Thompson Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, migratory birds get confused, injured, and killed by two things
found in abundance in downtown Toronto—artificial light and glass.
Problems with birds and glass are well-known: unlike us, birds don’t
understand that what they see in a window is a reflection. As a result,
thousands fly into city windows thinking that a reflected surface is a
restful tree or open sky. At high speed, the collision is usually fatal.
The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www1.toronto.ca/wps/portal/contentonly?vgnextoid=c5f20621f3161410VgnVCM10000071d60f89RCRD&amp;amp;vgnextchannel=f6ce5d0a02148410VgnVCM10000071d60f89RCRD&quot;&gt;City of Toronto’s best practices guide for bird-friendly
glass&lt;/a&gt;
cites a study that estimated that in Canada, about 25 million birds die
each year from colliding with windows. It is a huge and pressing
problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Less well-known are the problems caused by artificial light. Many
migratory birds fly at night when it is cooler and safer from predators,
using the moon and stars for navigation. Light coming from our cities
confuses and attracts these birds, drawing them into the city where they
are at risk of being harmed by busy roads or reflective surfaces. This
phenomena is called “Fatal Light Attraction.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One group trying to solve these problems is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flap.org/index.php&quot;&gt;Fatal Light Awareness
Program (FLAP) Canada&lt;/a&gt;. This
Toronto-based group and its volunteers run an emergency bird rescue
program out of Metro Hall at 55 John Street. They also educate
Torontonians about the dangers faced by migratory birds and advocate for
policies and architecture that helps to protect them. While rescuing
birds, they also collect data about when and where different species of
birds are killed to emphasize the importance of taking action. There are
20 types of birds listed under the &lt;em&gt;Species at Risk Act&lt;/em&gt; on their record
of species that have been found dead after colliding with glass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;city-planning-to-reduce-bird-deaths&quot;&gt;City Planning to Reduce Bird Deaths&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www1.toronto.ca/wps/portal/contentonly?vgnextoid=f85552cc66061410VgnVCM10000071d60f89RCRD&quot;&gt;Toronto Green
Standard&lt;/a&gt;
is a checklist for developers that helps to create more sustainable
buildings. It has two tiers, and a variety of measures that can be
implemented, ranging from improvements to energy efficiency to
protections for migrating birds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first tier is mandatory for new developments. Among many other
requirements, it specifies that new buildings must treat at least 85% of
all exterior glass within the first 12 meters of a building in a way
that prevents confusing reflections. This can be done using materials
that are low-reflecting and opaque, or visual markers such as
“fritting”—the application of ceramic dots to the glass during
manufacturing. You can see these methods being used in planned
developments in Bloor-Yorkville:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/75 Yorkville Plan-COLLAGE-annotated.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Development proposals in Bloor-Yorkville with bird-friendly
glass&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Development proposals in Bloor-Yorkville with bird-friendly
glass marked in green: Top – 75 Yorkville Ave, Bottom – 848 Yonge
Street.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second tier of the Toronto Green Standard is optional, but the City
offers financial incentives for developers who meet this higher level of
sustainability. Bird protection measures in this tier include a
requirement to point architectural illumination downwards and turn it
off completely between 11 p.m. and 6 a.m. during the migratory season so
that the light does not confuse migrating birds. There is also an option
to increase the coverage of bird-friendly glass to 95% of the building’s
first 12 meters. So far, tier two buildings are rare (the City’s website
lists about 10), but hopefully one will be planned for Bloor-Yorkville
soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-you-can-help&quot;&gt;How You Can Help:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Turn off unnecessary lights at home and at work – especially when
you are leaving work at the end of the day. (A timer plug extension
might help).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the outside of your building, place visual markers on
window-glass (5 cm apart) or hang ribbons or strings in front of
windows (10 cm apart). (See &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flap.org/commercial_new.php&quot;&gt;FLAP’s tips on
window-markers&lt;/a&gt;—the small
details do matter.) It’s OK to be a little creative with window
markers: the Pan-Am aquatic center has small graphics of athletes
instead of dots and it complements their overall branding.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Speak with your property manager about using lights that turn off
automatically and installing special film outside of windows to
reduce reflection.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Place bird feeders close to your windows (less than half a metre
away) so birds leaving the feeder cannot hit your window at high
speed if they go in the wrong direction.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flap.org/volunteer.php&quot;&gt;Volunteer with FLAP Canada&lt;/a&gt; to
help with bird rescue and research.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Take action tips from City of Toronto Communications.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;strategies-that-dont-work&quot;&gt;Strategies That &lt;em&gt;Don’t&lt;/em&gt; Work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Predator Bird Decals: Many people think that large stickers of
birds-of-prey will scare off smaller birds from windows, but
experiments have shown that it doesn’t work! Smaller markers that
are close together, such as dot stickers 5 cm apart, work much
better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Images/IMG_1648-COLLAGE.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Picture of Two types of decals: small dot markers about 5cm
apart and bird-of-prey decals, which are ineffective&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Two types of decals: Left – small dot markers about 5cm
apart. Right – bird-of-prey decals, which are ineffective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Angled Glass: The updated City of Toronto Bird-Friendly Guidelines
has removed angled glass as a strategy due to a lack of supporting
scientific evidence. Birds fly in all directions, so it makes sense
that this would not reduce the impact of collisions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Interior Blinds: Markers never disappear, and they sit on the
outside of a window. Blinds are designed to be taken up and down,
and sit behind the glass. To be effective, window applications or
coverings need to be on the outside so they block or obscure any
confusing reflections.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tinted Glass: Like angled glass, there isn’t enough evidence to say
that tinted glass helps reduce collisions. There are anti-reflective
applications listed in the Toronto Green Standard that will work.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Interior Screens: Like blinds, these sit behind the glass. There is
a lack of evidence that putting interior screens behind windows will
help prevent birds from colliding with the glass.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Strategies to avoid taken from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www1.toronto.ca/wps/portal/contentonly?vgnextoid=c5f20621f3161410VgnVCM10000071d60f89RCRD&amp;amp;vgnextchannel=f6ce5d0a02148410VgnVCM10000071d60f89RCRD&quot;&gt;Bird-Friendly Development Guideline:
Best Practices – Glass
(2016)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-to-do-if-you-find-a-dead-or-injured-bird&quot;&gt;What to Do If You Find a Dead or Injured Bird:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you see a bird knocked out from colliding with a window or if you
find an injured bird on the ground, this is what you should do:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Try to handle the bird as little as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gently place the bird in an un-waxed paper bag or cardboard box.
Keep the container closed (you can poke some air holes in the top).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do not&lt;/strong&gt; give the bird water or food.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Roll clean tissues or paper towel into a donut shape and put it in
the container as a perch for the bird to sit upright.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Temporarily keep the bag or box in a safe, quiet location.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you hear the bird fluttering inside the container within an hour,
take it to a park, ravine, or any other area away from hazards, such
as windows, buildings, or busy roads, and slowly open the container
to let the bird fly out.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Contact the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.torontowildlifecentre.com/&quot;&gt;Toronto Wildlife
Centre&lt;/a&gt; for more
instructions if the bird has not shown any activity after one hour.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Recuperation tips from FLAP Canada. See &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flap.org/faqs.php&quot;&gt;their website for more
Frequently Asked Questions&lt;/a&gt; about helping
birds.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Coleman</name></author><category term="Bloor-Yorkville 2017" /><category term="Urban Ecology" /><category term="Fatal Light Attraction" /><category term="Injured Birds" /><summary type="html">This article originally appeared on the Bloor-Yorkville BIA Blog</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://tallcoleman.me/assets/Images/IMG_1648-COLLAGE.jpg" /></entry></feed>